If your goal is to become financially
如果你的目标是实现财务自由
independent at a young age, this is a
年轻时就独立，这是一种
very controversial thing to say, you
这番话很有争议，你
probably don't want to go buy a house
可能不想买房
because people typically buy a house
因为人们通常会买房
they can't possibly afford. The bank
他们根本负担不起。银行
wants you to do that cuz that's how they
他们想让你这么做，因为他们就是这么做的。
make the most money. So, you're putting
赚取最多的钱。所以，你正在投入
your capital into that house and now
你把资金投入到那栋房子里，现在
it's not going to be earning thing. It's
这不会是个赚钱的办法。它是
going to be sitting idally. And people
坐姿非常理想。还有人
say, "Well, you know, I can buy this
我说，“嗯，你知道，我可以买这个
house cuz my mortgage is the same as my
房子，因为我的抵押贷款和我的房子一样多
rent." Well, yeah, but your mortgage is
租金。”嗯，是啊，但是你的房贷是
just the starting point. So, what comes
这只是起点。那么，接下来会发生什么呢？
to mind if I want to be financially
我介意自己是否想在经济上……
wealthy?
富裕？
&gt;&gt; Okay, so we've got a lot to go through.
好的，我们有很多事情要处理。
&gt;&gt; J Collins is a renowned financial expert
J·柯林斯是一位著名的金融专家
known for his book, The Simple Path to
因其著作《通往幸福的简单之路》而闻名
Wealth.
财富。
&gt;&gt; He's teaching millions a straightforward
他正在向数百万人传授一种简单易懂的方法。
and realistic avenue for achieving
实现这一目标的切实途径
wealth
财富
&gt;&gt; so that anyone can have financial
这样任何人都可以拥有经济能力。
security.
安全。
&gt;&gt; What is the simple path to wealth?
通往财富的简单途径是什么？
&gt;&gt; So, first of all, avoid debt because you
所以，首先，要避免负债，因为……
can never be financially independent if
如果
you're carrying around debt. Next, live
你背负着债务。接下来是直播
on less than you [music] earn. But the
收入比你（音乐人）赚的还少。但是
problem is the way our culture has
问题在于我们文化的方式……
taught us to think about money is solely
教会我们仅仅把金钱看作是
in terms of what can you buy with it.
就它能买到什么而言。
But the more musthaves you have in your
但是，你拥有的必备物品越多……
life, the less likely you are to become
生活，你越不可能成为
wealthy. And then the final one, invest
富裕。最后一点，投资
the surplus. So stocks are the single
盈余。所以股票是单一的
most effective, strongest wealth
最有效、最强大的财富
building tool that's ever been created.
有史以来最强大的建筑工具。
But the biggest push back I get is from
但我遇到的最大阻力来自
people who say, "Well, that's great. I
那些说“哦，那太好了”的人。
mean, if you got a big income, 100, 200,
意思是，如果你收入很高，100、200，
$300,000 a year, then yeah, the simple
年薪30万美元，那当然，就是这么简单。
path to wealth will work for you."
“致富之路终将对你奏效。”
That's not the truth. For instance, a
那不是事实。例如，
friend of mine and he was making a
我的一个朋友，他当时正在制作一个
million dollars a year and he was broke
他年收入百万美元，结果却破产了。
because people have large incomes are
因为人们收入很高
much more likely to be drawn into the
更容易被卷入
competing with the Joneses, whereas the
与琼斯一家竞争，而
people who make less money probably
收入较低的人可能
don't have those same social pressures
没有同样的社会压力
and are more readily able to do it. So,
而且他们更容易做到这一点。所以，
&gt;&gt; let's talk about investing then. Where
那我们来聊聊投资吧。在哪里
do you think we should be investing our
你认为我们应该投资吗？
money at this moment of time? Should I
此时此刻，钱呢？我应该吗？
buy Bitcoin? Do I need a financial
购买比特币？我需要财务方面的帮助吗？
adviser? So, my advice, and this is a
顾问？所以，我的建议是，这是……
little different than the more common
与常见的略有不同
advice out there, would be
目前的建议是……
&gt;&gt; this has always blown my mind a little
这件事一直让我有点难以置信。
bit. 53% of you that listen to this show
少量。 53% 的听众收听了这个节目
regularly haven't yet subscribed to the
经常还没有订阅
show. So, could I ask you for a favor
展示。所以，我能请你帮个忙吗？
before we start? If you like the show
开始之前？如果你喜欢这个节目
and you like what we do here and you
你喜欢我们在这里做的事情，你
want to support us, the free simple way
想支持我们吗？免费又简单的方式！
that you can do just that is by hitting
你可以通过点击来做到这一点。
the subscribe button. And my commitment
订阅按钮。我的承诺
to you is if you do that, then I'll do
对你来说，如果你那样做，那么我也会那样做。
everything in my power, me and my team,
我和我的团队将竭尽全力
to make sure that this show is better
为了确保这个节目更好
for you every single week. We'll listen
每周都为您准备。我们会听的。
to your feedback. We'll find the guest
感谢您的反馈。我们会找到那位客人。
that you want me to speak to and we'll
你想让我跟谁谈谈，我们……
continue to do what we do. Thank you so
继续做我们正在做的事情。非常感谢
much.
很多。
[music and singing]
[音乐和歌唱]
JL Collins,
JL Collins，
you wrote a book, a very iconic book
你写了一本书，一本非常经典的书。
that sold millions of copies called The
那本销量数百万册的书叫做《
Simple Path to Wealth. Why did you write
通往财富的简单途径。你为什么写
this book?
这本书？
&gt;&gt; I actually that book was an outgrowth of
实际上，那本书是……的衍生作品。
my blog.
我的博客。
I started the blog to archive
我创建这个博客是为了存档。
information I wanted my daughter to have
我希望女儿掌握的信息
available because if you get money
之所以能获得资金，是因为如果你有钱的话。
right, your life is so much better. You
没错，你的生活好多了。你
have so many more options. And the world
选择更多了。以及世界
offers so much to people who have the
为拥有……的人们提供了很多
resources with which to access it and so
获取资源等等
little for those people who don't have
对于那些没有……的人来说，这几乎没什么用。
the resources to access those things.
获取这些资源的途径。
And and if you don't have it, it life is
如果你没有它，生活就完了。
just so much harder than it than it
比这难得多
needs to be.
必须如此。
&gt;&gt; When you think about the average person
当你想到普通人时
listening right now, what is what are
我现在正在听，这是什么？
some of the fundamental sort of
一些基本的
misconceptions or misunderstandings or
误解或误会或
what would you call it? Black spots that
你会怎么称呼它？黑点
they have as it relates to money, the
就金钱而言，他们拥有……
things they walk around assuming about
他们四处走动，想当然地认为……
money that are incorrect
错误的货币
&gt;&gt; that that you were maybe trying to get
你或许是想得到
out of your daughter's mind.
简直疯了，你女儿都看不下去了。
&gt;&gt; Right? So there's a chapter in the book
正确的？所以，书中有一章是这样的。
called how to think about money. And the
名为“如何看待金钱”。以及
fundamental way I think the vast
我认为，从根本上来说，广阔的
majority of people think about money
大多数人都在考虑金钱问题。
because this is what our culture has
因为这就是我们文化所拥有的。
taught us. The way our culture has
教导了我们。我们的文化方式
taught us to think about money is solely
教会我们仅仅把金钱看作是
in terms of what can you buy with it.
就它能买到什么而言。
[snorts] So if you go to the average
[嗤笑] 所以如果你去平均
person that lottery for instance is like
例如，彩票就像……
a billion dollars at the moment. So
目前价值十亿美元。所以
people are buying lottery tickets. And
人们正在购买彩票。和
if you interviewed people standing in
如果你采访那些站在……的人
line to buy lottery tickets and said,
排队买彩票时，他说：
"Okay, if you win this million dollar,
“好的，如果你赢得了这100万美元，
what are you going to do with it?" Well,
你打算怎么处理它？嗯，
what you're typically going to hear is,
你通常会听到的是：
"Well, I'm going to pay off my debts and
“嗯，我要还清我的债务。”
I'm going to pay off my mortgage and I'm
我打算还清房贷，而且我
going to buy my parents a house and I'm
我打算给父母买套房子，我是
going to buy myself a Lamborghini. I'm
我打算给自己买辆兰博基尼。我是
going to buy I'm going to buy I'm going
我要去买，我要去买。
to buy." That's the way most people
去买。”大多数人都是这么做的。
think about money. And that's certainly
想想钱的事。那当然是
one of the things that money is very
金钱的一大特点是……
good at. It is a means of exchange.
擅长。它是一种交换媒介。
But the other thing your money can do
但你的钱还能做的另一件事是……
for you is work for you. Your money can
对你来说，工作就是为你而做。你的钱可以
make you more money. So you can exchange
帮你赚更多钱。所以你可以交换
your time and effort and labor to earn
你投入的时间、精力和劳动来赚取
money. And that's what most of us do.
钱。而这正是我们大多数人所做的。
But you can also divert some of the
但你也可以转移一部分
money you earn into investments into
你赚的钱用于投资
what I call buying your freedom. And now
我称之为用金钱换取自由。现在
your money is working for you. So
你的钱正在为你赚钱。所以
instead of just thinking about what your
而不是仅仅思考你的
money can buy, you can start thinking
金钱能买到的东西，你就可以开始思考了。
about what can your money earn.
了解你的钱能赚多少钱。
&gt;&gt; You can buy your freedom.
你可以用金钱买到自由。
&gt;&gt; You can buy your freedom, your financial
你可以用金钱买到自由和财务自由。
freedom.
自由。
&gt;&gt; Why is that an important refraraming of
为什么这是一个重要的重新表述？
the role of money in your view? What
您认为金钱扮演着怎样的角色？什么
does that do if I start thinking about
如果我开始思考……会怎么样？
it through that lens? Well, because as
透过那个镜头看？嗯，因为作为
long as you are dependent on exchanging
只要你依赖于外汇交易
your effort, time, and labor for money,
你付出的努力、时间和劳动换取了金钱，
you are beholden to whoever is willing
你要对任何愿意帮助你的人负责。
to pay you to do that. That's a limit of
付钱让你做这件事。这是极限
freedom. It's a it's a form of, without
自由。它是一种形式，没有
being too dramatic, a form of slavery.
过于戏剧化，这是一种奴役形式。
If you are always living paycheck to
如果你总是月光族
paycheck to pay the mortgage or the rent
用工资支付房贷或房租
or whatever, if on the other hand, work
或者不管怎样，另一方面，工作
is optional, you're a good example. and
这是可选的，你就是一个很好的例子。和
you've been a very successful guy.
你一直都很成功。
[snorts]
[嗤笑]
You're not doing this podcast because
你做这个播客不是因为
you need the money. If you were still
你需要这笔钱。如果你仍然
stuck at a job that paid you a wage, you
你困在一份只能挣工资的工作中，你
wouldn't have the option to do this
没有这样的选择。
because you'd have to devote all your
因为你必须投入所有的
time to that job so you could pay the
需要时间去上班，这样你才能付得起工资。
mortgage, so you could pay the rent, so
还房贷，这样你就能付房租了。
you could put food on the table. Money
你可以养家糊口。钱
buys freedom.
换取自由。
&gt;&gt; How does one get out of that situation?
如何才能摆脱这种困境？
you know, if I I used to work in call
你知道，如果我以前在电话公司工作的话
centers um answering phones and selling
中心负责接听电话和销售
people things.
人事。
&gt;&gt; How does one in your view realistically
在你看来，现实中一个人该如何……
get from that place where you are kind
从你友善的地方离开
of beholden to the paycheck? And I was
受制于薪水？而我当时
I'd spend my wage within the first week
我第一周就把工资花光了。
or so of the month and then I'd just
大概一个月左右，然后我就……
suffer for the next 3 weeks. In the UK,
接下来的三周将饱受煎熬。在英国，
we have like a four week paying cycle. I
我们的付款周期大概是四周。我
think in the US it's 2 weeks typically,
在美国，通常需要两周时间。
but I took a I think a reckless road out
但我选择了一条我认为很鲁莽的路。
of that life. The thing that gave me the
那段人生。给我带来
proclivity to take the risk is like some
冒险倾向就像某些
kind of insecurity and trauma where like
某种不安全感和创伤，就像
I couldn't I didn't have a plan B
我做不到，我没有备用方案。
because I wanted to be I wanted to like
因为我想成为那样的人，我想喜欢那样的人。
validate myself or something. And so I
证明自己之类的。所以，我
wonder if the the skill or the thing
不知道是技能还是东西
that I was given that I'm most thankful
我最感激的是别人给予我的这些。
for is like some kind of chip on my
对我来说，这就像我身上的某种芯片。
shoulder,
肩膀，
&gt;&gt; some kind of drama.
某种戏剧。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. But but on genuinely because I
是的。但是，真的，因为我
think like what would make you take a
想想什么会让你采取
risk like some of the risks that I took
风险，比如我承担的一些风险。
to leave university to then like be be
离开大学，然后就像……
broke and I was like, well, I just I was
我当时破产了，我就想，好吧，我当时就是
driven I was dragged by some kind of
我被某种东西拖着走
trauma.
创伤。
&gt;&gt; Right? One of the things that I've
正确的？其中一件我……
observed, and I think to the extent that
观察到，我认为在某种程度上，
I've had some success in my life, this
我的人生取得了一些成功，这
is true, that successful people do tend
没错，成功人士确实倾向于
to have trauma in their background. At
他们有过创伤经历。在
least that's my observation. Now, I'm
至少我是这么认为的。现在，我是
sure there are exceptions to that, but
当然也有例外，但是……
it does seem that people like us are
看来像我们这样的人确实
striving to overcome
努力克服
those past traumas, to have that chip on
那些过去的创伤，就像被烙上了印记。
the shoulder, to prove something.
肩膀，是为了证明些什么。
I've also met people who are very
我也遇到过一些非常
content to be completely lacking in
内容完全缺乏
ambition
志向
and to have enough to have a comfortable
并且拥有足够的钱，过上舒适的生活。
life and kind of do what they want to do
过着这样的生活，做着他们想做的事。
to have financial independence maybe but
或许是为了经济独立，但
they don't have this drive to be
他们没有这种动力。
successful to to make a mark on on the
成功地在……上留下印记
world and they tend to have had better
世界，而且他们往往拥有更好的未来。
childhoods and and uh and I think that
童年，还有，嗯，我觉得
there is that wasn't me. That doesn't
那不是我。那不是
appear to be you. But I think there's a
看起来像你。但我认为存在一种
lot to be said for for that, right?
这确实有很多值得称道的地方，对吧？
&gt;&gt; You I mean you open the book about
你，我的意思是，你打开那本书……
talking about a parable of the monk
谈论僧侣的寓言
&gt;&gt; and the minister
以及部长
&gt;&gt; and the minister.
还有部长。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Can you uh tell me about that parable
你能跟我说说那个寓言故事吗？
because it seems to somewhat relate to
因为它似乎与此有些关联
what we're seeing here. I think
我们现在看到的。我认为
&gt;&gt; very very much so and that's the reason
确实如此，这就是原因。
I open the book with it. So the parable
我用它打开了这本​​书。所以这个寓言
is there are these uh two boys who grew
是不是有两个男孩长大了？
up together. their childhood friends. As
一起起来。他们的儿时好友。作为
frequently happens, they go their
经常发生这种情况，他们会去他们的
different directions in life as they
人生走向不同的方向，因为他们
become adults. And one becomes a very
长大成人。而一个人会变得非常
successful, powerful minister to the
成功、有权势的部长
king, and the other becomes a humble
国王，另一个则成了谦卑的人。
monk in tattered robes with a begging
身穿破烂僧袍的僧侣乞讨
bowl and what have you. And years later,
碗之类的东西。多年以后，
they run into each other on the road.
他们在路上偶遇。
And they're getting reacquainted.
他们正在重新熟悉起来。
And as they are, the minister, the king,
而他们现在的样子，大臣，国王，
takes pity on on his povertystricken
怜悯他那贫困潦倒的……
friend and his tattered robes. And he
朋友和他破烂的袍子。而他
says, 'You know, if you could learn to
他说，“你知道，如果你能学会……”
cater to the king, you wouldn't have to
讨好国王，你就不必……
live on rice and beans. To which the
靠米饭和豆子过日子。其中
monk replies, if you could learn to live
僧侣回答说，如果你能学会生活
on rice and beans,
米饭和豆子
you wouldn't have to cater to the king.
你无需讨好国王。
And for me, I've always been a little
对我来说，我一直有点
bit more towards the monk side. I'm uh
更偏向僧侣的一面。我呃
I'm not a very materialistic person, and
我不是一个很物质的人，而且
I'm comfortable and able to get along on
我感觉很自在，也能与人相处融洽
on very little. And I think there's
花费很少。我觉得有。
something beautiful about needing less.
需求越少，越美好。
&gt;&gt; I have from my interviews met people who
通过我的采访，我遇到了一些……
are very wealthy, even actually off
他们非常富有，甚至实际上已经破产了。
camera,
相机，
&gt;&gt; who are very, very wealthy and appear to
他们非常非常富有，而且看起来
be happy. Yes.
要开心。是的。
&gt;&gt; But I think I I think it's safe to say
但我认为，可以肯定地说
that the richest people I know are
我认识的最富有的人是
amongst the least happy people I know.
我认识的人当中，我算是最不快乐的人之一。
So if I think about the very top, the
所以，如果我考虑最顶端，
billionaires that I know off camera,
我私下认识的亿万富翁们，
&gt;&gt; they are amongst the least happy
他们是幸福感最低的人群之一。
typically.
通常。
&gt;&gt; Mhm. Um because I think whatever's taken
嗯。嗯，因为我觉得不管发生了什么。
them there is still haunting them while
那里仍然萦绕着他们，而
they're there. So it could be the chip
它们就在那里。所以，问题可能出在芯片上。
on the shoulder, the insecurity,
肩膀上，是不安。
whatever happened to them that made them
无论他们身上发生了什么事，使他们变成了他们
so driven and obsessed with validation
如此执着于获得认可，如此痴迷于此。
and climbing is still haunting them now.
登山这件事至今仍困扰着他们。
But I do also I do know people like I
但我确实也认识一些像我这样的人。
say that are very very rich and that
他们说自己非常非常富有，而且
live remarkably content lives. And I
过着非常满足的生活。我
think part of it is their relationship
我认为部分原因是他们的关系。
with the stuff. Like I think it is
和那些东西。就像我想的那样
possible
可能的
&gt;&gt; and they probably keep it at arms
他们很可能把它当作武器收藏。
length, right? They're a little psychic
长度，对吧？他们有点通灵能力。
distance from the stuff.
与物品保持距离。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And I just speaking from my own
是的。我只是就我个人而言。
journey at a very young age up until the
从很小的时候就开始了这段旅程，直到……
age of 25, I was convinced that buying a
25岁那年，我确信购买
Range Rover Sport was going to like
路虎揽胜运动版本来会很受欢迎
really make me really happy. And um the
真的让我非常开心。嗯……
anti-limax once I I got those things was
一旦我拿到那些东西，就变成了抗利马斯。
was like it was staggering. It was a
简直令人震惊。那是一个
complete
完全的
&gt;&gt; mental it was like someone had shaken my
精神上，感觉就像有人摇晃了我的身体。
head. My reality distorted for a second
头。我的现实感在那一瞬间扭曲了。
because I thought this was meant to be
因为我觉得这是命中注定的
it.
它。
&gt;&gt; And now I can still get things that I
现在我仍然可以得到我想要的东西
like. But um I was saying to Will the
喜欢。但是，嗯，我是在跟威尔说……
other day that when I walked into my new
前几天，当我走进我的新家时……
house in LA um I had pre-repped myself
我在洛杉矶的房子，嗯，我已经提前准备好了。
to know that it was going to have zero
知道它将为零
impact on my happiness and that meant
对我的幸福感的影响，这意味着
that I actually enjoyed it weirdly.
奇怪的是，我竟然还挺喜欢的。
&gt;&gt; Right.
正确的。
&gt;&gt; Like I was actually super grateful
我真的非常感激
because I'd pre-repped myself to have a
因为我已经提前做好了准备，要有
healthier relationship with the thing
与事物建立更健康的关系
&gt;&gt; to bring the expectation down.
降低预期。
&gt;&gt; Exactly.
确切地。
&gt;&gt; So there are a couple things at play
所以，这里有几个因素在起作用。
there. I think one is it's the journey
那里。我认为其中一点是，这是一段旅程。
that's really satisfying.
这真让人感到满足。
&gt;&gt; The destination tends to be less so. And
目的地往往不太如此。和
I think that's one of the problems with
我认为这是问题之一
being very materialistic because you
你非常物质主义，因为你
know if your definition of happiness is
了解你对幸福的定义是否是
if I only owned this watch, right? If I
如果我拥有这块手表就好了，对吧？如果我
only had this watch maker make me this
我只让这位钟表匠给我做了这个
intricate watch, then I would be happy.
如果是精密的腕表，我就很开心了。
Well, I mean maybe, but probably not.
嗯，我的意思是，也许吧，但可能性不大。
You're probably going to have that
你很可能会遇到这种情况。
watch. You're going to look at it and
手表。你会去看它，然后
say, "That's really nice. Wow, that's
比如说，“那真不错。哇，那真……”
good." And it'll and then well, what's
很好。”然后，嗯，接下来会怎样呢？
next? But if you enjoy the journey or
下一个？但如果你喜欢这段旅程，或者
and I think you made a very wise
我认为你做出了一个非常明智的决定。
decision if you reset your expectations
如果你重新调整预期，就会做出决定
and say, you know, I'm going to have
然后说，你知道，我打算……
this nice house or this nice watch, but
这栋漂亮的房子或者这块漂亮的手表，但是
I don't expect it to make me happy, but
我不指望它能让我快乐，但是
it's going to be a nice thing to have in
拥有它将是一件很不错的事。
in my life.
在我的生活中。
&gt;&gt; And somebody once said much wiser than
有人曾说过，比这明智得多
me, you know, money doesn't change who
你知道，对我来说，金钱改变不了什么。
you are. It it can magnify who you are.
你是。它可以放大你的个人特质。
So if you're an unhappy person and
所以，如果你是一个不快乐的人，
you're have lots of money, you will
如果你有很多钱，你就会
probably still be an unhappy person.
可能仍然会是一个不快乐的人。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; Uh if you're a happy person, I mean, one
呃，如果你是一个快乐的人，我的意思是，一个
of the happy, in fact, the single
事实上，快乐的人，单身人士
happiest guy I know. His life was the
我认识的最快乐的人。他的一生是
biggest financial disaster of anybody I
这是我经历过的最严重的财务灾难。
personally know. And this guy's he's the
我个人认识。而这个人，他就是……
literally the happiest human being I've
我见过的最快乐的人，没有之一。
ever met.
从未见过。
&gt;&gt; Cuz he was happy before.
因为他之前很开心。
&gt;&gt; Because he was happy before. And there's
因为他以前很快乐。还有……
other things besides money that makes
除了金钱之外的其他因素也能带来收益。
you happy. Money. And the reason that I
你开心。钱。而我的理由是……
I it was so important to me to teach my
对我来说，教导我的孩子们是如此重要。
daughter this, money gives you options,
女儿，金钱能给你更多选择。
right? Money allows you a lot wider
正确的？金钱能让你拥有更广阔的视野。
range of choices in life,
人生中的选择范围
but it doesn't necessarily make you
但这并不一定意味着你
happy, right? If it allows you to pursue
开心吧？如果它允许你追求
an option
一个选项
that otherwise you couldn't pursue and
否则你就无法继续下去了。
that option makes you happy, that's a
那个选择让你感到快乐，那就是
different thing. I think if I was
完全是两码事。我想如果我是
listening to this and I was broke, like
听着这些歌，我当时身无分文，就像
I used to be very broke, I would still
我以前很穷，但我仍然
pursue wealth at all costs because I
不惜一切代价追求财富，因为我
know I heard this phrase the other day
我知道我前几天听到过这句话。
which was it is easier to get rich than
哪一种更容易致富
it is to give up the idea that getting
放弃获得的想法。
rich will make you happy. And I
富有会让你快​​乐。我
[laughter] I thought to myself,
[笑声] 我心想，
&gt;&gt; and if you haven't got rich, you would
如果你还没发财，你就会
always think
总是想
&gt;&gt; 100%. You'd always wonder if that was
100%。你总会想知道那是不是……
And you know what? So much of the
你知道吗？很多
unhappiness or anxiety that I had when I
当我感到不快乐或焦虑时
was, you know, in my early early innings
你知道，那是在我职业生涯的早期阶段。
of my life, my career came from looking
我的人生，我的事业，都源于观察。
down and seeing the baiff letters or
向下看，看到贝夫的信件或
came from the credit card debt or how am
源于信用卡债务还是其他什么原因？
I going to eat today or, you know, can't
我今天要么吃东西，要么就吃不上。
go out and see my friends. So much of my
出去见见我的朋友们。我的很多
mind was occupied by my inability to
我的思绪被我无法做到的事情所占据。
have freedom,
拥有自由，
&gt;&gt; right? my lack of freedom, my need to
正确的？我缺乏自由，我需要
get up at 8:00 and walk for an hour and
早上8点起床，步行一小时
a half to a call center was, you know,
半个呼叫中心，你知道的，
so what I managed to remove was that I
所以我设法删除的是我
wouldn't say I I added happiness, but I
我不会说我增添了快乐，但是
removed the unhappiness.
消除了不快乐。
&gt;&gt; Well, and that's a that's a key point.
嗯，这可是个关键点。
You know, money doesn't necessarily make
你知道，金钱并不一定能带来收益。
you happy, but the lack of money.
你很开心，但是缺钱。
&gt;&gt; Oh, yeah.
哦，是的。
&gt;&gt; Can be terrible challenge, especially in
这可能是一个巨大的挑战，尤其是在
this modern culture we've created.
我们创造的这种现代文化。
&gt;&gt; Okay. So, if you have kids listening
好的。所以，如果你有孩子在听
right now, please cover their ears cuz
现在，请捂住他们的耳朵，因为
I'm going to say a swear word. Parents
我要说一句脏话。父母
always message me and ask me to stop
总是给我发信息，让我停止
swearing. going to say well um a lot of
咒骂。嗯，很多
people are obsessed with this idea of
人们对这个想法非常着迷
[__] you money
去你的钱
&gt;&gt; right
正确的
&gt;&gt; let me just give you a definition so fu
让我给你解释一下“fu”的定义。
money refers to a financial situation
金钱指的是一种财务状况。
where a person has enough money to live
一个人有足够的钱生活的地方
comfortably without needing to work and
无需工作就能舒适地生活
it gives you the freedom to say f you to
它赋予你对……说“去你的”的自由
anyone or anything you don't want to
你不想让任何人或任何事
tolerate such as a job a boss or a
容忍，例如工作、老板或
situation that doesn't align with your
这种情况与你的预期不符
values what does that mean to you
价值观对你来说意味着什么？
&gt;&gt; yeah so for me so that's a good
是的，对我来说，这是个好消息。
definition but I would substitute in
定义，但我会用……代替
that definition financial independence
财务独立的定义
FU money for me is the money you
对我来说，FU 钱就是你给我的钱。
accumulate on the way, right? So, for
一路积累下来，对吧？所以，对于
instance, if you're a bodybuilder,
例如，如果你是一名健美运动员，
you know, financial independence is when
你知道，财务独立是指……
you're on the stage and you're winning,
你站在舞台上，而且你赢了。
you're at the elite level. But along the
你已经达到了精英水平。但沿着
way, from the moment you start working
从你开始工作的那一刻起，就一直如此。
out, you get a little bit stronger, a
出去走走，你会变得更强壮一些，
little bit stronger, a little bit
稍微强一点，一点点
stronger, right? Same thing financially.
更强，对吧？财务方面也是如此。
The moment you start setting aside money
当你开始存钱的那一刻
and investing it, you become a little
投资之后，你会变得有点
bit financially stronger. And that
经济实力略有增强。而那
builds over time. That in my mind is the
随着时间的推移而形成。在我看来，那就是
FU money because long before you're
去他妈的钱，因为在你……之前很久
financially independent, that money
经济独立，那笔钱
gives you enormous freedom. You might
赋予你极大的自由。你可能
not be able to never work again, but if
并非永远无法再工作，而是如果
you need to, you could leave a toxic job
你需要这么做，你可以离开一份糟糕的工作。
knowing you could survive for months or
知道自己可以生存数月或
even years while you looked for the
即使你寻找了好几年
better job because you have that FU
因为你拥有那份FU，所以工作更好了。
money. So it allows you to say f you in
钱。所以它允许你骂人。
that case to an employer.
将此案提交给雇主。
&gt;&gt; And if your daughter daughter turned
如果你的女儿变成了……
around, what's her name?
她叫什么名字？
&gt;&gt; Jessica.
杰西卡。
&gt;&gt; Jessica. If Jessica turns around to you
杰西卡。如果杰西卡转过身来面对你
and says, "Dad, what are what is
然后说：“爸爸，什么是……
something I should not do with my money
我不应该用我的钱做这件事。
if I
如果我
um want to be wealthy?
你想变得富有吗？
What is what are like the big what is
什么是大的？
the first thing that comes to mind to as
首先想到的就是……
a no no if I want to be financially
如果我想在经济上取得成功，这是绝对不行的。
wealthy?"
富裕？”
The mo more common advice that I think
我认为最常见的建议是……
you should avoid if your goal is to
如果你的目标是……，你应该避免这样做。
become financially independent at a
在某个阶段实现经济独立
young age. You probably don't want to go
年轻。你可能不想去
buy a house.
买房。
That's a very controversial thing to
那是一件极具争议的事情。
say. The reason you want buy a house is
说。你想买房的原因是
because houses dramatically inflate by
因为房价会大幅上涨
and large your cost of living. You know,
并大幅增加你的生活成本。你知道，
you're you're putting your capital into
你正在把你的资金投入到
that house and now it's not going to be
那栋房子，现在不会再有了。
earning thing. can be sitting idally
赚钱的事。可以处于理想位置
along with owning a house. You have the
以及拥有一套房子。你有
expenses of maintaining it, paying the
维护费用，支付
taxes on it, blah blah blah. If you stay
税收等等等等。如果你留下
in a apartment that is just enough to
住在一间刚好够用的公寓里
meet your needs, which by the way is
满足您的需求，顺便说一句，这
what my daughter has done and continues
我女儿过去和现在所做的一切
to do, your costs will be lower.
这样做，你的成本会更低。
&gt;&gt; Explain that to me. Explain why my cost
请你给我解释一下。解释一下我的费用为什么
of living goes up if I buy a house.
如果我买房，生活成本就会增加。
&gt;&gt; Sure. So people, it doesn't have to, but
当然。所以各位，这并非必须，但是……
people people typically buy the most
人们通常购买最多的
house they can possibly afford. The
他们能负担得起的房子。这
industry drives them that way. If you go
行业因素驱使他们这样做。如果你去
to a real estate agent, you say, "I
你对房地产经纪人说：“我
think I'm I want to buy a house." Right?
我想买套房子。对吧？
First question they're going to ask you
他们要问你的第一个问题是什么？
is, "How much do you make? How much do
就是，“你挣多少钱？你挣多少钱？”
you want to spend?" You know, and and
你想花钱吗？你知道，还有
then you go to the bank and you say,
然后你去银行说，
"Okay, I want to buy a house. How much
“好的，我想买房子。多少钱？”
will you lend me?" And they'll say,
你们愿意借给我吗？”他们会说，
"Well, how much you make?" And then
“那你收入多少？”进而
they'll come back with the large number
他们会带着大量人员回来。
of how much they're willing to lend you.
他们愿意借给你多少钱。
If you follow those guidelines, you're
如果你遵循这些准则，你
going to wind up with a house that's
最终会得到一套房子
going to be a burden. You are not buying
将会成为负担。你不买
it from a position of strength. You are
从优势地位发起进攻。你是
stretching to buy it. You are borrowing
费尽心思才买到它。您正在借款
the most money a bank's willing to give
银行愿意提供的最大金额
you. You probably don't want to do that.
你。你可能不想那样做。
I mean, you can, that's the bank wants
我的意思是，你可以这么做，银行也希望如此。
you to do that cuz [clears throat]
你得这么做，因为[清嗓子]
that's how they make the most money, but
这是他们赚钱最多的途径，但是
that's not the best thing for you to do.
这样做对你来说不是最好的选择。
But that's what you get drawn into. And
但你就是这样一步步被卷入其中的。和
then when you buy that house, I don't
等你买了那栋房子，我就不买了。
know that I've ever known anybody,
我知道我认识的任何人，
including me, by the way, and I've owned
顺便说一句，也包括我，而且我曾经拥有过。
houses most of my adult life, who's
我成年后的大部分时间都住在这所房子里，那是谁？
owned a house without doing renovations
拥有一套房子却没进行过装修
on it. So, you've got those costs.
就在上面。所以，这些成本都需要考虑。
You're going to furnish that house cuz
你要布置那栋房子，因为
you're probably buying more square
你可能买的是更多方形产品。
footage than you were renting before.
比你以前租的影片要好。
You're going to need new furniture, or
你需要添置一些新家具，或者
maybe you just want better furniture for
或许你只是想要更好的家具。
your new house, maybe new appliances,
你的新房子，或许还有新的家电，
landscaping, taxes, maintenance. I mean,
景观设计、税费、维护。我是说，
the the list is endless. And people say,
这样的例子不胜枚举。人们说，
"Well, you know, I can buy this house,
“嗯，你知道，我可以买下这栋房子，”
and my mortgage is the same as my rent."
我的房贷和房租一样多。
Well, yeah, but your mortgage is just
嗯，是啊，但是你的房贷只是
the starting point. You've got all these
起点。你拥有所有这些
other expenses with the house. And the
与房屋相关的其他费用。以及
other thing is they are variable
另一点是，它们是可变的。
expenses.
开支。
&gt;&gt; Variable expenses.
可变费用。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. With your rent, you know, if if
是的。你知道，如果你要交房租的话……
you're renting an apartment, you're
你租了一套公寓，你是
paying $2,500 a month for your
每月支付 2,500 美元
apartment, right? you know exactly what
是公寓，对吧？你很清楚这一点。
your housing costs are for the term of
您的住房费用涵盖整个租期
your lease, right? $500 a month. If you
你的租约是这样的，对吧？每月500美元。如果你
own a house, maybe your mortgage is
如果你拥有一套房子，也许你的抵押贷款是
$2,500 a month. And then you need a new
每月2500美元。然后你就需要一个新的
roof. That's 20 grand. Or you need a new
屋顶。那是两万美元。或者你需要一个新的
septic system, which by the way, I'm
化粪池系统，顺便说一句，我是
looking at having to put it in my
看着不得不把它放进我的
cottage, you know. Well, that's another
你知道，就是那种小屋。嗯，那是另一个故事了。
25 grand, right? And so, and you don't
2.5万美元，对吧？所以，你不会
necessarily know when those things are
未必知道这些事情何时发生
going to come at you.
他会来找你。
&gt;&gt; It is a bit of a trap, isn't it? It's a
这有点像个陷阱，不是吗？这是一个
trap that um I didn't realize this until
陷阱，嗯，我之前没意识到这一点。
I bought a house and most people don't
我买了房子，而大多数人没有。
&gt;&gt; like I even sit here on this podcast
就像我坐在这里听这个播客一样。
doing this for a living and then I I
我以此为生，然后我
made this stupid mistake of buying a
我犯了个愚蠢的错误，买了一个
house and I do think it was a stupid
房子，而且我觉得那是个愚蠢的房子
mistake because I we'll talk about
错误，因为我们会谈谈
opportunity cost in a second but I was
机会成本在一秒钟之内，但我当时
in hindsight it was like a terrible
事后看来，这就像一场可怕的
decision. I spent all this money on this
决定。我把这些钱都花在这上面了。
house. It was a house abroad. It was
房子。那是一栋海外的房子。那是
also like a holiday home I guess
感觉也像个度假屋一样。
&gt;&gt; and every time I come all I see is
每次我来这里，看到的都是
things that I need to change.
我需要改变的事情。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. It's looking at the United States
是的。它关注的是美国
for instance, if 20 years ago, 30 years
例如，如果20年前，30年前
ago, you'd bought a house in San
几年前，你在圣路易斯买了一栋房子。
Francisco,
弗朗西斯科
well, you've done very, very well
嗯，你做得非常非常好。
financially. If you bought a house in
经济方面。如果你在……买了一套房子
Detroit,
底特律，
not so much. So then the question
不多。那么问题来了
becomes, and people will say, well,
变得如此，人们会说，好吧，
obviously you don't buy a house in
显然你不会在……买房
Detroit, you buy a house in San
底特律，你在圣路易斯买房
Francisco. Well, I'm not an expert in
弗朗西斯科。嗯，我不是这方面的专家。
real estate, but I am reading more and
虽然我主要从事房地产行业，但我正在阅读更多相关书籍。
more commonly that San Francisco is has
更常见的情况是，旧金山有
a lot of very challenging problems at
很多极具挑战性的问题
the moment. Detroit, on the other hand,
那一刻。而底特律则恰恰相反，
where I was just visiting a couple of
我当时只是去拜访几个人。
years ago, is enjoying a renaissance.
几年前，它正在经历复兴。
Detroit's coming back. So, who's to say
底特律要复兴了。所以，谁又能说得准呢？
in 20, 30 years, people won't be saying,
20年、30年后，人们就不会再说这句话了。
"If you bought in Detroit back in 2025,
“如果你在2025年在底特律买了房，
you were golden." And if you bought San
你真是太棒了。” 如果你买了桑
Francisco, yeah, not so much. Sometimes
弗朗西斯科，嗯，不太像。有时
real estate, buying a house can work out
房地产，买房可能会成功
in a spectacular fashion. And that's the
以一种惊人的方式。就是这样。
stories people tend to hear, but not
人们经常听到的故事，但并非如此。
always.
总是。
&gt;&gt; And that's what I tend to see in the
这就是我经常在……中看到的。
comment section when we talk about this
当我们在评论区讨论这个问题时
issue of buying a house. I was just
买房问题。我当时只是
looking at the comment section actually.
我正在看评论区。
And on a previous conversation where we
在之前的一次谈话中，我们
talked about whether you should buy a
讨论了你是否应该购买
house, someone said, "I bought a house
有人说：“我买了一栋房子。”
and it's the best thing I ever did."
这是我做过的最棒的事。
Right? It's launched my mindset in new
正确的？它开启了我全新的思维模式。
directions. Remember that having your
方向。记住，拥有你的
own space has profound psychological
自己的空间具有深刻的心理意义。
impacts and can be life-changing for
影响深远，甚至可能改变人生。
some of that don't live in a healthy
有些生命并不健康
environment. The psychological impact of
环境。心理影响
buying a house.
买房。
&gt;&gt; What that commenter just said is is can
那位评论者刚才说的是可以
be and for him obviously it's absolutely
对他来说，这显然是绝对的。
true.
真的。
I am not anti- house. As I mentioned a
我并不反对房屋。正如我提到的……
moment ago, I've owned houses most of my
就在刚才，我大部分时间都拥有自己的房子。
adult life, but I've never bought them
成年生活，但我从未买过它们
because I thought they were an
因为我以为他们是
investment. I bought them because I
投资。我买它们是因为我
thought they would enhance my life in a
我原以为它们能提升我的生活品质。
way I wanted it enhanced. They would
按照我想要的方式进行增强。他们会
make my life better. They are in my view
让我的生活变得更好。在我看来，他们是……
an expensive indulgence. I have nothing
昂贵的享受。我什么都没有
against expensive indulgences. That's
反对奢侈消费。那是
one of the reasons we accumulate money,
我们积累财富的原因之一，
right? I like some expensive and some I
正确的？我喜欢一些昂贵的，也喜欢一些我
don't care about, some I like. Um, but
我不在乎，有些我喜欢。嗯，但是
that's what they are. And if you can
它们就是这样。如果你能
easily afford it, then by all means buy
如果经济条件允许，那就一定要买。
the house. Looking at some stats here,
房子。这里有一些统计数据，
it says home buying was once a solid
报告称，购房曾经是一项稳健的生意。
investment due to rising property values
由于房地产价值上涨而进行的投资
and lower mortgage rates. However, for
以及更低的抵押贷款利率。然而，对于
younger generations, this is no longer
年轻一代，这种情况已经不再存在了。
the case because of skyrocketing home
这种情况是因为房价飙升
prices. Since 1980, US home prices have
价格。自 1980 年以来，美国房价一直
increased by over 300%, outpacing
增长超过300%，超过了预期。
inflation and wage growth. In 2023,
通货膨胀和工资增长。 2023年，
mortgage rates surged past 7%, making
抵押贷款利率飙升至7%以上，使得
monthly payments significantly higher
月供显著增加
than before. And medium wages have only
比以前更糟。而中等工资只有
risen by about 15% since year the year
自上一年以来上涨了约15%。
2000. While home prices have more than
2000年。虽然房价已经上涨超过
doubled, making home ownership less
翻了一番，使得房屋拥有率下降
affordable. And lastly, the cost of
价格实惠。最后，还有成本
renting is often cheaper than buying,
租房通常比买房便宜。
especially in cities where prices have
尤其是在物价高昂的城市
outpaced wage growth, leading many
工资增长速度超过工资增长速度，领先于许多
younger people to choose renting for
年轻人选择租房
flexibility. This point of flexibility
灵活性。这一点灵活性
as well is one we don't talk about.
还有一个我们不愿提及的话题。
&gt;&gt; Right.
正确的。
&gt;&gt; Which is the ability to go do something
也就是去做某事的能力。
else in another country.
否则，在另一个国家。
&gt;&gt; Exactly.
确切地。
&gt;&gt; And my brother said this to me when I
我哥哥当时对我说了这些话
was 20. My brother's very smart. He's a
我当时20岁。我哥哥非常聪明。他是一个
year older than me, a financial genius,
比我大一岁，是一位金融天才
and has a much different brain to mine.
他的大脑和我的大脑截然不同。
And I remember when I was 20, maybe 24
我记得我20岁，或者24岁的时候。
and I was talking about do I buy a house
我当时在讨论要不要买房。
and he both told me it was the worst
他们都告诉我这是最糟糕的情况。
investment I could ever make. But he
我所能做的最大投资。但他
also told me to think about flexibility
他还告诉我要注意灵活性。
and my ability to get up and move.
以及我起床和活动的能力。
&gt;&gt; Yes.
是的。
&gt;&gt; And I was what do you mean? And he said,
我当时就想：你什么意思？他说：
"Well, listen, you're in a certain era
“听着，你身处一个特定的时代。”
of your career where
你的职业生涯中，
you might be called by someone in San
你可能会接到圣安东尼奥某人的电话。
Francisco who offers you a great
弗朗西斯科会给你带来很多好处
opportunity and you might want to go
机会，你或许想去
next week." And actually when I look at
下周。”实际上，当我看到
how my career transpired, that's exactly
我的职业生涯就是这样发展的，就是这样。
what happened. I was in Plymouth and
发生了什么。我当时在普利茅斯，
then I went to Manchester for business.
然后我去曼彻斯特出差。
Then I went to London for business. Then
然后我去伦敦出差。然后
I went around the world to San Francisco
我环游世界去了旧金山
to New York for business. And I'm I'm
去纽约出差。而我，我
moving with the opportunity.
抓住机遇。
And if I was anchored somewhere because
如果我被困在某个地方，因为
a mortgage does
抵押贷款
&gt;&gt; dragging that along.
拖着它走。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. And a mortgage does like
是的。抵押贷款确实如此
psychologically anchor you. This is what
从心理上给你带来安全感。这就是
people don't talk about. It creates a
人们不愿谈论。它创造了一个
huge amount of guilt if you then want to
如果你之后想这样做，你会感到巨大的内疚。
get up and go because you in your head
起来走吧，因为你脑子里想着
you're going, "Well, I'm going to be
你会说，“好吧，我打算……”
paying double."
付双倍价钱。
&gt;&gt; Well, so I agree with everything you
嗯，所以我完全同意你的观点。
said. I agree I I agree with your
说。我同意，我同意你的观点。
brother. Flexibility, especially when
兄弟。灵活性，尤其是在
you're young and your career is in a
你还年轻，你的事业正处于起步阶段。
dynamic [snorts] phase, it is not to be
动态[哼声]阶段，它不应该是
underrated. For my daughter, I mean, she
被低估了。就我女儿而言，我的意思是，她
loves living in Savannah. They've been
热爱在萨凡纳的生活。他们一直是
there for 3 years, but she has an
她在那里待了3年，但她有一个
adventuresome soul. And you know, she
充满冒险精神的灵魂。你知道，她
said, "I don't know. I mean, maybe at
他说：“我不知道。我的意思是，也许在
some point I'll want to go live in
总有一天我会想搬去住。
Europe or somewhere else." Well, if you
欧洲或其他地方。”嗯，如果你
have a house, that complicates that
有房子的话，这就复杂了。
decision. And even if you are fortunate
决定。即使你很幸运
enough to buy in a market where your
足以在市场上购买，而你的
values are rising, the cost associated
价值上涨，相关成本也随之增加。
with buying and selling of houses are
房屋买卖
enormous. the, you know, the real estate
巨大的。你知道，就是房地产
commission and the taxes and what have
佣金、税金以及其他费用
you. So, getting in and out of a house
你。所以，进出房屋
is an expensive proposition. Getting in
这是一个代价高昂的方案。进入
and out of apartment doesn't cost
搬出公寓并不花钱。
anything. I mean, maybe your security
任何事物。我的意思是，也许你的安全
deposit rate, but that's it. That's
存款利率，仅此而已。那是
that's very clean and simple, but if
那非常简洁明了，但是如果
you're if you were to buy a house in
如果你要买房的话……
Savannah and then just say, you know, I
萨凡纳，然后就说，你知道，我
think I want to go live in in Portugal,
我想去葡萄牙生活。
well, now you got to sell that house. Or
好了，现在你得把房子卖掉了。或者
maybe you have to rent it. Now you're a
或许你得租它。现在你是一名
landlord. You're an accidental r
房东。你是个意外的r
landlord, which was subject to my second
房东，这是我的第二份合同。
book. You know, that's not optimal. I
书。你知道，这并不是最佳方案。我
mean, if you set out to be a landlord,
也就是说，如果你立志成为一名房东，
great. But if you become an accidental
伟大的。但如果你意外地
landlord because you can't sell your
因为你不能卖房，所以你得找房东。
house that you don't want to live in
你不想住的房子
anymore, that's not so great. So
现在，这可就没那么好了。所以
flexibility is is enormously important.
灵活性至关重要。
If I if I were to ask you, what is the
如果我问你，什么是……
simple path to wealth? and you had to
通往财富的简单途径？你必须
respond in a sentence, what would that
请用一句话回答：那会是什么？
sentence be?
句子是什么？
&gt;&gt; Avoid debt. Live on less than you earn.
避免负债。量入为出。
Invest a surplus.
将盈余资金进行投资。
&gt;&gt; So, let's talk about debt then.
那么，我们就来谈谈债务问题吧。
&gt;&gt; Okay.
好的。
&gt;&gt; Why did you say avoid debt?
你为什么说要避免负债？
&gt;&gt; You can never be financially independent
你永远不可能实现经济独立。
if you're carrying around debt.
如果你背负着债务。
It's a ball and chain that you drag drag
这是你拖着走的沉重枷锁。
along, especially consumer debt. Now, to
尤其是消费债务。现在，
be clear, if you're in business and your
要清楚，如果你是做生意的，而且你的
business is is carrying debt as a as a
企业背负债务，就像……
function of of running the operation for
执行操作的功能
one reason or another, that's kind of a
无论出于何种原因，这都算是一种……
different thing. But in terms of
完全是两码事。但就……而言
personal debt, uh if you're running up
个人债务，呃，如果你负债累累的话
credit card debt, if you're leasing
如果你正在租车，信用卡债务就可能成为问题。
expensive cars or or borrowing money to
买昂贵的汽车，或者借钱
buy expensive cars or what have you,
买辆豪车之类的，
possibly a mortgage [snorts] is in a
可能抵押贷款[嗤之以鼻]在
slightly different category, but it has
类别略有不同，但它有
all the disadvantages we just talked
我们刚才讨论的所有缺点
about. Yeah, debt's a ball and chain.
关于。是啊，债务就像沉重的枷锁。
It's it's like asking a swimmer to
这就像要求游泳运动员……
compete and and strapping a weight
竞争并绑上重物
around their waist. Uh it just is it
她们的腰部周围。呃，就是这样。
possible? Well, sure. I guess it is, but
可能的？当然可以。我想的确如此，但是
it's a whole lot a whole lot more
远不止如此。
difficult. So, job one if you have debt
难的。所以，如果你有债务，首要任务就是偿还债务。
is to blow it out.
就是把它吹掉。
&gt;&gt; And I mean, blowing it out is a dream
我的意思是，把它吹起来简直是个梦想
for many, but it's uh easier said than
对很多人来说是这样，但说起来容易做起来难。
done. I guess
完毕。我猜
&gt;&gt; it simply means that you have to
这仅仅意味着你必须
organize your life in such a fashion
以这种方式安排你的生活
that you can divert some money to either
您可以将部分资金用于以下用途：
buying your freedom investments or if
购买您的自由投资，或者如果
you have debt paying off that debt. You
你背负着债务，却还要偿还这笔债务。你
just you have to do that. And people
你只需要这样做。还有人
say, "Well, I can't do that. You know, I
我说：“好吧，我做不到。你知道，我
I need to have this. I the you know, I
我需要这个。你知道，我
need to have the these the two least
至少需要这两个。
luxury cars and we need to live in this
我们需要开豪华车，我们需要生活在这样的环境中。
neighborhood and we need to send the
邻里关系，我们需要发送
kids to these schools. We need to and I
孩子们要去这些学校。我们需要，而且我
call that the tyranny of the must-haves.
这可以称之为“必需品暴政”。
The more musthaves you have in your
你拥有的必备物品越多
life, the less likely you are to become
生活，你越不可能成为
financially independent." Now, that's
经济独立。”这才叫真正的独立。
your choice. That's an individual's
你的选择。那是个人的
choice. It may very well be that those
选择。很有可能就是那些
things are more important to you than
对你来说，有些东西比……更重要
buying your freedom. And it's your
用金钱换取自由。这是你的
money. It's not for me to tell anybody
钱。我无权告诉任何人。
how they should spend their money or
他们应该如何花钱？
what's important to me or what's
对我来说重要的是什么？或者说，什么才是最重要的？
important to them. For me, there was
对他们来说很重要。对我来说，有
nothing I could spend my money on that
我没东西可以买来花。
was more important than my freedom.
比我的自由更重要。
Which is why from the beginning, I
所以从一开始，我就
diverted half of my income to buying
我把一半的收入都用来购买东西了。
that thing. Was never deprivation.
那个东西。从来就不是匮乏。
Right? Most people say, "Oh, that's this
正确的？大多数人会说：“哦，那是这个。”
is a path of deprivation. I can't spend
这是一条充满匮乏的道路。我无法花费
my money." Well, not for me. I, you
我的钱。”嗯，不是给我的。我，你
know, I spent every dime that ever came
我知道，我把挣来的每一分钱都花光了。
my way. It's just that I spent half of
我的方式。只是我花了一半的时间
those dimes on the thing that I wanted
我想要的那东西上的那些硬币
to own the most, which was my freedom.
拥有最多的东西，那就是我的自由。
And you own that by owning assets. So, I
而你拥有资产就拥有了这一切。所以，我
wasn't I wasn't depriving myself any
难道我没有亏待自己吗？
more than if somebody said, you know,
比有人说“你知道”要好得多
I'm looking at buying a a Mercedes or a
我正在考虑买一辆奔驰或者一辆
Volkswagen, right? If I'm buy the
是大众汽车，对吧？如果我买
Mercedes, I'm in this big fancy car and
奔驰，我开着这辆豪华大车。
people will be impressed. If I buy the
人们会印象深刻。如果我买
Volkswagen, yeah, I'm in this more
大众，是的，我更喜欢这个。
modest car, but then I've got a whole
车子虽然不大，但我还有整整
bunch of money left over that I can
还剩下不少钱，我可以
spend on a wardrobe or going out to
花钱买衣服或外出
dinner or a more expensive apartment.
晚餐还是更贵的公寓。
It's just a matter of choosing where you
这只是选择在哪里的问题。
spend your money on. Right? So, one of
把钱花在……上。正确的？所以，其中一个
the choices and I I do I am under no
这些选择，我，我确实，我没有受到任何约束
illusion that most people who read my
大多数人读过我的文章后都会产生一种错觉。
book will actually follow the simple
这本书实际上会遵循简单的原则。
path cuz I I think there's just way too
因为我觉得这条路太难走了。
much cultural influence to spend your
文化影响深远，值得你花时间去体验。
money elsewhere. But at least the people
钱花在别处。但至少人民
who read the book and listen to this
读过这本书并听过这段话的人
interview will be aware that there is
面试官会意识到这一点。
something else they could buy with their
他们还可以用这些钱买其他东西。
money. and that's their personal freedom
钱。那是他们的个人自由。
and you do that by assets and there was
你可以通过资产来实现这一点，而且当时……
nothing more important to me nothing I
对我来说，没有什么比这更重要的了。
wanted more so it was not deprivation at
想要更多，所以这不是匮乏。
all
全部
&gt;&gt; I amum I reflect back on
我沉默不语，回想起
where I used to be in my life and if I'd
我过去的生活状态，以及如果我……
heard this conversation then I really
听到这段对话后，我真的
really struggled with um saving money
存钱真的很难。
because saving spending money was so
因为省钱太重要了。
closely linked to my sense of self and
与我的自我意识密切相关
my self-esteem
我的自尊
&gt;&gt; a lot of people feel that way I've
很多人都有这种感觉，我也一样。
shared this story before, but when I I
之前分享过这个故事，但是当我……
was working in those call centers at uh
曾在那些呼叫中心工作过
which one, Swinton Swinton's car
是哪一辆，斯温顿的车？
insurance where I used to work, I would
在我以前工作的保险公司，我会
get my paycheck and it might be I don't
我拿到工资后，可能就拿不到了。
know, £1,500 or £2,000, whatever. And
知道，1500英镑也好，2000英镑也好，随便吧。和
like on my way home on payday, I'd go
比如发薪日那天回家路上，我会去
buy a 60-in TV [clears throat]
买一台60英寸的电视机[清嗓子]
and [laughter] I'd put it in the house
然后（笑声）我会把它放在家里
and then I'd try and see if I had enough
然后我会试着看看我是否足够。
money to buy a PlayStation
买PlayStation的钱
&gt;&gt; and then about a week later when I
大约一周后，当我
realized that I was broke, I would sell
意识到自己身无分文，我就卖掉
both. And I look at that behavior as
两个都。而我把这种行为看作是
such absolute like
这种绝对的
&gt;&gt; it's objectively like crazy behavior
客观来说，这简直就是疯狂的行为。
like repeated videos
就像重复播放的视频
but it shows the extent to which I got a
但这表明我得到的程度有多大
dopamine hit from having a nice thing
拥有美好事物带来的多巴胺刺激
and I was trapped in that cycle of like
我陷入了那种循环中，就像
&gt;&gt; buy the nice thing dopamine hit feel
买下那件让人愉悦的东西，感受多巴胺带来的快感。
validated feel like I'm a successful
感觉自己得到了认可，觉得自己很成功
person and then have to sell it a week
然后一周内必须卖给一个人。
later.
之后。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. So, I really have a huge amount of
是的。所以，我真的有很多
empathy for people that are stuck in
对那些身陷困境的人们抱有同情心
this spending for self-esteem cycle. And
这是为了提升自尊心而进行的消费循环。和
they hear these, you know, they hear
他们听到了这些，你知道，他们听到
people like me and you talk about these
像你我这样的人会谈论这些
things now
现在的情况
and it feels easier said than done.
但感觉说起来容易做起来难。
&gt;&gt; That to me seems kind of insane. And and
我觉得这简直太疯狂了。而且
you know, one of the things that
你知道，其中一件事是
somebody pointed out one time is if
有人指出，有时候是这样的：
you're driving around in a Ferrari, you
你开着法拉利到处兜风，你
know, maybe you're thinking to yourself,
也许你会想，
if you're bought the Ferrari because you
如果你买法拉利是因为你
want to impress people, everybody's
想给别人留下好印象，每个人都想
looking at me and they're thinking,
他们看着我，心里想着：
"Wow, what a cool guy that is driving
哇，开车的那家伙真酷！
driving that Ferrari." No, that's not
开着那辆法拉利。”不，那不是
what they're thinking.
他们在想什么。
They're looking at you in that Ferrari.
他们都在看着你开着那辆法拉利呢。
And what they're thinking is, "Wow, I
他们心里想的是，“哇，我
would look cool if I was driving that
如果我开那辆车，肯定很酷。
Ferrari." They're not thinking about you
法拉利。”他们没在想你
at all. it doesn't it you're making no
完全没有。它没有，你没有做出任何决定
impact on on what their opinion of you
这会影响他们对你的看法。
is.
是。
&gt;&gt; So on this point of debt, I did have
所以，关于债务问题，我的确有
some people contact me that were
有些人联系我，他们
childhood friends of mine recently and
最近，我的儿时朋友们
asked um asked me for advice on getting
有人问我关于如何获得的建议。
out of debt.
摆脱债务。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; And one particular friend said that he
一位朋友特别提到他
had $40,000
拥有 4 万美元
worth of debt and asked me for advice on
他们欠下了巨额债务，并向我寻求建议。
it. And I I really [clears throat]
它。我真的[清了清嗓子]
I'm not an expert in this so I kind of
我不是这方面的专家，所以我有点……
hesitated to give any advice.
犹豫不决，不敢给出任何建议。
&gt;&gt; But the advice I'm hearing from you is
但我从你那里得到的建议是
essentially you have to make a
本质上，你必须做一个
concession. You have to pull back your
让步。你必须收回你的
spending and get things back under
支出并把事情重新控制在合理范围内
control. You have to I know sell your
控制。你必须知道卖掉你的
house.
房子。
&gt;&gt; So, here's some good news. So, you're
所以，这里有个好消息。所以，你是
carrying to your friend. He's carrying
帮朋友带过去。他带着
$40,000 in debt, right? My advice would
负债4万美元，对吧？我的建议是
be, and this is a little different than
是，而且这与……略有不同
the more common advice out there, but I
市面上有很多常见的建议，但我
would look at all my debts and I would
我会查看我的所有债务，然后我会
pick the one that was charging me the
选那个向我收费的。
highest interest rate and I would I'd
最高利率，我会……
pay the minimums on all the others and I
其他所有款项都只付最低还款额，而我
would focus on paying that one down as
会集中精力偿还那笔债务。
fast as I could because that's the
我尽可能快地赶时间，因为那就是
biggest return on my investment. And
投资回报率最高。和
when that one was gone, I'd go to the
当那个人走了之后，我就去……
second until I worked my way through.
第二，直到我一步步完成。
It's going to be hard. And the more
这将会很困难。而且越多
quickly you do it, the harder it's going
做得越快，难度就越大。
to be cuz you're going to have to make
因为你得这么做。
more dramatic adjustments to your life.
你的生活将发生更大幅度的改变。
That's the bad news. Here's the good
这是坏消息。以下是优点
news is once you are out of debt, if you
好消息是，一旦你还清债务，如果你
do this, you've developed a wonderful
这样做，你就培养出了一个很棒的
discipline of living on less than you
节俭生活的自律
earn and diverting the excess to
赚取收入并将多余部分转移出去
something else that you want more. In
你还想要些什么？在
this case, to something else you want
在这种情况下，你想要的是其他东西。
more is being out of debt.
摆脱债务才是最重要的。
If you continue with that discipline,
如果你继续保持这种自律精神，
you now have the cash flow to begin
你现在有了启动资金。
building those assets and becoming
积累这些资产并成为
wealthy. You've already developed that
富裕。你已经发展出这种能力了。
lifestyle and that discipline. So that's
生活方式和自律。就是这样。
the one ray of sunshine, if you will, in
如果你愿意的话，可以称之为一缕阳光。
in the process of getting out of debt.
正在努力摆脱债务。
&gt;&gt; Okay. Play devil's advocate with me then
好的。那你跟我一起扮演反方角色吧
on this one.
就这个而言。
&gt;&gt; Sure.
当然。
&gt;&gt; So when I was 18, 19 years old, my
所以当我18、19岁的时候，我的
strategy I was well aware that I'd
我很清楚自己所采取的策略。
[__] up my financial situation. Like I
把我的财务状况搞砸了。就像我
was it was plainly clear that I'd
很明显，我
figured out what a credit score was and
我弄明白了什么是信用评分，
I realized that I destroyed mine. I also
我意识到我毁掉了我的那份。我
had these letters that [laughter]
收到这些信件[笑声]
these fail letters and and I had I had
这些失败的信件，还有我，我曾经
mounting issues. I was avoiding
安装问题。我一直在躲避。
finances, bills, envelopes, you name it.
财务文件、账单、信封，等等。
I just thought if I don't look at it, it
我当时就想，如果我不去看它，它
doesn't exist,
不存在，
&gt;&gt; which I know a lot of people do because
我知道很多人都这么做，因为
when I was writing a previous book that
当我写上一本书的时候
I wrote, I looked into some of the stats
我写了些东西，也查阅了一些统计数据。
about humans ability to avoid. Mhm.
关于人类的规避能力。嗯。
&gt;&gt; Whether it's health situations, if a
无论是健康状况，如果
friend of yours gets a bad diagnosis, I
你的朋友被确诊患有重病，我
was reading a study that said some
我正在阅读一项研究，该研究指出一些
people are more likely to not go get
人们更有可能不去获取
checked
已检查
&gt;&gt; even if their friends had a because they
即使他们的朋友有，因为他们
just want to avoid it.
只想避免这种情况。
&gt;&gt; Um, and then with national finances, I
嗯，然后是关于国家财政方面，我
was reading a study that said we're
我读过一篇研究报告，报告说我们
incurring billions and billions and
耗资数十亿，而且
billions and billions of debt as a
数十亿的债务
society just because we don't look at
社会仅仅因为我们不去看
our bank balance. We don't open
我们的银行存款余额。我们不开门
envelopes. So, I know I'm not the only
信封。所以，我知道我不是唯一一个。
one.
一。
&gt;&gt; No, not at all.
不，完全不是。
&gt;&gt; My strategy was my This is such a dumb.
我的策略是……这真是太蠢了。
&gt;&gt; I'm not sure I want to hear this.
我不太确定自己是否想听到这些。
Well, go ahead.
好的，请便。
&gt;&gt; Honestly, and this sounds like crazy
说实话，这听起来简直太疯狂了。
talk, but it's just the truth. In my
说出来可能有点夸张，但说的都是实话。在我的
head, my strategy was
头，我的策略是
&gt;&gt; I'm going to get so rich that I outpace
我会变得非常富有，以至于超越所有人。
this debt
这笔债务
&gt;&gt; and then I'll deal with it later.
之后我会处理这件事。
&gt;&gt; My strategy was if I can just get really
我的策略是，如果我能真正变得非常
rich, which is kind of the inverse of
富有，这可以说是……的反义词。
what you're advising,
你提出的建议是……
&gt;&gt; then this debt won't be a problem.
那么这笔债务就不会成为问题。
&gt;&gt; At 18 or 19 years old, you don't know
18、19岁的时候，你什么都不知道
the world. You are guessing,
世界。你是在猜测，
&gt;&gt; right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; And I was guessing that I could earn my
我当时猜测我能挣到我的
way out of it. The probability says I
摆脱困境的方法。概率表明我
was wrong.
错了。
&gt;&gt; The probability says that I was like
概率表明我就像
delusional or some or just like I
妄想症，或者某种程度上，或者就像我一样
watched too many rap videos or
说唱视频看多了或者
something,
某物，
&gt;&gt; right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; Um, so objectively that is a reckless
嗯，客观来说，这是一种鲁莽的行为。
choice. Even if even if it's true and it
选择。即使即便这是真的，而且
ends up being true for you, you end up
如果最终对你来说是真的，你最终
being what it's still a bad choice
即便如此，这仍然是个糟糕的选择。
because probability is stacked against
因为概率对它不利。
you.
你。
&gt;&gt; Well, that's true. And but you just made
没错，确实如此。但是你刚刚做了
a critical point in that you can make a
关键在于你可以做出……
bad choice where things work out well
糟糕的选择，结果却出乎意料地好。
for you.
为你。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, exactly. It's a bad choice.
对，没错。这是个糟糕的选择。
&gt;&gt; So, a great example of that is investing
因此，投资就是一个很好的例子。
in Bitcoin, right? I'm not I'm not a
用比特币支付，对吧？我不是，我不是
proponent of investing in Bitcoin.
比特币投资的倡导者。
Certainly, for those people who bought
当然，对于那些购买的人来说……
Bitcoin 10, 15 years ago, they've done
比特币在10到15年前就已经存在了。
extraordinarily well.
非常好。
They got lucky. Lots of speculations
他们运气不错。各种猜测
don't work out that well. So if you are
效果不太好。所以如果你是
speculating
推测
then you it might work out
那么，也许你会成功。
extraordinarily well for you but it's
对你来说非常好，但是……
you're taking some pretty heavy risks in
你冒的风险相当大。
doing that right it's same thing with a
这样做是对的，和
lottery ticket I mean the chances of
我指的是彩票的概率
winning the lottery are infantestimally
赢得彩票是幼稚的
small but people buy lots and lots of
虽然个头小，但人们买了很多。
lottery tickets somebody somebody does
彩票有人某人做
win it but that's probably not a good
赢了，但这可能不是个好结果。
way to spend your money
花钱的好方法
&gt;&gt; Bitcoin
比特币
&gt;&gt; you're not a fan of Bitcoin No. And I'm
你不喜欢比特币？不，我是。
not I'm not opposed to Bitcoin existing
我并不反对比特币的存在。
in the world.
在世界上。
Uh but for me, it's a speculation and
但对我来说，这只是猜测而已。
I'm not a speculator.
我不是投机者。
&gt;&gt; When you say spec, give me some color
说到规格，请给我一些具体信息。
because I'm sure there's some people who
因为我确信有些人
are listening now that are either
现在正在收听的要么是
thinking about Bitcoin or have invested
正在考虑或已经投资比特币
in Bitcoin.
以比特币形式。
&gt;&gt; I mean, if you want to speculate that
我的意思是，如果你想进行推测的话
Bitcoin, so I I would recommend against
所以我并不推荐使用比特币。
it. So, and people and they might push
它。所以，人们可能会推动
back and say, "Well, but JL, you know,
回去说：“嗯，但是JL，你知道，
you were recommending against against it
你当时是反对它的。
10 years ago, which I was, and you
十年前，我就是，还有你
you've been wrong. I mean, absolutely
你错了。我的意思是，绝对的
wrong. It's been great 10 years. It's
错误的。这十年过得很棒。它是
blown. It's done far better than the S&amp;P
吹走了。它的表现远胜于标普500指数。
500." Well, that's true. If you'd had a
500。” 嗯，没错。如果你有
crystal ball, if I'd known that 10 years
如果我早知道10年后会发生这样的事，那该多好啊
ago, yeah, well, I would have been in
以前，是啊，嗯，我本来应该在……
Bitcoin, right? We don't have crystal
比特币，对吧？我们没有水晶
balls. So the question isn't how is
球。所以问题不在于“如何”
Bitcoin done in the last 10 years. It's
比特币在过去十年中的发展历程。它是
how how is it going to do in the next 10
它未来10年的表现会如何？
years. I don't know the answer to that.
年。我不知道答案。
But that's the question. Is it worth
但这正是问题所在。值得吗？
$100,000 a coin now? Is it going to
现在一枚硬币值10万美元？它会……
continue to grow at that pace that you
继续以你这样的速度成长
regret that you missed over the last 10
后悔错过了过去10年
years? That's the question you have to
年？这是你必须问的问题。
ask yourself.
问问自己。
But I could say its success is evidence
但我可以说，它的成功就是最好的证明。
that it's serving some kind of utility
它发挥着某种作用
for some people somewhere. Its success
对某些地方的某些人来说。它的成功
means that there is demand for it by
这意味着市场对它有需求。
very nature that the price has increased
价格上涨的根本原因就在于此。
so crazily over the last 15 years.
过去15年里，情况变得如此疯狂。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. That and that's an argument that
是的。那就是，这也是一种论点。
people make and there's a lot of debate
人们制造了很多东西，也引发了很多争论。
around that, right? is, you know, what
大概就是那个时候，对吧？你知道，就是什么
is the function that it has or that it's
是它所具有的功能，或者说是它的功能
going to develop? And you might well be
会发展吗？你很可能
right. I don't I don't know the answer
正确的。我不知道答案
to that question. It's not currently at
关于这个问题。目前还不是
least a currency because it's way too
至少是一种货币，因为它太……
volatile to serve as a currency unless
除非波动性较大，否则不适合用作货币。
you're doing illegal things that
你正在做违法的事情。
make it more attractive than the
使其比……更具吸引力
volatility makes it unattractive. So
波动性使其缺乏吸引力。所以
that's not necessarily good for society,
这对社会未必是好事。
but but so it can't function as a
但是，所以它不能作为……
currency. So, right now it's just a
货币。所以，现在它只是一个
speculation. Is it going to grow into
推测。它会发展成什么样子呢？
something that's more functional? Well,
更实用一些的东西？出色地，
you know, listening to one of the other
你知道，听听其他人的发言
interviews you you you did,
你接受过采访吗？
that woman absolutely believes that
那个女人对此深信不疑。
that's what's happening. And they Kathy
事情就是这样。还有凯西
Wood, so that's why she's in Bitcoin.
所以她才会涉足比特币领域。
And she may be right, but she's
她或许是对的，但她
speculating. And again, I have nothing
推测。我又一无所有了。
against speculating as long as you
只要你反对投机，就不要投机。
understand, as I'm sure she does, that
我相信她也明白这一点。
that's what you're doing.
你正在做的就是这个。
&gt;&gt; You'd prefer investing.
你更倾向于投资。
&gt;&gt; I prefer to have an engine creating
我更喜欢让引擎自行创建
wealth behind where I put my money.
我投资的地方背后蕴藏着财富。
&gt;&gt; I had um a text message from a really
我收到了一条短信，发件人非常……
good friend of mine who my audience will
我的一位好朋友，我的观众将会……
know because they've been on the show
因为他们上过这个节目，所以知道。
before as a guest and uh they're very
之前作为客人去过，他们非常……
well known in the UK. Um they text me
在英国广为人知。嗯，他们给我发短信了。
and said, "Please, can I ask you a
然后说道：“请问，我可以问你一个问题吗？”
question? If you had mortgages and you
问题？如果你有抵押贷款，而且你
had a lump sum of money, thinking about
手头有一笔钱，正在考虑……
the future of AI, potential market
人工智能的未来，潜在市场
crashes, would you pay off chunks of the
如果发生事故，你会偿还部分债务吗？
mortgage or would you invest? My feeling
你会选择买房还是投资？我的感觉
is that stocks aren't really safe. Am I
那就是股票并非真正安全。我是谁？
being paranoid?
你是不是多疑了？
&gt;&gt; Well, there that's there are a couple
嗯，那里有几个。
questions embedded in that. So, the
其中蕴含着一些问题。所以，
first question is would I pay off a
第一个问题是，我是否愿意偿还贷款？
mortgage? And the second question is are
抵押？第二个问题是：
stocks safe? Right?
股票安全吗？正确的？
&gt;&gt; [snorts]
[嗤笑]
&gt;&gt; So the mortgage one first to me is is
所以对我来说，抵押贷款首先是
pretty easy. It kind of depends on your
很简单。这在某种程度上取决于你的
interest rate.
利率。
&gt;&gt; What is an interest rate?
什么是利率？
&gt;&gt; So an interest rate is what you pay to
所以，利率就是你支付给债权人的费用。
borrow money. So when you when you get a
借钱。所以当你得到一个
mortgage, you're borrowing money, right?
抵押贷款，就是借钱，对吧？
You're borrowing it from a bank or a
你是向银行或……借的。
financial institution
金融机构
and they they want to be paid for
他们想要获得报酬
letting you use their money. And three
让你使用他们的钱。还有三
three and a half% or less, that's really
百分之三点五或更少，那真是太少了。
cheap money. I would hold on to that. I
廉价资金。我会留着它。我
I would be in no hurry to pay that off.
我并不急于还清这笔款项。
On the other side, if you have a
另一方面，如果你有一个
mortgage rate that's say 6% or higher,
比如说，抵押贷款利率在6%或更高。
well, when you pay off that mortgage,
嗯，等你还清房贷之后，
essentially you're locking in a
本质上，你是在锁定一个
guaranteed return of that interest rate,
该利率有保障的回报，
right? So, if you pay off an 8%
正确的？所以，如果你还清了8%的贷款
mortgage, you've locked in an 8% return
如果您选择抵押贷款，您已锁定 8% 的回报率。
on that money effectively. And then to
实际上，这笔钱就这么用在了上面。然后到
finish the thought is if your interest
完成这个想法是，如果你感兴趣的话
rates between those those two like three
那两者之间的利率就像三个
and a half percent to five and a half
百分之一点五到百分之五五
six percent then I would say it would
如果是百分之六，那我会说就是百分之六。
depend whether you pay it off or not is
取决于你是否还清贷款。
what makes you emotionally more
什么会让你在情感上更加……
comfortable and there's value in being
舒适自在是有价值之处的。
emotionally comfortable. So if you are
情绪舒适。所以如果你是
comfortable carrying the debt you might
能够承受债务的程度
say well I think I can do better in the
我说，嗯，我觉得我在这方面可以做得更好。
stock market so I'm going to carry it.
股市行情，所以我打算持有它。
If emotionally like me you just would
如果你和我一样在情感上很像，你就会
rather not have any debt at all than you
宁愿完全不负债，也不愿……
then you blow it off. Maybe we could use
然后你就把它吹走了。或许我们可以利用
the coins as a an example of what an
以硬币为例，说明什么是
interest rate is.
利率是。
&gt;&gt; Sure. Let's say I'm sitting on this pile
当然。假设我正坐在这堆东西上。
of gold and you want to borrow some of
你拥有一些黄金，你想借一些。
my gold. I'm happy to loan you, Stephen,
我的黄金。我很乐意借给你，斯蒂芬。
these 10 very valuable old pieces. But I
这10件非常珍贵的古董。但我
don't like you well enough to just let
没那么喜欢你，所以才不会放你走。
you borrow them for free.
你可以免费借用它们。
I want to be paid. I want to get a
我想要报酬。我想得到一个
reward back for that. So, when you
为此给予奖励。所以，当你
return these gold pieces to me in a
请把这些金币还给我。
year, you're going to return 11 gold
今年，你将返还11枚金币。
pieces to me. You're going to pay me
对我来说是碎片。你要付钱给我
10%. Cuz an extra gold piece is 10% of
10%。因为多一枚金币是10%
these 10, right? Make sense?
这10个，对吧？明白了吗？
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; That's what interest is.
这就是利息。
&gt;&gt; So, I if I say, "Okay, I'm going to buy
所以，如果我说，“好的，我要买了
a house,
一栋房子，
&gt;&gt; right? You're going to take you're going
正确的？你要去，你要走了
to take those 10 gold pieces. Go ahead
拿走那10枚金币。前进
and take them."
然后把它们带走。
&gt;&gt; So, I'm buying a house that costs 10
所以，我要买一套价值10的房子。
gold pieces, right? Right. So, I'm going
金币，对吧？正确的。所以，我要走了
to accept your 10% interest rate.
接受你们10%的利率。
&gt;&gt; Okay. Am I paying 10% a year on the to
好的。我每年要支付10%的利息吗？
on the total
总计
&gt;&gt; on the balance? So, the way a mortgage
总的来说呢？所以，抵押贷款的方式
works is in the let's say it's a 30-year
作品处于……比如说，这是一部30年的作品
mortgage, you're going to be sp giving
抵押贷款，你将要支付
me a certain amount of money every
我每月都会收到一定数额的钱。
month, right? That's your mortgage
是月份，对吧？那是你的房贷。
payment. And in the beginning, most of
支付。起初，大部分
that payment is going to be interest to
那笔款项将产生利息
me. And a very tiny sliver of it will be
我。而其中极小的一部分将会是
paying down the principal part of the 10
偿还10本金
gold pieces that you bought or that you
你买的或你拥有的金币
Yeah. that you borrowed. A very tiny
是的。你借的。非常小
sliver. And then over the course of 30
一小块。然后在接下来的30年里
years that ratio changes as you pay down
随着你偿还贷款，这个比例会逐年变化。
the debt and less and less of it is
债务，而且债务越来越少。
interest payments and more and more of
利息支付以及越来越多的
it is paying down the principal until at
它正在偿还本金，直到……
the end of 30 years you've paid all the
30年过去了，你已经付清了所有款项
principal and you've paid me a fairly
校长，你付给我的报酬相当可观。
enormous amount of money in debt over
背负巨额债务
that or in uh interest over that 30
或者说，超过30%的利息
years.
年。
&gt;&gt; And how do I get a good interest rate?
我怎样才能获得优惠的利率？
How do I get a very very low interest
如何获得非常非常低的利率
rate? And what is a low interest rate
速度？低利率是什么意思？
&gt;&gt; on a mortgage?
还房贷吗？
&gt;&gt; Yeah. So the only way you can get a So
是的。所以你只能通过这种方式获得 So
first of all, you're going to pay
首先，你要付钱
basically whatever the current interest
基本上就是当前的市场兴趣。
rates are.
利率为。
&gt;&gt; Who sets the current interest rates?
谁来设定当前的利率？
&gt;&gt; So the Fed sets an overall interest
因此，美联储设定了整体利率。
rate. You've heard the Fed will raise or
速度。你听说过美联储将加息或
lower interest rates and that will
降低利率，这将
influence what lenders like bank and
影响贷款机构（如银行）的选择
mortgage companies will charge. It
抵押贷款公司会收取费用。它
doesn't require them to do a certain
并不要求他们做某事
level, but it will influence up or down
水平，但它会影响上下方向。
how much they're going to expect in
他们期望得到多少？
return for their money. The Fed is a
收回他们的钱。美联储是
government.
政府。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, the Fed is a government agent
是的，美联储是政府机构。
partially because the the Fed is
部分原因是美联储
anticipating inflation
预期通货膨胀
by how they set interest rates. So if
通过他们设定利率的方式来决定。所以如果
I'm lending you money and I'm worried
我借钱给你，我很担心。
about inflation, if [clears throat] I
关于通货膨胀，如果[清嗓子]我
lend you my 10 gold pieces and say I
我借给你我的10枚金币，然后说我
want 11 back in a year, 10%. But
一年内想收回 11，10%。但
inflation is 15%. Well, I've just made a
通货膨胀率为15%。嗯，我刚刚做了一个
very, very bad deal. So if I think
非常非常糟糕的交易。所以如果我认为
inflation is going to be 15%, I'm going
通货膨胀率将达到15%，我要走了
to want two gold pieces back and maybe
想要回两枚金币，也许
or you know, so I so I'm I'm making a
或者你知道，所以我正在做一个
profit above and beyond inflation. So
高于通货膨胀率的利润。所以
going back to your question, how do you
回到你的问题，你如何……
get a good mortgage rate? Well, you shop
想获得优惠的房贷利率吗？嗯，你购物
around to various lenders at the time
当时我向多家贷款机构咨询过。
you want the mortgage and see, you know,
你想申请抵押贷款，然后你就会明白，
who's offering what? And there'll be
谁在提供什么？而且还会有
some variation within a eighth of a
八分之一以内存在一些差异
percent or a quarter of a percent or
百分之几或四分之一百分之几或
something, but for the most part,
有些事，但大部分情况下是这样。
they're all going to be very tightly put
它们都会被安排得非常紧凑。
together because they're looking at the
因为他们正在看着……
overall projection of what inflation's
通货膨胀的总体预测
going to be, what they can charge, what
将会是什么情况，他们可以收取多少费用，以及什么
the cost of money is, what they can
资金成本就是他们能做什么。
charge in interest, and then
收取利息，然后
competitively what they what they have
竞争优势在于他们拥有什么
to do to get your business. So, there's
如何才能获得你的生意。所以，就是这样。
not going to be a lot of variation.
不会有太大的变化。
you're not going to get a a
你不会得到A的
significantly better interest rate than
利率明显优于
somebody else, but if you shop around,
或许可以找找其他人，但如果你多比较几家，
you can probably do a little bit better.
你或许可以做得更好一些。
And interest rates have been fluctuating
利率一直在波动。
quite a lot over the last 20 odd years.
过去二十多年来，变化相当大。
In the early 2000s, interest rates in
2000年代初期，利率
the US were relatively high, peaking at
美国的情况相对较高，峰值达到
almost 7%
近7%
in 2006 due to efforts to curb
2006年，由于遏制措施
inflation. And then after the financial
通货膨胀。然后是财务之后。
crisis, um they dropped a little bit.
危机期间，嗯，他们稍微下降了一些。
Um, and I was looking here. Post 2008,
嗯，我当时正在看这里。 2008年之后，
central banks around the world adopted
世界各国的中央银行都采用了
ultra low interest rates to revive
超低利率将刺激经济复苏
economies. US rates were slashed to near
经济体。美国利率大幅削减至接近
0% by 2008 and remained there for nearly
到2008年为0%，并保持了近一段时间。
a decade.
十年。
&gt;&gt; Right.
正确的。
&gt;&gt; Damn. Um, COVID 19 pandemic uh interest
该死。嗯，我对新冠疫情很感兴趣。
rates led to another record in cuts
利率导致降息幅度再创新高
globally with the US Fed lowering
全球范围内，随着美联储下调利率
interest rates to 0% to 0.25% to combat
为应对危机，利率将降至0%至0.25%。
economic disruption. So, does this mean
经济动荡。所以，这是否意味着
I should really be waiting for a time
我应该等一段时间。
when the interest rates are really
当利率真的
really low if I want to buy a house?
如果我想买房，价格真的很低吗？
&gt;&gt; Well, not necessarily because you never
嗯，不一定，因为你从来没有
know when that's going to happen. I
知道那件事何时会发生。我
mean, some some people have said
意思是，有些人说过
predicting what the stock market is
预测股市走向
going to do is very very difficult.
要做这件事非常非常困难。
Predicting where interest rates are
预测利率走向
going to go even more so. So I think if
还会更加如此。所以我觉得如果
you're going to if you're going to buy a
如果你打算买一个，你就会这么做。
house then again you buy it based on
然后你又根据以下因素购买了房子
whether you can easily afford it,
无论你是否能轻松负担得起，
whether it meets your needs at a given
它是否满足您在特定情况下的需求
time and you deal with the interest
时间和你处理利息
rates you have to deal with. And of
你必须面对的利率。以及
course they'll be part of the equation
当然，它们会是等式的一部分。
in terms of how much you can afford
就你的经济能力而言
because the interest rate on your
因为你的利率
mortgage is going to have a lot to do
抵押贷款将发挥重要作用。
with how much you have to pay every
你每件事都要支付多少钱
month
月
&gt;&gt; and it's quite high at the moment.
目前价格相当高。
Interest rates
利率
&gt;&gt; high compared to what? So the fir you
相对于什么而言高？所以，你
know right now mortgage rates are 6% 7%
现在已知抵押贷款利率为6%至7%。
somewhere in there. The first mortgage I
就在那里的某个地方。第一笔抵押贷款
took out was 18%.
取出的金额为 18%。
&gt;&gt; 18%. That would have been in 1979
18%。那应该是1979年。
because in the 1970s we had really high
因为在20世纪70年代，我们的利率真的很高。
inflation. And when you have high
通货膨胀。当你情绪高涨时
inflation, you have high interest rates,
通货膨胀，利率也很高。
right? So to me, I hear a 6% mortgage
正确的？所以对我来说，我听到的意思是6%的抵押贷款利率。
rate and it's doesn't sound bad to me,
评分？我觉得还不错。
but for people who grew up where
但对于那些在那种地方长大的人来说，
mortgage rates were 2 and a half, 3%.
抵押贷款利率为2.5%至3%。
Well, yeah, I mean, it's huge. It
嗯，是啊，我的意思是，它太大了。它
depends on your perspective.
这取决于你的视角。
&gt;&gt; And the other half of the lady's
而这位女士的另一半
question who sent me that text message
我想知道是谁给我发的这条短信
was around is investing in stocks safe
投资股票安全吗？
right now? and she did sort of preface
现在？她确实做了个铺垫。
it by saying the questions in the
通过回答问题来实现这一点。
context of AI all of this disruption
人工智能背景下的所有颠覆性变革
that's going on in the world people are
这就是世界上正在发生的事情，人们正在经历的。
going to lose their jobs etc et like is
他们会失去工作等等，就像这样
it safe to invest in stocks right now
现在投资股票安全吗？
&gt;&gt; so depends on your time horizon so
所以这取决于你的投资期限。
stocks are are the single
股票是单一的
most effective strongest wealth building
最有效、最强的财富积累
tool that's ever been created but they
迄今为止创造出来的最强大的工具，但他们
are also very very volatile so when she
她们的情绪也非常非常不稳定，所以当她
says are stocks safe to invest in right
有人说现在投资股票安全吗？
now.
现在。
What I hear is very shortterm thinking
我听到的是一种非常短视的想法。
and stocks are never safe to invest in
投资股票从来都不是安全的。
for the short term because they're
短期内，因为它们是
volatile at any given moment. They can
随时可能波动。他们可以
take a deep plunge and that's a
纵身一跃，那就是
perfectly natural part of the process.
这是过程中完全自然的一部分。
People get all create especially if you
人们会变得很有创造力，尤其是如果你
watch the news they people go insane and
看看新闻，人们都疯了。
panicked. But crashes and pullbacks in
惊慌失措。但崩溃和回调
the stock market are perfectly natural
股市完全是自然现象。
part of the process. They are very very
这是过程的一部分。他们非常非常
difficult if not impossible to predict
难以预测，甚至不可能预测
when they're going to happen. But that's
它们何时会发生。但那是
the reason you never
你从未遇到过的原因
want to invest in stocks for money that
想用这笔钱投资股票
you're going to need in the new near
在新的近
term. If you zoom out for longer periods
学期。如果你长时间缩小画面
of time, which is I re is what I
时间，也就是我重新开始的内容，就是我
recommend, stocks are stunningly
推荐，股票表现惊人
reliable. I mean, there are very few
可靠的。我的意思是，这样的人很少。
times over the course of 10 years where
在10年期间，有多次这种情况
stocks have not given you a good return.
股票投资并没有给你带来良好的回报。
and you go out 20 years and I I mean
你出去20年，我的意思是
it's very rare. So if you look long-term
这种情况非常罕见。所以，如果你着眼于长远发展的话。
stocks are extremely safe and extremely
股票非常安全，而且极其
powerful in building in building wealth,
在积累财富方面具有强大的力量，
but they are very volatile along the
但它们的波动性非常大
way. So you have to be willing and able
方式。所以你必须有意愿并且能够
to endure that volatility. If you're
承受这种波动。如果你是
going to panic and sell when the market
市场出现恐慌并抛售时，人们会恐慌抛售。
drops, not if because the market will
下跌，而不是“如果”，因为市场将会下跌。
drop. It's a perfectly natural part of
降低。这是完全自然的一部分
the process. If you're going to panic
过程。如果你要恐慌的话
and sell when that happens, you do not
当这种情况发生时就卖掉，你不需要这样做。
want to invest in stocks because they
想投资股票是因为他们
will leave you bleeding on the side of
会让你侧面流血
the road. Following my advice will leave
道路。听从我的建议，你就会离开
you bleeding on the side of the road if
如果你倒在路边流血的话
you panic and sell. It's 100% dependent
你惊慌失措地抛售了。这完全取决于
on tying yourself to the mass during the
在弥撒期间将自己与弥撒联系起来
storm and ignoring the volatility and
风暴，忽视波动性，
continuing to invest into it because now
继续投资是因为现在
you're actually accumulating shares on
你实际上是在积累股票
sale because prices are down because the
因为价格下降所以促销
storm never lasts. It always blows over
暴风雨不会持续太久。风总会过去。
and the sunshine comes back out and
阳光再次普照大地。
prosperity returns. You're talking here
繁荣终将回归。你在这里说话
about the emotional side of investing,
关于投资的情感层面，
which
哪个
&gt;&gt; which is critical.
这一点至关重要。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; If you if you can't control your
如果你无法控制你的
emotions, you're you're going to be
情绪，你将会是
selling at the wrong time and buying at
在错误的时间卖出，在错误的时间买入
the wrong time.
时机不对。
&gt;&gt; So, this is such a huge part of it that
所以，这部分内容非常重要，
people don't talk about enough. They
人们谈论得不够多。他们
talk about tactics, strategies, what to
讨论战术、策略、以及什么
invest in, etc. But they don't talk
投资等等。但他们不谈论。
about the emotional side, which is
关于情感方面，那就是
really like arguably a even bigger
真的很喜欢，甚至可以说是更大的
element of this because if you think
这其中的一个因素是，如果你认为
about even how the brain is set up and
甚至包括大脑的构造方式以及
what drives us most, it's it's fear.
驱使我们最大的，是恐惧。
It's it's emotion.
是情感作祟。
&gt;&gt; You're in greed.
你贪婪了。
&gt;&gt; And when the when the prices drop, you
当价格下跌时，你
know, I mean, we've all got a story. So
我知道，我的意思是，我们每个人都有自己的故事。所以
many people listening. I remember my
很多人都在听。我记得我的
first ever investment. I put £10,000
首次投资。我投入了10000英镑
into Facebook stock a long long long
长期持有Facebook股票
long time ago. And then it went down and
很久以前。然后它就倒下了，
I sold.
我卖掉了。
&gt;&gt; I thought, I'm never investing again.
我当时想，我再也不投资了。
&gt;&gt; And if I just left it,
如果我就这么放着不管了，
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Um, God, that would be worth so much
嗯，天哪，那价值连城。
money. It probably be worth six figures
钱。它的价值可能达到六位数。
now,
现在，
&gt;&gt; right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; But I I hadn't, no one had ever taught
但我没有，从来没有人教过我。
me about the emotional side. And
我跟你谈了谈情感方面的事情。和
actually part of the reason I sold it
实际上，这也是我卖掉它的部分原因。
was because I needed that money.
因为我需要那笔钱。
&gt;&gt; So there's two things there. One is the
所以这里有两件事。一个是
emotional side of selling it. The other
销售过程中的情感因素。另一个
thing is investing money that is not for
问题在于把钱投资到不属于自己的地方。
the long term cuz you turned out you
从长远来看，因为你最终还是……
should never invest in money in the
绝不应该投资于……
stock market that is you're not willing
也就是说，你不愿意进入股市。
to commit for decades. This is a
承诺持续数十年。这是
longterm horizon because that's what
着眼长远，因为这就是……
allows you to weather the storms. If
让你能够安然度过风暴。如果
you're saving for a house for instance,
例如，你在攒钱买房。
well you probably don't want to be in
你可能不想参与其中。
the stock market. The best investor I've
股票市场。我遇到的最好的投资者
ever met is my girlfriend. Uh because
我遇到的第一位就是我的女朋友。呃，因为
she she loses the password [laughter]
她把密码弄丢了[笑声]
to the investing app. And honestly,
到投资应用程序。老实说，
every like two years I go, "Babe, do you
大概每隔两年，我就会说：“宝贝，你愿意吗？”
remember?" I was like, "You bought loads
记得吗？”我当时就想，“你买了很多。”
of that index fund or Bitcoin or
该指数基金或比特币或
whatever it is."
不管它是什么。
&gt;&gt; I was like, "Do you know the price of
我当时就问：“你知道……的价格吗？”
it?" And she's like, "No, I forgot. I've
是吗？”她回答说：“不，我忘了。”我已经
forgotten the password to the app." And
我忘记了应用程序的密码。
we always like log back in once every
我们总是喜欢每隔一段时间重新登录一次。
two years and look at it. I'm like, "Oh
两年后再看看。我当时就想，“哦”
my god, babe. You're rich." And she's
我的天哪，宝贝。你很有钱。”而她也是。
like, "Oh, okay." And then she loses the
就像，“哦，好的。”然后她输了
password again. She forgets it. This is
请再次输入密码。她忘了这件事。这是
an incredibly important point you just
你刚才提到的这一点极其重要。
touched on. So Jack Bogle, the guy who
略有提及。所以杰克·博格尔，就是那个……
created retail index funds that we can
我们创建了零售指数基金，我们可以
invest in now, created the Vanguard
现在就投资，创建了先锋集团
Group in 1975.
1975 年成立的团体。
Bogle once said, you know, invest in the
博格尔曾说过，你知道，投资于
S&amp;P 500 and don't even open your
标普500指数，甚至不要打开你的
statements when they come. Just let them
声明将在发布时发布。就让他们去吧
stay. Don't even open them for 20 years
停留。 20年内都不要打开它们
and then open the final one and have a
然后打开最后一个，然后……
cardiologist standing by because you
心脏病专家随时待命，因为你
will be stunned at the level of wealth
将会被如此惊人的财富水平所震撼。
that you've accumulated. One of the
你已经积累起来的。中的一个
things that I wrote this this book for
我写这本书的目的
my daughter, right? My daughter is
我女儿，对吧？我的女儿是
sounds like she's kind of like your
听起来她有点像你
girlfriend. She's very smart, but she
女朋友。她很聪明，但是她
has zero interest in this financial
对这门金融业毫无兴趣
stuff.
东西。
That is a superpower because unlike me
那是一种超能力，因为不像我
and maybe a lot of people listening to
或许很多人都在听
us who are interested in this stuff and
我们这些对这些东西感兴趣的人
who are watching the market all the
一直关注市场的人
time, she and your girlfriend are never
时间，她和你的女朋友永远不会
going to be tempted to panic when the
当……时，我可能会忍不住惊慌失措。
market drops because they're not going
市场下跌是因为他们不去
to notice the market dropped, right?
注意到市场下跌了吗？
Because they're they don't they don't
因为他们是，他们不，他们不
care. And the less you tinker with your
关心。你越少对它进行改动，你的
investments.
投资。
Charlie Munger, who was Warren Buffett's
查理·芒格，他是沃伦·巴菲特的……
partner, once said, "The worst thing you
合伙人曾说过：“最糟糕的事情是你
can do as an investor is get in the way
作为投资者，可以做的事情可能会成为阻碍。
of compounding, right? And that means
复利效应，对吧？这意味着
dancing into the market trying to sell
跳进市场试图出售
and buy back in and what have you. Just
然后重新买入等等。只是
[clears throat] let the compounding
[清嗓子] 让复合
run." I get so many people who read my
跑。” 很多人读过我的
work and they say, "Wow, JL, I I I
工作之后，他们会说：“哇，JL，我我我
really get it and it's wonderful and
完全理解了，这太棒了。
you're absolutely right about
你说的完全正确。
everything, but if we just did this one
一切都好，但如果我们只做这一件的话
little thing differently, it would be
一点小不同，就会是
even better." And they are I've come to
甚至更好。”而他们正是我所认识的。
think of them as the tinkerers, right?
把他们想象成修修补补的人，对吧？
&gt;&gt; Are they men?
他们是男人吗？
&gt;&gt; They I think a lot of them are men. I
我认为他们当中很多都是男性。我
think I think women are a little less
我觉得女性在这方面稍微逊色一些。
inclined to tinker because men put their
男人喜欢修修补补，因为他们把……
masculinity on the line in doing these
这样做会危及男性尊严。
things and that's not useful.
这些东西没用。
&gt;&gt; I asked the question about men and women
我问了关于男人和女人的问题。
because I got some stats here from
因为我在这里得到了一些统计数据
actually from Vanguard that says men are
实际上，来自先锋集团的说法是，男人是
70% more likely to invest in high-risisk
投资高风险产品的可能性高出70%
assets like individual stocks versus
资产，例如个股，与
safer assets than women. Men's portfolio
比女人更安全的资产。男士投资组合
are 50% more volatile, which leads to
波动性增加50%，这导致
higher potential returns, but also huge
潜在回报更高，但同时也巨大
greater losses. As it relates to men,
损失更大。就男性而言，
again, despite having higher
再次，尽管拥有更高的
risk-taking, men underperform women in
在冒险方面，男性表现不如女性
long-term returns annually due to
由于长期收益，每年都会产生回报
overtrading, tinkering,
过度交易、修修补补、
&gt;&gt; and timing mistakes, tinkering. And men
以及时机把握失误和反复调整。男人
trade 45% more often than women,
女性的交易频率比女性高45%，
resulting in more fees because every
导致费用增加，因为每
time they make a trade, they pay a fee
每次进行交易时，他们都要支付费用。
and lower gains. That's according to
收益也更低。这是根据……
Berkshire Hathaway.
伯克希尔·哈撒韦公司。
The summary here is that men take more
简而言之，男性服用更多药物。
risks, but in the long term tend to earn
存在风险，但从长远来看往往会有收益。
less because of frequent mistakes and
由于频繁犯错而减少
emotional trading, whereas women are
情绪化交易，而女性则不然。
more cautious and their approach tends
他们更加谨慎，他们的做法也更倾向于……
to yield better returns.
为了获得更好的回报。
&gt;&gt; So, you know what we've learned here?
所以，你知道我们从中学到了什么吗？
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; I have a very strong feminine side.
我身上有着非常强烈的女性特质。
[laughter]
[笑声]
&gt;&gt; Well, gosh. Yeah. Damn.
哎呀，真是的。是的。该死。
&gt;&gt; Protecting your business's data is a lot
保护企业数据至关重要。
scarier than people admit. You've got
比人们承认的更可怕。你已经拥有
the usual protections, backups,
常规的保护措施、备份、
security, but underneath there's this
安全，但其下却隐藏着这种东西。
uncomfortable truth that your entire
令人不安的事实是，你的全部
operation depends on systems that are
运行取决于以下系统：
updating, syncing, and changing data
更新、同步和更改数据
every second. Someone doesn't have to
每秒钟。有些人不必
hack you to bring everything crashing
黑客攻击你，导致一切崩溃。
down. All it takes is one corrupted
向下。只需要一个腐败分子就够了。
file, one workflow that fires in the
文件，一个在以下情况下触发的工作流程
wrong direction, one automation that
方向错误，一个自动化程序
overwrites the wrong thing, or an AI
覆盖了错误的内容，或者人工智能
agent drifting off course, and suddenly
特工偏离航线，突然
your business is offline. your team is
您的企业已离线。你的团队是
stuck and you're in damage control mode.
陷入困境，你只能采取补救措施。
That's why so many organizations use our
这就是为什么这么多组织使用我们的服务。
sponsor, Rubric. It doesn't just protect
赞助商：Rubric。它不仅能保护
your data. It lets you rewind your
您的数据。它可以让你倒带
entire system back to the moment before
整个系统恢复到之前的状态。
anything went wrong. Wherever that data
出了什么岔子吗？无论这些数据在哪里
lives, cloud, SAS, or onrem, whether you
无论是在云端、SAS 还是本地部署，无论您
have ransomware, an internal mistake, or
可能感染了勒索软件、内部错误，或者
an outage, with Rubric, you can bring
使用 Rubric，您可以应对系统故障。
your business straight back. And with
你的生意又回来了。而且
the newly launched Rubric Agent Cloud,
新推出的 Rubric Agent Cloud，
companies get visibility into what their
公司可以清楚地了解他们的
AI agents are actually doing. so they
人工智能代理正在实际执行操作。所以他们
can set guard rails and reverse them if
可以设置护栏，如果需要的话还可以反转护栏方向。
they go off track. Rubric lets you move
他们偏离了轨道。 Rubric 让你移动
fast without putting your business at
快速发展，同时又不影响您的业务
risk. To learn more, head to rubric.com.
风险。欲了解更多信息，请访问 rubric.com。
&gt;&gt; You talked about compounding. You talked
你谈到了复利。你谈到
about how one should maybe not open the
关于为什么有些人可能不应该打开
envelope that has the state.
装有州名的信封。
&gt;&gt; That's Jack Bogle has said that, but I
杰克·博格尔说过这话，但我
agree with it. Yeah.
同意。是的。
&gt;&gt; I I don't have to explain the graph I've
我不需要解释我画的这张图。
just passed you for you to know what
刚才经过你身边，是为了让你知道什么
that is, right?
没错吧？
&gt;&gt; On the bottom, the red line is 11%
底部的红线代表 11%。
&gt;&gt; Mhm. returns. So the blue line that's
嗯。返回。所以，那条蓝线是
that's running fairly flat is the
目前运行相当平稳的是
contributions to this hypothetical
对这一假设的贡献
investment and the red line is the value
投资，红线代表价值
that that how it how it grows. And
这就是它的生长方式。和
what's striking, and this is this is
引人注目的是，这就是……
what's striking about compounding in
复利最引人注目的地方在于……
general, is that the two track each
总的来说，就是两条轨道各自运行。
other almost exactly for a surprisingly
其他几乎完全一样，令人惊讶的是
long time, and then they begin to
过了很久，然后他们开始
diverge, and then the compounding makes
发散，然后复利效应会加剧这种情况。
the value of the investment skyrocket.
投资价值飙升。
It hockey sticks.
它像曲棍球棒一样。
And I didn't know you were going to show
我不知道你会来。
this to me, but what's interesting to me
对我来说是这样，但真正让我感兴趣的是……
about [clears throat] this is I used to
关于[清嗓子]这是我以前常说的
do these shitakas. They were events
做这些石竹。它们是一些事件
where we'd take a small group of people
我们会带一小群人去那里
to some cool place in the world and hang
去世界上某个很棒的地方闲逛
out. And there were people who followed
出去。还有一些人跟随他们。
my work and and I would have one-on-one
我的工作，以及我会进行一对一的交流
sessions with them and we talk about
我们与他们会面，并讨论……
whatever they wanted, but mostly it was
不管他们想要什么，但大多数时候是
their finances. And very commonly these
他们的财务状况。而且这些情况非常常见
people would lay out their their
人们会摆出他们的
investments, their their finances, and
投资、他们的财务状况，以及
and
和
they would ask, "Am I financially
他们会问：“我的经济状况如何？”
independent?" And that's a there's a
独立？而且还有……
very simple mathematical formula about
关于一个非常简单的数学公式
that. How much did you spend? I spend
那。你花了多少钱？我花费
$100,000 a year. Okay. If you take the
年薪10万美元。好的。如果你采取
4% guideline, what's that?
4%的指导原则是什么？
&gt;&gt; Withdrawal. So, a guy named Bill Ben
提款。所以，有个叫比尔·本的人
came up with the idea that you could
想出了一个主意，那就是你可以
safely withdraw 4% of your portfolio and
安全地提取您投资组合的 4% 和
it would continue to survive over time
它会随着时间的推移继续存在下去。
and it would so you could you could pull
这样你就可以拉动
that out without depleting the
在不耗尽的情况下做到这一点
portfolio. There was a woman who came to
文件夹。有一位女士来到这里
one of our [__] talk. She was a banker.
我们闲聊的其中一段。她是一名银行家。
So obviously knows her way around basic
显然她很懂基本操作。
math, right? She was at the end of Stuck
数学，对吧？她在《困境》的结尾。
where she was going to take a new job
她原本打算在那里开始一份新工作。
starting that Monday was going to pay
从周一开始就要付出代价了。
her a million dollars a year [snorts]
她一年能挣一百万美元。[嗤之以鼻]
and we're going over her finances and
我们正在审查她的财务状况。
she said, you know, I've got $5 million
她说，你知道，我有500万美元。
invested. Okay.
投资。好的。
Am I financially independent? Well, I
我经济独立吗？嗯，我
can't answer that question until I know
在我知道答案之前，我无法回答这个问题。
how much are you spending. Said, well,
你每天花费多少钱？说得好，
I'm spending $100,000 a year. Okay.
我每年花费10万美元。好的。
Well,
出色地，
$100,000 a year, if you multiply it by
每年 10 万美元，如果你乘以
25, you get $2.5 million.
25岁，你将获得250万美元。
4% of 2 and a.5 million is 100,000,
2的4%加上50万是10万。
right? So, that's how that math works.
正确的？这就是数学的运作方式。
So, if you need 100,000 to live on, you
所以，如果你需要10万才能生活，你
need 2.5 million invested. Make sense?
需要投资250万。明白了吗？
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Okay. So, you can look at it either way.
好的。所以，你可以从两个角度来看待这个问题。
You can say, I've got two and a half
你可以说，我有两个半
million. If I take 4% of that a year,
百万。如果我每年取出其中的4%，
that's 100,000. or I I I'm spending
那是10万。或者我正在花费
100,000. How much do I need? You
100,000。我需要多少？你
multiply that by 25 two and a half.
乘以 25 再加 2.5。
&gt;&gt; So, just to make sure I'm clear,
所以，为了确保我的意思表达清楚，
[snorts]
[嗤笑]
&gt;&gt; if I look at my investment portfolio and
如果我查看我的投资组合，
I have $100 in there,
我里面有100美元。
&gt;&gt; if I can live, are you saying that if I
如果我能活下去，你的意思是如果我
live on $4,
靠4美元生活
which is 4% of my investment portfolio,
这占我投资组合的4%，
then I'm financially independent.
那样我就经济独立了。
&gt;&gt; Right. That's a good Now, it's a good
正确的。那很好，现在很好
guideline. I mean there's lots of
指导原则。我的意思是，有很多
variations but this is a guy guideline
形式多样，但这是一条男士指南。
this financial adviser Bill Benin came
这位财务顾问比尔·贝宁来了
up with
向上
u and then there was a thing called the
然后还有一种叫做……的东西
Trinity study which was done I want to
我想做的三一学院研究
say in the '9s that looked at a lot of
比如说在90年代，我们考察了很多……
these scenarios and basically verified
这些情况基本上都得到了验证。
that this was a very good baseline. Um,
这是一个非常好的基准。嗯，
so 4% is I don't like the word rule
所以4%是……我不喜欢“规则”这个词。
because that implies that it's hard and
因为那意味着这很难，而且
fast, but it's a great guideline. If you
虽然速度很快，但它是一个很好的指导原则。如果你
want to have a have an idea of whether
想了解一下是否
or not you're financially independent or
或者你是否经济独立
not, this is a good guideline. So
不，这是一个很好的指导原则。所以
anyway, this woman says she's spending
总之，这位女士说她正在花钱
$100,000 a year and she's got 5 million.
她年收入10万美元，现在却有500万美元。
She wants to know, am I financially
她想知道，我的经济状况如何？
independent in financially independent?
经济独立吗？
And I said, times two. I mean, you have
我说，乘以二。我的意思是，你有
twice as much money as you need given
所需金额的两倍
your level of spending. So, the question
你的消费水平。所以，问题是……
that I always had going back to this
我一直都有这种感觉，一直想回到这里。
little chart is how and I would get this
小图表展示了如何操作，我会得到这个
question a lot, Stephen. You know,
斯蒂芬，多问问题。你知道，
they'd show me their numbers and they
他们会给我看他们的号码，然后他们
would very clearly be financially
显然，这在财务方面会非常明显。
independent on that based on that math
独立于基于该数学原理的
we just discussed. And these were smart
我们刚才讨论过。这些都很聪明。
people who can easily do basic
能够轻松完成基本任务的人
arithmetic. Said, how how is it that
算术。话说，怎么会这样呢？
they're asking me this this question?
他们问我这个问题？
And suddenly it dawned on me, this is
突然间我恍然大悟，这就是
how
如何
because compounding
因为复利
is a is a hockey stick. It goes along
是一根曲棍球棒。它继续
and and kind of doesn't appear to be
而且似乎并非如此
happening and then it's slowly starts to
事情发生了，然后慢慢地开始
happen and all of a sudden it's way up
事情突然发生，然后就一路飙升。
here. It happens so quickly and so
这里。这一切发生得如此之快，如此之快
stunningly they can't quite believe it.
令人震惊的是，他们简直不敢相信。
It turned out is not that they couldn't
结果证明，并非他们做不到。
do the basic math. They certainly could
做一些基本的数学运算。他们当然可以
do the basic math.
做一些基本的数学运算。
What it was is they couldn't quite
问题是，他们根本无法……
[clears throat] believe what the math
[清嗓子]相信数学结果
was telling them and they wanted me to.
我告诉了他们，他们也希望我这么做。
It's like
就像
you you see what's on that wall over
你看到那面墙上有什么了吗？
there. I mean, are you seeing what I'm
那里。我的意思是，你明白我的意思吗？
seeing? Cuz I can't quite believe that
看到了吗？因为我实在难以置信。
I'm seeing that. I need you to confirm
我看到了。我需要你确认
that. Yeah, you're seeing the same thing
那。是的，你看到的也是一样的情况。
I'm seeing. And in this example, all it
我看到了。在这个例子中，所有的一切
is is someone has, you know, they've
就是有人有，你知道，他们有
started with zero
从零开始
&gt;&gt; and they've paid in a small contribution
他们也缴纳了一小笔费用。
every year to their investment. The
每年都投入到他们的投资中。这
investment is getting 11% return a year
这项投资每年可获得 11% 的回报。
&gt;&gt; and suddenly the thing goes
突然，事情就……
&gt;&gt; I think that was one of the most pivotal
我认为那是最关键的事件之一。
moments in my life where I went online
我人生中上网的时刻
&gt;&gt; five six years ago and looked at a
五六年前，我看过一个
compounding interest calculator. So
复利计算器。所以
&gt;&gt; it's stunning.
太惊艳了。
&gt;&gt; It's it is stunning.
它真是太惊艳了。
&gt;&gt; It is absolutely stunning.
真是美极了。
And it shows that if you just leave your
这表明，如果你只是离开你的
money in a place where it's getting this
钱在一个正在变成这样的地方
kind of return
某种回报
over time,
随着时间的推移，
everything seems to take care of itself.
一切似乎都能迎刃而解。
&gt;&gt; So let me let me close the circle in a
那么，就让我来结束这个循环吧。
sense on on that subject because one of
继续关注这个话题，因为其中一个
the things that I think gets overlooked
我觉得容易被忽略的事情
with my book is this is the simple path
我的书里写的就是这条简单的路
to wealth.
致富。
Which means if you follow it, you will
这意味着如果你遵循它，你将会
become wealthy, right? So we go back to,
变得富有，对吧？所以我们回到……
you know, buying those things that
你知道，买那些东西
people maybe want to buy, whether it's
人们可能想买，无论是……
the fancy car or the or the house. Well,
那辆豪车或者那栋房子。出色地，
once you become wealthy, you can not
一旦你变得富有，你就不能
only buy those things, but you're buying
只买那些东西，但你却在买
them from a position of power, right?
从权力地位上对他们下手，对吧？
You can easily afford them. you become
你完全买得起。你变得
financially independent, which means
经济独立，这意味着
that your investments are throwing off
你的投资正在造成混乱
more money than you're spending. My wife
比你实际花费的钱更多。我的妻子
and I are basically uh pretty naturally
我基本上就是……嗯，很自然
frugal people. And that's one of the
节俭的人。这是其中之一
ways I suppose that we got to where we
我想，我们走到今天这一步的方式大概就是……
are. But that doesn't necess necessarily
是。但这并不一定如此。
serve us at the level of wealth now. And
请以您现在的财富水平为我们服务。和
so we still have this tendency to say,
所以我们仍然有这种倾向，会说：
"Oh, we're thinking about getting this
“哦，我们正在考虑买这个
stuff. How much does it cost? And do we
东西。它要多少钱？我们是否真的如此？
really want to spend that money?" And
真的想花这笔钱吗？
depending on who it is, either she'll
根据对方是谁，她要么会……
turn to me or I'll turn to her and say,
要么你来跟我说，要么我就转头对她说，
"Doesn't matter. It's free. Everything's
“没关系。反正免费。一切都是……”
free. It doesn't." And that's a very
自由的。并非如此。”而这非常
liberating way to look at things. So
一种令人耳目一新的看待事物的方式。所以
that's where the simple path ultimately
这就是简单路径最终的归宿。
will will get you. That's what I bought
你会得到你的。我买的就是这个。
all those years ago.
那是很多年前的事了。
&gt;&gt; One of the thoughts that I had, which I
我当时的想法之一是，
do think is somewhat illogical, was my
我觉得这有点不合逻辑，这是我的。
brother and me are very different
我和哥哥性格很不一样
people. So he was very, very frugal and
人们。所以他非常非常节俭，
I was reckless. And one of the ways that
我当时太鲁莽了。其中一种方法是……
I self-justified my recklessness was,
我为自己的鲁莽行为辩解说：
well, you know, you've got to enjoy
嗯，你知道，你得享受。
life. And I'm only young once, so I'm
生活。青春只有一次，所以我
only going to get the opportunity to do
只会获得这样的机会
some of these things that are part of
其中一些是……的一部分
being young once, going to a nightclub
年轻的时候，去夜总会
and buying champagne and partying, you
还有买香槟、开派对，你
know? So, I thought, yeah, I could save
知道？所以，我想，是的，我可以省钱。
and save and save and save and I could
然后我就一直存，存，存，然后我就可以
get to, you know, 70, 80 years old and
到了七八十岁的时候，你知道，
have all this money, but what is the
拥有这么多钱，但是……
point if I haven't like enjoyed myself?
如果我玩得不开心，该怎么评价呢？
I think it is a mistake to think that
我认为这种想法是错误的。
you need to spend money to be happy, to
你需要花钱才能快乐，
enjoy yourself. And the other thing I
玩得开心。还有另一件事，我
will say is that
会说的是
it's a lot more useful having money at
有钱当然更有用。
this age than it would have been in my
比我年轻时要大得多。
20s because
20多岁，因为
money buys comfort among other things
金钱除了其他东西之外，还能买到舒适。
and comfort becomes much more important
舒适性变得更加重要
to you as you age.
随着年龄增长，对你来说也是如此。
They did a study where they put people
他们做了一项研究，将人们……
in a brain imaging scanner and they
在脑成像扫描仪中，他们
asked them to think about themselves
让他们思考自己
tomorrow. Then they asked them to think
明天。然后他们让他们思考
about themselves in a couple of years.
几年后他们会对自己作何感想。
Then they asked them to think about
然后他们让他们思考……
themselves in 10 years time and they
十年后的他们自己
looked at the brain. And then they did
观察了大脑。然后他们就这么做了。
another study where they got the same
另一项研究也得出了相同的结果。
people to think about a celebrity.
人们会想到名人。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; That they didn't know. I think it was
他们并不知道。我想是
Matt Damon or someone famous like that.
马特·达蒙或者其他像他一样有名的人。
And what the study proved was that we
这项研究证明的是，我们
think about ourselves in 10 years time
想想十年后的我们自己
in the same way that we think about Matt
就像我们看待马特一样。
Damon. The further away
达蒙。距离越远
the time horizon, the more it becomes a
时间跨度越大，它就越会变成
total stranger, right?
完全陌生的人，对吧？
&gt;&gt; And so I was writing I was writing
于是我就开始写作，我就开始写作
recently for a chapter in my upcoming
最近，我为即将出版的一本书中的一个章节做了准备。
book about this idea that our future
这本书探讨了我们未来的这一理念。
self is a stranger. To the brain,
自我感到陌生。对大脑而言，
thinking about me when I'm 60
想想我60岁时的样子
&gt;&gt; is like thinking about Matt Damon,
就像想到马特·达蒙一样，
right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; I don't know a [__] guy.
我一个男人都不认识。
&gt;&gt; So why do I care? Why do I care about
那我为什么要关心呢？我为什么会在意
protecting him? And I think this kind of
保护他？我觉得这种
speaks to what we were saying there is
这正印证了我们刚才所说的。
young people and even me as a young
年轻人，甚至包括我年轻时也是如此
person kind of didn't really give a [__]
这个人似乎根本不在乎
about 60-year-old me,
大约60岁的我，
&gt;&gt; right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; Like I I it's so far away that I I don't
就像我……它太远了，我……我不知道
really care about protecting his
非常在意保护他
interest. I almost think that's a
兴趣。我几乎认为那是一个
different person. He can figure that
不同的人。他能想到这一点
out,
出去，
&gt;&gt; right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; And you know, you are How old are you
你知道，你多大了？
now?
现在？
&gt;&gt; I'm 75.
我75岁了。
&gt;&gt; So you have the the wisdom of hindsight.
所以你拥有了事后诸葛亮的智慧。
So you can tell me as a 33y old what
所以，作为一个33岁的人，你可以告诉我什么
it's like to be both 33 and 75. When I
感觉就像同时是33岁和75岁。当我
was 33, I didn't think about
我当时33岁，没想过这个问题。
me at an older age at all. I mean, it
我年纪大了之后会是什么样子呢？我是认真的
never crossed my mind to do such a
我从未想过要这样做。
thing. Right? So, I was not doing what I
事物。正确的？所以，我并没有做我该做的事。
was doing for the benefit of 75year-old
这样做是为了一位75岁老人的利益。
JL. I was doing it for the benefit of
JL。我这样做是为了……的利益
25-year-old JL, 30-year-old JL. Right?
25岁的JL，30岁的JL。正确的？
remember going back to an early part of
记得回到早期
our conversation
我们的对话
what my definition of FU money it's the
我理解的“FU money”是指……
money that you're accumulating
你正在积累的钱
before that gets you ultimately to being
在此之前，你最终会成为
financially independent which is when
经济独立，也就是当
you no longer need to trade your labor
你不再需要出卖自己的劳动力了。
for money right your money is doing all
对于金钱来说，你的钱正在做一切。
that
那
I wanted that right now so when I was 25
我当时就想要那个，所以在我25岁的时候。
I'd saved the princely sum of $5,000
我攒下了5000美元这笔巨款。
adjusted for inflation to be about 25
经通货膨胀调整后约为25
$30,000 today. U and I wanted to go back
今天3万美元。你和我都想回去
around Europe, right? But that meant
欧洲各地，对吧？但这意味着
quitting my job, which I kind of liked.
我辞掉了那份我其实还挺喜欢的工作。
But the fact that I had that money gave
但我拥有那笔钱的事实给了我
me the financial strength to go in and
我有足够的经济实力进入这个行业
negotiate that deal. If I was living
协商达成这笔交易。如果我活着
paycheck to paycheck, I wouldn't have
如果靠工资过日子，我肯定不行。
had that. I was far from being fully
有。我离完全成熟还差得很远。
financially independent. So, I wasn't
经济独立。所以，我不是。
doing this for 75 year old JL. I was
这样做是为了75岁的JL。我当时
doing this right now for 25 year old JL.
我现在正在为25岁的JL做这件事。
And it's just like when you work out,
就像你锻炼的时候一样，
and clearly you do, right? You don't go
显然你也是这么想的，对吧？你不去
to the gym thinking, at least I'm making
去健身房的时候心想，至少我还在锻炼。
a presumption here, I'm doing this for
这里有个假设，我这样做是为了
75year-old Steven. You're doing this
75岁的史蒂文。你在做这件事
because you want to be stronger tomorrow
因为你想明天变得更强大。
than you are today. for 33 year olds
比你现在的状态好得多。 33岁人群
even. So that's my way of thinking about
甚至。这就是我的想法。
it. I I never did this for future me.
它。我做这一切并非为了未来的自己。
Maybe some people do and that's probably
或许有些人会这么做，这大概就是事实。
not a bad exercise. It's probably a bit
这算是一项不错的锻炼。可能有点
of wisdom in that. I wasn't that smart.
其中蕴含着智慧。我没那么聪明。
&gt;&gt; So you would you would save $5,000 a
这样你就能省下5000美元。
year.
年。
&gt;&gt; Well, in those days, so my first
嗯，在那些日子里，所以我的第一次
professional job paid me $10,000 a year
这份专业工作年薪1万美元。
and I saved 5,000. Yeah, I saved half of
我省了5000元。是的，我省下了一半。
it. Going back to this point of
它。回到这一点
compounding and how how important it is
复利及其重要性
to start investing in things that will
开始投资那些
offer you compounding returns.
为您提供复利收益。
&gt;&gt; If you started investing $500 per month
如果你每月投资 500 美元
and you got an annual return of 8%
你的年收益率为 8%。
because you're investing in some of the
因为你投资了一些
things that we'll talk about in a
我们将在……中讨论的事情
second.
第二。
&gt;&gt; In 35 years
35年后
you will be a millionaire. You'll have
你将成为百万富翁。你将拥有
more than a million dollars. You'll have
超过一百万美元。你将拥有
1.043 043 million
104.3043万
&gt;&gt; over those 35 years you would have
在那35年里，你将拥有
invested about $200,000 but you would
投资了大约20万美元，但你会
have made $850,000
已赚85万美元
from the interest over that period of
在此期间产生的利息
time.
时间。
&gt;&gt; Well, just to be clarified, not
嗯，澄清一下，不是
necessarily the interest, but the growth
必然是兴趣，但增长
cuz that 11% is not interest. It's it's
因为那11%并不是利息。是它的
growth. Some of it might be uh dividends
生长。其中一些可能是股息。
in the case of which is a kind of a form
在这种情况下，这是一种形式
of interest you can think of but it's
你能想到的有趣的事情，但它是
not just just to be technically correct
不仅仅是技术上的正确性
right which is which is interesting. So
对，这很有意思。所以
if I was when I was born if my parents
如果我出生时是……如果我的父母
had put $500 a month away in a
我每月往账户里存500美元。
investment that we'll talk about now
我们现在要讨论的投资
&gt;&gt; by the by the age I am now I would have
到我现在的年纪，我应该已经
roughly been a millionaire just from
差不多就成了百万富翁
them putting $500 a month away from me.
他们每个月从我这里扣除500美元。
Right.
正确的。
&gt;&gt; Pretty crazy.
真是太疯狂了。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. But that's the power of
是的。但这就是力量所在
compounding. I mean, the, you know, it's
复利。我的意思是，你知道，就是
it's very gratifying to me that twice a
令我非常欣慰的是，两次
year I I'm a guest lecturer for a friend
今年我应邀去朋友家做客座讲师。
of mine who's a professor at uh
我的朋友，他是呃……的教授
University of Colorado in Boulder. And
科罗拉多大学博尔德分校。和
it's always fun to talk to her students
和她的学生们聊天总是很有趣。
because they're exceedingly bright. They
因为它们非常明亮。他们
ask great great questions and it's just
问一些非常好的问题，仅此而已
stimulating for me. But I think about
对我来说很有启发。但我一直在想……
these young people. I mean, these are
这些年轻人。我的意思是，这些是
18, 19, 20 year olds who are thinking
18、19、20岁的年轻人正在思考
about doing this stuff at that age. And
关于在那个年纪做这些事。和
the remarkable amount of time that they
他们花费的时间之长令人惊叹
have for this compounding to work for
为了让这种复利效应发挥作用
them, it's it's just incredible. They
他们，这简直太不可思议了。他们
are going to be so much better off than
他们的境况将会比现在好得多。
if not. Um, so let me throw out a tip
如果不。嗯，那我给你个建议吧。
for for you if and when you ever have
如果你有需要，可以随时联系我。
kids and for anybody who's listening who
孩子们，以及所有正在收听的人
has has young children, you know, as
有年幼的孩子，你知道，就像
your kids start to grow and hopefully
你的孩子开始长大，希望
they get part-time jobs, right? They
他们会找兼职工作，对吧？他们
start whether it's shoveling snow or
无论是铲雪还是其他什么，都要开始
busting tables at a local restaurant or
在当地餐馆收拾餐桌或
whatever it is and they start earning
不管是什么，他们就开始赚钱了。
some income. Well, you can take that
一些收入。嗯，你可以把那句话带走。
income and up to I think it's $7,000 is
收入最高可达7000美元。
the limit now. Put that in a Roth IRA
到此为止了。把这笔钱存入罗斯个人退休账户（Roth IRA）。
which will never be taxed. It will grow
这部分永远不会被征税。它会成长
tax-free forever and they're going to be
永久免税，而且它们将会是
by definition because they're making
根据定义，因为他们正在制造
almost no money in in they're not paying
他们几乎没收到钱，因为他们不付款。
any income tax. So, you don't need any
任何所得税。所以，你不需要任何
any deduction from that. And it doesn't
从中扣除任何费用。但事实并非如此。
have to be their money. So, let's say
肯定是用他们自己的钱。所以，我们假设
your kid makes $3,000 during the course
你的孩子在课程期间赚了3000美元
of a year.
一年。
you can take $3,000 and fund a Roth IRA
你可以拿出 3,000 美元开设一个罗斯个人退休账户 (Roth IRA)。
for them. Imagine just if they never
对他们来说。想象一下，如果他们从未
added anything other than that, you
除了这些之外，你还添加了其他任何东西。
know, you do that until they they get
你知道，你这样做直到他们得到
out of college or whatever. You know,
大学毕业什么的。你知道，
that baseline is going to grow tax-free
该基线将免税增长。
for an extended period of time. That's
持续相当长的一段时间。那是
one of the great keys to wealth building
财富积累的关键之一
is just time. And and is that advice
只是时间问题。那算什么建议？
that you still believe in that people
你仍然相信人们
should be saving 50% of their income?
他们应该储蓄收入的50%吗？
&gt;&gt; Yeah, I think it's a good rule of thumb.
是的，我认为这是一个很好的经验法则。
It gets you to financial independence in
它能让你实现财务自由
a pretty reasonable depending on what
相当合理，具体取决于什么
the market does in say a 10 to 15 year
市场通常会在10到15年内出现这种情况。
time period. The push back that you
时间段。你受到的反击
might anticipate is from people who say
可能会预期的是来自那些说
that's impossible. Nobody can save 50%
那不可能。没人能省下50%的钱
of their money. Just that's that's
他们的钱。就是这样。
that's silly. And I'm sorry, but I've
真傻。我很抱歉，但我
did it and I've now at this point I've
我已经做到了，现在我已经……
known countless people who've done it.
我认识无数这样做过的人。
So, it's certainly you may choose not to
所以，你当然可以选择不这样做。
do it, but it's certainly possible.
去做吧，这当然是有可能的。
&gt;&gt; Let's say you're earning $40,000
假设你年收入4万美元
a year, which is the low end,
一年，这是最低水平。
&gt;&gt; the average medium. So, that would be
平均水平。所以，那就是
let's say $3,000 a month.
假设每月 3000 美元。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; So, you're you're earning $3,000 a
所以，你每月能赚3000美元。
month. You're then going to pay tax on
月。然后你就要缴纳税款了。
that. This is what my my math says here.
那。这是我的数学计算结果。
It says very little tax would be would
它说税收会非常少。
be paid after all of your taxes. And so
扣除所有税款后支付。所以
you're still you've still got roughly
你仍然，你仍然大致拥有
$3,000 a month, about 2,900 um which you
每月 3000 美元，大约 2900 微米，你
you would take home.
你可以带回家。
&gt;&gt; I so I would need to save 1,400 of that
所以，我需要存下其中的1400。
which means my total expenses need to be
这意味着我的总支出需要是
1,400 a month. So first thing I need to
每月1400美元。所以，我首先需要做的是
do is live somewhere very very
住在非常非常的地方
affordable
价格实惠
&gt;&gt; depending where I live, you know, what
这取决于我住在哪里，你知道，什么
city I live in.
我居住的城市。
&gt;&gt; Then I need to basically radically
然后我需要彻底地
reduce my my expenditure, right,
减少开支，对吧？
&gt;&gt; to be able to save 50% a month. And I
每月可节省 50%。我
guess the question is most people
我想这个问题是大多数人
would assume they wouldn't like that
我会认为他们不会喜欢那样。
lifestyle.
生活方式。
They wouldn't like to prepare their own
他们不愿意自己准备。
lunches every day. They wouldn't like to
每天午餐。他们不愿意
not have a Starbucks coffee. They
不喝星巴克咖啡。他们
wouldn't like to live in a small small
不想住在小房子里
shoe box and probably socialize a lot
鞋盒，而且可能经常社交
less.
较少的。
&gt;&gt; So I guess that's the key rebuttal is I
所以我觉得关键的反驳就是……
guess yeah, it's possible.
我想是的，有可能。
There's a chapter that talks about this
有一章专门讨论这个。
with an even lower uh because when I was
甚至更低，因为当我……
writing the book um I think I used a
写这本书的时候，嗯，我想我用了……
$25,000
25,000 美元
annual income. So the math works is is
年收入。所以数学原理是有效的。
it easy? No. But it goes back to
这容易吗？不。但这要追溯到……
fundamentally
从根本上
what is it that you want? You said well
你想要什么？你说得好
I may not want like that. I might want
我可能并不想那样。我可能想要
to have lattes and all these other
喝拿铁以及其他这些东西
things. Well it's your money. That's
事物。这是你的钱。那是
your prerogative.
这是你的权利。
But time is going to happen regardless
但时间总会流逝，无论如何。
of what you do. And if you say, "Instead
你所做的事情。如果你说，“相反
of having those things now, I'm going to
现在拥有了这些东西，我打算
spend my money on buying my freedom,"
“把钱花在换取自由上。”
you will get to the point where
你会达到这样的地步：
everything is free, including those
所有东西都是免费的，包括那些
lattes.
拿铁。
&gt;&gt; So, let's talk about investing then.
那么，我们就来谈谈投资吧。
&gt;&gt; Um, we have two buckets here on the
嗯，我们这里有两个桶。
table for an analogy
类比表格
&gt;&gt; around tax advantaged investing.
围绕税收优惠投资。
I'm going to take your lead on this.
这件事我打算听你的。
&gt;&gt; Okay. So, if you dump that bucket in
好的。所以，如果你把那桶水倒进……
there, I'll dump this bucket in here.
好了，我把这桶水倒进来。
Okay.
好的。
The idea is that and I'm going to speak
我的想法是这样的，接下来我要说……
in terms of the United States. The
就美国而言。这
government provides
政府提供
savings vehicles that are tax advantage
具有税收优惠的储蓄工具
to encourage people to acquire money for
鼓励人们筹集资金
their for their old age. Right? So in
他们是为了安享晚年。正确的？所以在
the United States there's things called
在美国，有些东西叫做
a 401k or 403b.
401k 或 403b 计划。
Uh these are employer related plans
呃，这些是雇主相关的计划。
where you can divert part of your income
你可以将部分收入用于其他用途
and the government specifies how much
政府会具体规定金额。
you can divert and they won't tax you on
你可以改道，他们不会向你征税。
that and you put it into an investment
然后你把它投入投资
bucket into an investment account of
将资金存入投资账户
some sort. you get to choose how you
某种程度上。你可以选择如何
want to invest it, but that would be the
想投资，但那将是
bucket. And that means that if you had
桶。这意味着，如果你有
however much money this represents
无论这代表多少钱
uh went into your 401k or your IRA,
呃，存入你的401k或IRA账户里了。
which is something you would do on your
这是你会在……上做的事情
own privately, which is also tax
私人拥有，这也是一种税收行为。
advantaged, right? So, in the example
有优势，对吧？所以，在这个例子中
that you've just [clears throat] handed
你刚刚[清了清嗓子]递交了
me, they're saying that this would
他们告诉我，这会
represent $20,750,
代表 20,750 美元，
which is uh before tax and with a match.
这是税前价格，并且包含匹配费用。
So, 401ks companies will frequently
因此，401k公司经常会
match part of your contribution. So, you
匹配你部分捐款。所以，你
say, "I'm going to do 5%." And they
我说：“我打算做 5%。”他们
might say, "Okay, we're going to match
可能会说：“好的，我们要匹配。”
the first 2% or whatever," which you
前2%或其他什么”，也就是你
should always take advantage of because
应该始终利用这一点，因为
that's that's free money. So this is not
那可是白送的钱啊。所以这不是
taxed immediately and you invest this
立即缴税，然后你投资这笔钱。
money. Let's say you invest it in a
钱。假设你把它投资于……
total stock market index fund which
全股票市场指数基金
would be my recommendation. So you get
我会推荐这样做。所以你得到
to invest all this money in your total
将所有这些钱投资到你的总额
stock market index fund. If instead you
股票市场指数基金。如果你
do it after you pay taxes on the same
在你缴纳了相同项目的税款之后再做这件事。
amount of money, well, by the time you
金额，嗯，到你
pay taxes, you're going to have about
交税，你大概会得到……
half of what it was before, which is
只有以前的一半，也就是
$10,340,
10,340 美元
which is what represented in here
这就是这里所代表的。
roughly half the number of of gold
大约一半的黄金
coins. Now, both of these things grow at
硬币。现在，这两样东西都在增长
the same rate because we've invested
同样的利率，因为我们已经投资了。
them in the same thing, right? So,
它们属于同一类情况，对吧？所以，
they're making 11% a year, whatever it
不管怎样，他们每年能赚11%。
is. So this is obviously going to grow
是。所以这显然会增长。
into a much bigger pile at the end of 30
30天后，它们堆积成更大的一堆。
years or 40 years or whatever it is than
几年，或者40年，或者不管多少年，都比这长。
this is because you're starting with a
这是因为你从一个
bigger pile. So that's the advantage of
更大的一堆。这就是它的优势所在。
deferring taxes. Now, the thing that
延期缴纳税款。现在，这件事是……
people tend not to think about or talk
人们往往不会去思考或谈论这些。
about that's incredibly important is
关于这一点，极其重要的是……
that it is not avoiding taxes. It is
它并没有逃税。这是
deferring taxes. Which means that
延期缴纳税款。这意味着
ultimately the government is going to
最终，政府将会
want their money. They're going to want
想要他们的钱。他们会想要
their cut. And typically that happens, I
他们分得的份额。通常情况下，这种情况就会发生。
think in the United States the age is 73
在美国，这个年龄应该是73岁。
or something when you're required to
或者当你被要求这样做的时候
begin taking money out of these
开始从这些资金中取出资金
accounts. It's called an RMD, a required
账户。它被称为RMD，即必需的
minimum distribution.
最低分配。
So, if you haven't started withdrawing
所以，如果你还没有开始提款
money from these accounts, by then the
到那时，这些账户里的钱
government will require you to begin on
政府会要求你开始……
a schedule based on your life expectancy
根据您的预期寿命制定的日程安排
to start pulling that money out because
开始把钱取出来，因为
they figure they've waited long enough
他们觉得已经等了足够长的时间了。
and now they want their cut. Okay?
现在他们也想要分一杯羹。好的？
[clears throat] So, it's not tax-free,
[清嗓子] 所以，它不是免税的。
it's tax deferred. Important thing to
它是延税的。重要的事情
understand if you start taking this
如果你开始服用这种药，就明白了。
money out before a certain age and if
在达到一定年龄之前提取资金，并且如果
memory serves me it's 59 and a half in
我记得没错的话，是59.5英寸。
the US then you will pay tax on it as
如果在美国购买，你就需要为此缴税。
you do whenever you withdraw the money
你每次取款时都会这样做。
and also a penalty right so they want
而且他们还想判罚，所以他们想要
you to keep it in at least until you're
你至少要把它留在体内直到……
59 and a half but they want you to start
59岁半，但他们想让你开始
taking it out at some point in this case
在这种情况下，迟早会把它取出来。
I think when you're 72 or 73 or
我认为当你72岁或73岁的时候，或者
something like and That's when they
类似这样，然后他们……
collect their money. So you say, well,
收回他们的钱。所以你会说，嗯，
okay, if that's the case, then what am I
好吧，如果真是那样的话，那我又是什么呢？
doing here? Because I got to pay the
来这里做什么？因为我必须付钱
taxes eventually anyway. And
反正迟早都要交税。和
mathematically, if your tax rate is the
从数学角度来说，如果你的税率是
same, it doesn't matter if you're tax
同样，无论你是否纳税都无关紧要。
deferred or not. The end result of
延期或不延期。最终结果是
amount of money that you have will be
你所拥有的金额将是
exactly the same.
完全一样。
The speculation is, and it's true in the
这种猜测是真的，而且在……中也确实如此。
vast majority of cases, that when you
绝大多数情况下，当你
retire and you start living on this
退休后，你就可以靠这个生活了。
money, you start pulling it out, you
你开始掏钱，你
will be in a lower tax bracket. So, you
将会进入较低的税率等级。所以，你
will have to pay some taxes, but you
你需要缴纳一些税款，但是你
won't have to pay as much as when you
你不用像以前那样支付那么多费用
were working and you were in a higher
当时你在工作，而且你的职位更高。
tax bracket. So, that's the gamble
税率等级。所以，这就是赌注。
you're taking. Now, looking at me
你在服用。现在，看着我
personally as an example, this didn't
就我个人而言，举个例子，这并没有。
work out for me. So, I did IAS and 401ks
对我来说很合适。所以我做了IAS和401k计划。
when I was working in my corporate
当我还在公司工作时
career. Put aside a fair amount of money
职业。预留一笔可观的资金
in them. Now, as it turns out, I'm in a
在它们之中。现在，事实证明，我身处……
higher tax bracket than I have ever been
我曾处于比以往更高的税级。
in because of the success of the
由于成功
activities that I do today. I had no
我今天所进行的活动。我没有
idea that that was going to happen. And
没想到会发生这种事。和
now I'm at that age where I have to take
现在我已经到了必须接受的年龄
RMDs. So RMDs are coming out at a higher
RMDs。因此，RMD（最低提款额）的数额正在增加。
tax rate for me than when I than the tax
我的税率比我以前的税率高。
benefit I got deferring it. But that's
延期付款给我带来的好处。但那是
unusual. Most people will benefit from
异常。大多数人都会从中受益
doing this because in their retirement
这样做是因为他们退休了
they won't have an income or their
他们将没有收入，或者他们的
income will be very modest and their tax
收入将非常有限，而且他们的税收也会很高。
rate will be equally modest and it will
利率同样会比较低，而且会
work out very nicely for them. But
对他们来说效果非常好。但
that's basically how that works. Does
基本上就是这样运作的。做
that make sense?
这样说得通吗？
&gt;&gt; It does. Yes. And and to try and
确实如此。是的。而且，还要尝试
summarize it um in a way that I fully
用一种我完全能理解的方式总结一下
understand to check I understand is
理解检查我理解是
every month when I'm paid I have an
每个月我拿到工资的时候，我都会……
opportunity before that money comes to
在那笔钱到来之前的机会
me to invest some of it and around the
让我投资其中的一部分，以及周围的
world whether it's Japan, Switzerland,
无论是日本、瑞士，还是世界各地
India, South Korea, Germany, Australia,
印度、韩国、德国、澳大利亚
UK, Canada, there's always some kind of
英国、加拿大，总是会有某种……
system
系统
&gt;&gt; of this, right?
就是这样，对吧？
&gt;&gt; Yeah. So I can say okay I'm going to get
是的。所以我可以说，好的，我要去拿
paid
有薪酬的
$1,000 this month. I'm gonna put a $100
本月1000美元。我打算投100美元。
of that before I even get it into one of
在我把它放进其中一个之前，就已经是这样了。
these investment accounts. It's not
这些投资账户。它不是
going to be taxed until
将被征税直至
&gt;&gt; and your employer might match part of it
你的雇主可能会匹配一部分费用。
or all of it.
或者全部。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. So, my employer might also add
是的。所以，我的雇主可能还会加上
$100 to it [clears throat] or or part of
100美元给它[清嗓子]或或一部分
it. That's going to compound over time.
它。随着时间的推移，这种情况会不断恶化。
I can take it out whenever I want, but
我可以随时把它拿出来，但是
if I take it out early, I get a penalty.
如果我提前出手，就会被罚。
&gt;&gt; And you pay tax.
而且你还要缴税。
&gt;&gt; And I pay tax. But assuming that I'm not
而且我还要缴税。但假设我不是
going to be earning as much as I do now
将来收入会和现在一样多。
when I'm older, when I take it out at 65
等我老了，等我65岁的时候把它拿出来
years old, I'm still going to pay tax,
虽然我年纪不小了，但我还是要缴税。
but a low rate of tax.
但税率很低。
&gt;&gt; There's no penalty at that point, but
那时不会受到处罚，但是
and presumably you'll be at a lower tax
而且你的税负大概也会降低。
rate, right?
是利率，对吧？
&gt;&gt; So it really only works if you're at a
所以它只有在你处于……时才真正有效。
lower tax rate when you're older.
年纪越大，税率越低。
&gt;&gt; Exactly. So most people work and then
确切地。所以大多数人先工作，然后……
and then they retire at a certain age
然后他们在达到一定年龄后退休。
and that income from their job goes
他们从工作中获得的收入
away. So by definition, they're in a
离开。所以根据定义，它们处于……
much lower tax bracket. So for the vast
税率低得多。所以对于广大而言
majority of people, this works out very
对大多数人来说，这非常有效。
nicely.
很好。
&gt;&gt; And you talk about, you know, because
你谈到，你知道，因为
people will will still have to make a
人们仍然需要做出选择
decision what they want to invest in,
他们决定投资什么，
&gt;&gt; right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; Where do you think we should be
你觉得我们应该在哪里？
investing our money at this moment of
此刻投资我们的资金
time? The for the average person, what
时间？对于普通人来说，什么
what should they be putting their money
他们应该把钱投到哪里呢？
into with everything you see happening
把你看到的一切事情都融入其中。
in the world?
在世界上？
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; You said not Bitcoin, but what where
你说不是比特币，而是其他什么东西？
should we put it?
我们应该放吗？
&gt;&gt; I'm an advocate of investing in
我提倡投资于
broad-based lowcost stock index funds.
覆盖面广、成本低廉的股票指数基金。
&gt;&gt; What is that? That is an example of that
那是什么？这就是一个例子。
is VTSAX which is Vanguard's total stock
VTSAX 是 Vanguard 的总股本。
market index fund. It invests in
市场指数基金。它投资于
virtually every publicly traded company
几乎所有上市公司
in the United States of America. That's
在美国。那是
very the number of those varies, but
这些数量差异很大，但是
it's roughly 3,600 companies.
大约有3600家公司。
&gt;&gt; So you're basically investing in
所以你基本上是在投资
America.
美国。
&gt;&gt; There are a lot of private companies
有很多私营公司
that I that I'm not invested in, but I'm
也就是说，我没有投入资金，但我
in every publicly traded company in in
在每家上市公司中
the country. And that means everybody
这个国家。这意味着所有人
from the factory floor to the CEO is
从工厂车间到首席执行官
working to make me richer. Now, some of
努力让我变得更富有。现在，一些
those companies are going to do
这些公司将会这样做
extraordinarily well and they're going
他们表现得非常好，而且进展顺利。
to succeed dramatically. And because
取得巨大成功。而且因为
this fund, as most funds like it are, is
这个基金，就像大多数同类基金一样，是
cap weighted and I'll explain that in a
市值加权，我稍后会解释。
minute. The more successful the company
分钟。公司越成功
is, the more of it I will own. So cap
也就是说，我拥有的就越多。所以上限
weighted simply means that the largest
加权仅仅意味着最大的
larger the market capitalization of the
市值越大
company is
公司是
&gt;&gt; the valuation
估值
&gt;&gt; the valuation [clears throat] right the
估值[清嗓子]正好
market capital the larger that is the
市值越大，就越有价值。
greater the percentage of the fund it
基金所占比例越大
will represent. So, you may have heard
将代表。所以，你可能听说过
people say that the top 10 companies in
人们说，排名前十的公司
the S&amp;P 500 have an outsized
标普500指数的涨幅异常大。
representation
表示
uh percentage- wise of what they well
呃，就他们所取得的成就而言，百分比是多少？
that's the reason it's it's cap
这就是它达到顶峰的原因。
weighted. So, I benefit from that
加权。所以，我从中受益。
success. Right now, if one of those
成功。现在，如果其中一个
companies falters
公司步履蹒跚
and
和
starts failing on their execution or a
开始在执行方面出现问题，或者
more aggressive, better organized
更具攻击性，组织性更强
competitor comes along and displaces
竞争对手出现并取代了
them, then they will drift away. But I'm
然后它们就会随波逐流。但我
okay with that because whatever that new
没问题，因为不管那是什么新事物
competitor is, I don't have to predict
竞争对手是谁，我不需要预测
who it is. I will own them. And that's a
是谁？我会拥有它们。而那是一个
process that I refer to as
我称之为过程
self-cleansing. I'm very proud of that
自清洁。我为此感到非常自豪。
term that I that I coined. So, a great
我创造的术语。所以，很棒
example of that is Sears. When I was a
西尔斯百货就是一个例子。当我还是个……的时候
kid, Sears, company you may not even be
孩子，西尔斯，这家公司你可能根本不认识。
aware of, but Sears was the Walmart and
我知道，但西尔斯就是沃尔玛，
Amazon of its time combined, but Sears
亚马逊是当时所有同类产品的总和，但西尔斯百货
at the turn of the last century, the
在上个世纪之交，
turn of the 1800s, looked around and
19世纪初，环顾四周，
said, you know, we have these
我说，你知道，我们有这些
brickandmortar stores, but there are all
实体店，但也有所有
these people living out in rural areas
这些居住在农村地区的人们
who are never going to get to our
他们永远也到不了我们这里。
brickandmortar stores. We could send
实体店。我们可以发送
them cataloges. Does this begin to sound
它们目录。这听起来是不是有点……
familiar? And then they could send us
熟悉的？然后他们就可以派我们来。
letters and money ordering things from
信件和汇款单
our catalog that we could then ship to
我们可以将产品目录寄送给您。
them. So they became, you know, Walmart
他们。所以他们就变成了，你知道的，沃尔玛。
with the brick-andmortar stores and then
先是实体店，然后
Amazon of his time absolutely dominated
他那个时代的亚马逊公司绝对占据主导地位。
for 100 years. If you had said to
一百年。如果你曾说过
somebody when I was first uh investing
我刚开始投资的时候，有人……
in the 1970s that Sears Sears built the
20世纪70年代，西尔斯百货公司（Sears）……
biggest building on the planet back in
地球上最高的建筑
the '7s, what was then known as the
7世纪70年代，当时被称为
Sears Tower in Chicago. If you had said
芝加哥的西尔斯大厦。如果你说过
Sears its days are numbered, you would
西尔斯百货的末日也快到了，你会……
have been laughed at. But its days were
曾被人嘲笑。但它的日子是
numbered because leaner, more aggressive
编号是因为更精简、更具攻击性
competitors came along and ate its
竞争对手出现并蚕食了它的市场份额。
lunch. Nobody could have predicted that.
午餐。谁也无法预料到这一点。
Certainly not me, but I didn't have to
当然不是我，但我也不必这么做。
if I own the index because then when
如果我拥有该指数，那么当
Walmart came along and then later Amazon
沃尔玛出现了，后来亚马逊也出现了。
and Sears faded away, I own those as
西尔斯百货公司倒闭了，我拥有那些……
well. That's that self-cleansing
出色地。这就是自清洁。
process.
过程。
&gt;&gt; And just for anyone that really doesn't
还有，对于那些真的不了解的人来说……
understand this at all, you're not
如果你完全不明白这一点，你就错了。
actually having to do anything because
实际上不必做任何事，因为
that index fund is just automatically
那个指数基金只是自动地
making the decisions.
做出决定。
&gt;&gt; Exactly. I don't have to do anything. I
确切地。我什么都不用做。我
just have to own it and I can own it
我只需要拥有它，我就能拥有它。
forever. So, if I went and I bought
永远。所以，如果我去买了
Sears stock as an example back in the
以西尔斯股票为例，回到过去……
day, well, whenever you own an
一天，嗯，每当你拥有一个
individual stock, you're going to be
个股，你将会
thinking about, okay, how long am I
我在想，好吧，我到底有多长？
going to own this? And what is going to
打算拥有它吗？接下来会发生什么？
trigger my sale of this particular
触发我出售这件特定商品
asset? And what I mean, what has to
资产？我的意思是，必须
happen to it that would make me not want
如果发生什么事，我会不想再要它了。
to own it anymore? And then, if I want
还能拥有它吗？然后，如果我想要
to get rid of it and I want something in
摆脱它，我想要一些东西。
the same space, what do I buy? Do I buy
同样的空间，我该买什么？我买吗？
this new upstart Walmart? you know, do I
这家新开的沃尔玛？你知道，我
buy this Amazon that back in the 90s is
买这个亚马逊，那是90年代的事了。
run by this wacko guy, Jeff Bezos, who
由这个古怪的家伙杰夫·贝佐斯运营，
kept saying, "No, profits don't matter.
一直说：“不，利润不重要。”
Profits don't matter." What who's who
利润并不重要。” 谁是谁
invests in a CEO that says profits don't
投资一位声称利润不会增长的首席执行官
matter? I mean, that's nuts, right? But
事情？我的意思是，这太疯狂了，对吧？但
those are the kinds of things you have
这些都是你拥有的东西。
to be have to be thinking about if you
你必须考虑你是否
own individual stocks. I don't have to
持有个股。我不必
think about any of that owning the index
想想看，拥有指数会是什么样的体验？
because if Jeff Bezos turns out that his
因为如果杰夫·贝佐斯最终被证明是他的
wackiness is brilliance, which it turns
古怪即是才华，它能改变一切。
out it was, then he's going to rise to
既然他已经出局了，那么他就会崛起。
the top, which it turns out Amazon did,
最终，亚马逊做到了这一点。
and I benefited from that. If it turns
而我从中受益匪浅。如果它转
out it was just wackiness, it would have
结果发现这只是胡闹，本来应该是这样的。
just faded away as a lot of companies
就像很多公司一样，就这样逐渐消失了。
have. But that wouldn't have mattered
有。但这无关紧要。
cuz whatever succeeds, I will I will own
因为无论成功与否，我都将拥有。
and benefit from. I was asking um the
并从中受益。我当时在问……
research team beforehand
研究团队事先
&gt;&gt; in the last 10 years which index fund
过去十年中，哪只指数基金
has performed the very very best
表现非常非常出色
&gt;&gt; and it said that the NASDAQ 100 which is
报告称，纳斯达克100指数是
very techheavy
技术含量很高
&gt;&gt; right
正确的
&gt;&gt; has performed at almost 20% a year for
近年来，其年增长率接近20%。
the last 10 years and when I think about
过去十年，当我回想起……
what's going on in the world at the
世界正在发生什么？
moment and the advent of this new
这一刻以及这一新时代的到来
technology called AI which is driving
驱动技术被称为人工智能（AI）。
everything it seems and our lives are
一切似乎都是如此，我们的生活也是如此。
going to become way more technological
将会变得更加科技化
with robots bots and automation and full
借助机器人、自动化和全面
self-driving. It appears to me like if
自动驾驶。在我看来，如果
there was ever a great time to be
曾经有过一段美好的时光
investing in an index fund, one should
投资指数基金时，应该
aim at the very techheavy index funds
瞄准科技股权重极高的指数基金
like the NASDAQ 100.
就像纳斯达克100指数一样。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; Is that is is that logical thinking or
那是逻辑思维吗？
is that
就是
&gt;&gt; it's it's logical think? Yes. So first
这是合乎逻辑的想法吗？是的。首先
of all it's logical thinking and
这一切都是逻辑思维和
actually had you done that same analysis
实际上，你是否也做过同样的分析？
10 years ago you would have done better
十年前你会做得更好。
than than uh VTSAX right because
比 VTSAX 还不如，对吧？
technology has absolutely dominated for
技术已经完全主导了……
the last 10 years it is a reasonable
过去十年，这是一个合理的
speculation that that will continue into
有猜测认为这种情况会持续下去
the future.
未来。
&gt;&gt; So why don't you
所以你为什么不呢？
&gt;&gt; for some period of time?
持续一段时间？
&gt;&gt; Well because the truth is that
因为事实是……
technology has not always dominated.
技术并非一直占据主导地位。
We're not going to go backwards though,
但我们不会走回头路。
are we?
是吗？
&gt;&gt; Well, no, but the point is that that it
不，但重点是……
changes. So, just like in my Sears
变化。所以，就像我在西尔斯百货公司一样。
example, Sears would have been at the
例如，西尔斯百货当时就在那里。
top of the index for a long time and
长期位居指数榜首
then it drifted away and got replaced.
然后它漂走了，被替换掉了。
So, that's an individual stock. Sectors
所以，这是一只个股。行业
of stocks have also done that over time,
随着时间的推移，股票也出现了这种情况。
right? So, right now the dominant sector
正确的？所以，目前主导行业
is tech. Wasn't always the case. might
是科技。情况并非一直如此。可能
not always be the case in the future. I
未来未必总是如此。我
don't know cuz I can't see the future. I
我不知道，因为我看不到未来。我
understand people who would say that
理解那些会这么说的人
clearly that's the best bet to go with
显然，这是最佳选择。
tech and your crystal [clears throat]
科技和你的水晶[清嗓子]
ball is clearer than mine and you might
你的球比我的更清晰，你可能
very well be right. But I don't have a
很有可能你说得对。但我没有
crystal ball and I don't have to worry
有了水晶球，我就不用担心了。
about that owning the total stock market
关于拥有整个股票市场
because if you're right, I will still
因为如果你是对的，我仍然会
benefit very nicely. Thank you very
好处非常明显。非常感谢
much.
很多。
If you're wrong,
如果你错了，
whatever replaces it, I will own.
无论它被什么取代，我都拥有它。
&gt;&gt; So, you have an analogy you came up with
所以，你想到了一个类比。
that involves beer and a glass,
那需要用到啤酒和玻璃杯，
&gt;&gt; right? Probably came up with a drinking
正确的？可能想出了一个喝酒的办法
beer. We go ahead.
啤酒。我们继续。
&gt;&gt; Well, show me show me the analogy.
好，请给我看看这个类比。
&gt;&gt; So,
所以，
thanks for not Whoa.
谢谢你没有发出“哇”的惊叹。
&gt;&gt; Oh, here we go.
哦，开始了。
&gt;&gt; I was going to say, thanks for not
我本来想说，谢谢你没有
shaking up the can.
摇晃罐子。
&gt;&gt; So, beer, right? So, I'm pouring it
所以，啤酒，对吧？所以，我正在倒它。
right down the middle. So, we get a nice
正好在正中间。所以，我们得到了一个不错的
thick head. That's even a little thicker
头很厚。那还要更厚一些。
than I hoped for. Okay. So,
比我预期的还要好。好的。所以，
imagine for a second. Right now, we have
想象一下。目前，我们有
a glass and we can see exactly how much
用玻璃杯，我们就能清楚地看到有多少
foam there is and how much actual beer
泡沫有多少？实际啤酒量又是多少？
there is, right? But imagine this was
确实有，对吧？但想象一下，如果……
that I poured it into this vessel
我把它倒进了这个容器里。
instead where we couldn't see that.
相反，我们却看不到这一点。
The analogy is the stock market. So,
这就像股票市场一样。所以，
when most people think of the stock
当大多数人想到股票时
market and when most people turn on uh
市场以及大多数人打开……的时候
CNBC, they turn on, you know, they look
CNBC，他们打开电视，你知道，他们会看
at at at the investment news and what
在投资新闻中，以及什么
have you, it's all this churning and
你明白吗，这一切都在翻腾涌动。
trading, you know, what stocks are hot
交易，你知道，就是交易哪些股票热门。
now, what stocks are rising, what stocks
现在，哪些股票在上涨？哪些股票？
are falling, what's, you know, it's all
正在下降，你知道，这一切都是
this trading. That's not the simple path
这项交易。那不是一条简单的路
to wealth. That's the foam, right? So
致富。那是泡沫，对吧？所以
the value in a stock, whatever the stock
股票的价值，无论股票是什么
is, what makes up the price of that
也就是说，这个价格是由哪些因素构成的？
stock is a combination of two things. It
股票是两件事的结合体。它
is the beer and it is the foam. And the
是啤酒，也是泡沫。以及
problem is unlike that glass,
问题不在于那块玻璃，
it's in a vessel like this. So it's hard
它装在这样的容器里。所以这很难
to see exactly how much beer there is as
看看究竟有多少啤酒
opposed to how much foam there is.
相反的是泡沫的多少。
&gt;&gt; And the beer is the value. The foam is
而啤酒本身就很有价值。泡沫是
the speculation.
猜测。
&gt;&gt; Exactly. The beer is the fundamental
确切地。啤酒是根本
operating value of the company, right?
公司的运营价值，对吧？
The sales and the expenses and the money
销售额、支出和资金
that's left over that you call profits,
剩下的部分就是你所说的利润。
right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; So that's the beer. The foam is what the
这就是啤酒。泡沫就是……
market
市场
determines that's worth at any given
决定其在任何给定时刻的价值
moment based on emotion,
基于情感的瞬间，
&gt;&gt; based and hype and speculation and fear
基于炒作、猜测和恐惧
and greed. And so up here, right, is the
以及贪婪。所以，这里，对吧，就是……
total value of the stock,
股票总价值
&gt;&gt; right? Exactly. The total value of the
正确的？确切地。总价值
stock. But this is all foam that can
库存。但这都是泡沫，
come and go very quickly, right? So let
来去很快，对吧？所以，让我们
think about Tesla for an example, right?
以特斯拉为例，对吧？
Tesla has a lot of foam cuz a lot of
特斯拉有很多泡沫材料，因为很多
people are speculating about the great
人们都在猜测伟大的
things Tesla's going to do in the
特斯拉未来将要做的事情
future. robotic cars, humanoid robots,
未来。无人驾驶汽车、人形机器人
you know, all these kinds of things
你知道，所有这些事情
which very may well come to pass. I
这很有可能成为现实。我
mean, Elon Musk is a stunningly
也就是说，埃隆·马斯克是一位令人惊叹的……
brilliant guy. So, who knows? But that's
真是个天才。谁知道呢？但那是
the speculation. That's the foam. The
猜测。那是泡沫。这
underlying beer of Tesla, the actual
特斯拉的底层啤酒，实际上
operating company, does not justify the
运营公司，这并不能证明其合理性
price of the stock. I mean, the the PE
股票价格。我的意思是，体育课
ratio of Tesla, you can look it up, is
特斯拉的比率，你可以查一下，是
some huge number, right? So there's a
是个很大的数字，对吧？所以，这里有一个
lot of speculation, a lot of foam in
很多猜测，很多泡沫。
Tesla. Now if things go to plan, then
特斯拉。如果一切按计划进行，那么
that foam will become as as in our
那种泡沫会变得像我们一样。
example, you notice the foam is
例如，你会注意到泡沫是
dissipating. We're getting more and more
消散。我们越来越
beer. If things go to plan for Tesla,
啤酒。如果特斯拉的计划按部就班地进行，
that's what will happen. The foam will
事情就是这样发展的。泡沫将
will eventually settle out into more and
最终会稳定下来，变得更加……
more beer, and Tesla will justify that
多喝点啤酒，特斯拉就会觉得这很合理。
high price and maybe then some. And I
价格很高，而且可能还会更高。我
guess Warren Buffett's greatness, if
猜猜沃伦·巴菲特的伟大之处，如果
I've interpreted his writing correctly,
我对他的文章的解读是正确的。
and why he was often considered as the
以及他为何经常被认为是
greatest investor of all time, was he
他是史上最伟大的投资者吗？
was able to pay for stocks where it was
能够支付股票的价格
mainly beer. And he paid at the price of
主要是啤酒。他为此付出了代价。
the beer, not for the foam.
是啤酒本身，不是泡沫。
&gt;&gt; Or he he looked for times where the
或者他寻找着这样的时刻
sentiment was so negative that he was
他的情绪非常消极，以至于
actually paying a little less than the
实际上支付的金额比……略少
price of the beer. Benjamin Graham who
啤酒的价格。本杰明·格雷厄姆
who wrote uh the intelligent investor
谁写了《聪明的投资者》？
who was a mentor to Warren Buffett
他是沃伦·巴菲特的导师
uh basically said what you should do is
呃，基本上就是说你应该怎么做……
look for value companies and try to
寻找具有价值的公司并尝试
determine where the beer is and then try
确定啤酒在哪里，然后尝试
to see if you can get a buying
看看能不能找到买家
opportunity watch it where you can buy
机会难得，快来看看哪里可以买到
it for less than the actual value of the
它的价格低于其实际价值
operation. That's ideal. And in those
手术。那真是太好了。而在这些
days when there wasn't so much
以前的日子里没有那么多东西
information freely available that was
可自由获取的信息是
probably a little easier to do. What
可能更容易一些。什么
Warren Buffett has said since then and
沃伦·巴菲特此后曾表示……
that's a great foundation if you're
如果你……，那将是一个很好的基础。
going to pick individual stocks. But
准备挑选个股。但
what Warren Buffett has said since then
沃伦·巴菲特此后说过的话
is he learned and I think and you don't
他学识渊博，我认为，而你不这么认为。
quote me on this but I think it was
请引用我的话，但我认为就是
Charlie Munger who actually made this
查理·芒格才是真正做出这个决定的人。
point to him that it's going to be very
向他指出，这将非常
very hard in this day and age even when
在当今时代，即使如此，也很难做到。
they started back in the 60s to find
他们早在 60 年代就开始寻找
companies where you can actually buy it
你可以在哪些公司买到它
for less than the actual beer value. So
价格低于啤酒的实际价值。所以
don't try to do that. Just try to find
别那样做。试着找找看。
companies that you can pay a fair price
你可以支付合理价格的公司
for that have a lot of beer in the mix
为此，混合物中加入了大量的啤酒。
that are mostly beer. Because if you buy
主要是啤酒。因为如果你买
those companies, they are by definition
这些公司，从定义上来说，就是
very well-run companies, strong brands,
管理完善的公司，强大的品牌
big moes around them, which makes them
它们周围有很多大毛，这使得它们
hard to compete.
竞争非常激烈。
&gt;&gt; I guess to do this, you're going to have
我想，要做到这一点，你需要……
to have a framework for valuing a
建立一个评估框架
company.
公司。
&gt;&gt; Exactly. And you're going to have to
确切地。你必须……
have great discipline,
具有高度自律性，
&gt;&gt; which is
即
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; hard. And that's what you know as Warren
难的。这就是你所认识的沃伦。
Buffett said I was blessed with an
巴菲特说我很幸运拥有……
ability to allocate capital effectively
有效配置资本的能力
and that's basically what he has done.
他基本上就是这么做的。
He's has capital and he is got the
他有资金，而且他拥有……
ability to look at different companies
能够考察不同的公司
and say of all the different companies I
在所有不同的公司中，我
could allocate capital to he's pretty
可以把资金分配给他，他很漂亮
skilled at at picking the ones that are
擅长挑选那些
are the best bets. One of the things
是最佳选择。其中一件事
that I really admired about Warren
我非常欣赏沃伦的这一点。
Buffett was his ability to do nothing,
巴菲特的过人之处在于他能够什么都不做。
&gt;&gt; which is one of the key things because
这是关键因素之一，因为
that goes back to Charlie Munger's
那要追溯到查理·芒格的时代。
thing, don't get in the way of your
别妨碍你。
compounding, right?
复利效应，对吧？
&gt;&gt; And there has been recent times where I
最近也出现过这种情况……
think we can all think of where
我想我们都能想到哪里
using your beer analogy, something
用你啤酒的比喻来说，某事
happens in the world and the true value
世界上发生的事情及其真正的价值
of a company
一家公司
is higher than the selling price. I.e.
高于售价。 IE。
If you go back to March 2020 during the
如果你回到2020年3月，你会发现……
the market selloff when the pandemic
疫情期间的市场抛售
happened and everybody panicked, Amazon,
事情发生了，大家都慌了，亚马逊也一样。
for example, the stock briefly dropped
例如，该股票曾短暂下跌
below roughly to about $1,500
低于大约 1500 美元
per share.
每股。
&gt;&gt; Mhm.
嗯。
&gt;&gt; Well [clears throat] below its intrinsic
嗯[清嗓子]低于其内在
value um because people were panicking,
因为人们当时很恐慌，所以价值……
right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; Uh and then it quickly rebounded again
嗯，然后它又迅速反弹了。
past $3,000
超过 3,000 美元
a share. So theoretically, if you had
一份。所以理论上讲，如果你有
noticed that drop, you could have made a
注意到那次下跌了吗？你本来可以做点什么的。
100% return on your money. Um,
投资回报率100%。嗯，
&gt;&gt; and by the extension, the whole market
进而，整个市场
did that.
做到了。
&gt;&gt; The whole market dropped, too. Yeah.
整个市场也下跌了。是的。
&gt;&gt; So, you could have done that with your
所以，你本来可以用你的……
index fund. This is why if you panicked
指数基金。这就是为什么如果你惊慌失措
and sold.
已售出。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Let's say you owned Amazon or you owned
假设你拥有亚马逊，或者你拥有
VTSAX and you panicked and sold, well,
VTSAX，你惊慌失措地抛售了，好吧。
you would have you would have lost
你会失去
everything and then it it recovered. So,
一切都恢复正常了。所以，
it works both ways. That's why I said
两种方式都适用。这就是我为什么说
earlier in our conversation, you you
在我们之前的谈话中，你
have to stay invested so that the dip
必须继续投资，才能在下跌时获利。
doesn't matter. and if anything take
没关系。如果有什么事的话……
advantage of the dip and buy more. So
趁着价格下跌多买一些。所以
you own Amazon, you see it dip, you say,
你持有亚马逊股票，看到股价下跌，你会说：
"Well, I still believe in the company. I
“嗯，我仍然相信这家公司。
still think it's a good company and it's
我仍然认为这是一家好公司，而且
got a good future." Or then maybe you
前途光明。”或者也许你
buy some more in the dip and you do
趁低买入一些，你就可以这么做了。
still better. But the important thing is
更好了。但重要的是……
you don't sell when it's down because
股价下跌时你不会卖出，因为
there's panic in the air.
空气中弥漫着恐慌的气氛。
&gt;&gt; And I think this is um this speaks to a
我认为这说明……
broader sentiment throughout this
贯穿整个事件的更广泛情绪
conversation which is to do what others
对话的内容就是做别人做的事
don't do. You know, and Warren Buffett's
不要这样做。你知道，还有沃伦·巴菲特的
famous for saying be fearful when others
他因说过“当别人害怕时，你要感到害怕”而闻名。
are greedy and greedy when others are
他们贪婪，而且当别人贪婪时，他们却不贪婪。
fearful. But generally the sentiment on
可怕。但总的来说，人们对……的看法
social media, especially for younger
社交媒体，尤其是对年轻人而言。
generations and especially for men,
几代人，尤其是对男性而言，
which is supported by the data, is that
数据也支持这一观点。
the way to make money is by like trading
赚钱的方法之一是进行股票交易。
crypto or by right
加密货币或依法
&gt;&gt; I mean there's so many people that sell
我的意思是，卖东西的人太多了。
this is such a we need to address this.
这是我们需要解决的问题。
&gt;&gt; You know, it's a platform.
你知道，它是一个平台。
&gt;&gt; It's a gambling. It's just gambling.
这是赌博。这纯粹是赌博。
&gt;&gt; It's it's a gambling platform. And so
这是一个赌博平台。所以
that's going, you know, people sometimes
你知道，有时候人们会那样做。
say to me, you know, I'd never invest in
告诉我，你知道，我永远不会投资
the stock market. It's just gambling. I
股票市场。这纯粹是赌博。我
say, well, you're half right. Our foam
嗯，你说的对了一半。我们的泡沫
[clears throat] is all dissipated. But
[清嗓子] 都消散了。但
if there were still foam here, I would
如果这里还有泡沫的话，我会
say yes. If you're doing it short-term
答应下来。如果你是短期执行的话
and you're playing with the foam,
你在玩泡沫塑料，
absolutely is no different than going to
绝对与去那里没有区别
Las Vegas. If you're investing for the
拉斯维加斯。如果你是为了……而投资
beer, it's an entirely different story.
啤酒的情况就完全不同了。
And you're investing for the long term.
而且你是在进行长期投资。
And there's lots of young people that
而且有很多年轻人
are being tempted into buying a course
被诱惑购买课程
that's going to help them learn how to
那将帮助他们学习如何……
trade.
贸易。
&gt;&gt; That's great for the people selling the
这对销售人员来说太好了。
course.
课程。
&gt;&gt; There's such an there's such an
有这样一个有这样一个
incredible like ir obvious irony to the
难以置信，就像他们明显的讽刺一样
idea that I have some secret about
我觉得我藏着一些秘密
trading that's really going to make, you
真正能让你获利的交易，你
know, that is capable of making one
要知道，它能够制造一个
wealthy,
富裕，
&gt;&gt; right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; And I'm going to give it to you
我会把它给你
&gt;&gt; or even sell it to you.
甚至可以卖给你。
&gt;&gt; Why would I need to if it worked,
如果真的有效，我为什么还需要这么做呢？
&gt;&gt; right? Like this is such an obvious
正确的？这明明显而易见啊
question to me. Like why would I need to
向我提问。我为什么要这么做？
sell it if it worked?
如果有效就卖掉？
&gt;&gt; It it is the obvious question. I mean,
这是一个显而易见的问题。我是说，
you know,
你知道，
&gt;&gt; and I feel sorry. I have great empathy
我感到很遗憾。我非常有同理心。
because the people that buy these things
因为买这些东西的人
are people that are desperate to get out
那些迫切想要逃离的人
of their financial situation and they
他们的财务状况以及他们
run out of options and so it's very
已经没有其他选择，所以非常
compelling to hear that there's some
听到这方面有一些令人信服的消息
secret that you can predict the stock
你可以预测股票的秘密
market. It's very compelling.
市场。它非常引人入胜。
&gt;&gt; You know, in another interview I I said
你知道，在另一次采访中我说过
one time we were talking about this
有一次我们谈到这件事
[clears throat] same line of
[清嗓子] 同一条线
conversation we're having and I said,
我们正在交谈，我说，
you know, I blame my mother. I would be
你知道吗，我得怪我妈。我会
a lot richer if she hadn't instilled a
如果她没有灌输这种思想，她会富有得多。
conscience in me. You know, she's cost
我内心的良知。你知道，她很贵
me millions of dollars instilling this
我花了数百万美元灌输这种理念。
conscience. I could have courses. I
良心。我可以选修课程。我
could be, you know,
有可能，你知道，
&gt;&gt; but no, I am saying that there is a path
不，我的意思是，有一条路可走。
that will give you great results
这将给你带来很好的结果
and it's a pretty well proven path at
而且这是一条相当成熟的路径。
this point.
这一点。
So many of us are pursuing passive forms
我们当中很多人都在追求被动形式
of income and to build side businesses
增加收入并发展副业
in order to help us cover our bills. And
为了帮助我们支付账单。和
that opportunity is here with our
机会就在眼前！
sponsor Stan, a business that I co-own.
赞助 Stan，这是我共同拥有的企业。
It is the platform that can help you
这是一个可以帮助你的平台
take full advantage of your own
充分利用你自己的优势
financial situation. Stan enables you to
财务状况。 Stan 使您能够
work for yourself. It makes selling
为自己工作。它使销售变得容易
digital products, courses, memberships,
数字产品、课程、会员资格、
and more simple products more scalable
更简单的产品，更具可扩展性
and easier to do. You can turn your
而且更容易做到。你可以把你的
ideas into income and get the support to
将想法转化为收入并获得支持
grow whatever you're building. And we've
无论你建造什么，都要让它生长壮大。我们已经
just launched Dare to Dream. It's for
刚刚推出了“敢于梦想”项目。这是为了
those who are ready to make the shift
那些准备好做出转变的人
from thinking to building, from planning
从构思到建造，从规划
to actually doing the thing. It's about
真正去做这件事。这是关于
seeing that dream in your head and
在脑海中看到那个梦境
knowing exactly what it takes to bring
确切地知道带来什么
it to life. Enter to win $100,000 for
赋予它生命。参与即有机会赢取 10 万美元
your dream. All you have to do is share
你的梦想。你只需要分享即可。
what it is. Learn more at
它是什么？了解更多信息，请访问
daretodream.stan.store.
daretodream.stan.store。
This is something that I've made for
这是我为……制作的东西
you. I've realized that the DVO audience
你。我意识到DVO的观众
are strivvers. Whether it's in business
他们是奋斗者。无论是在商业领域还是其他领域。
or health, we all have big goals that we
对于健康而言，我们都有远大的目标，我们
want to accomplish. And one of the
想要达成的目标。其中之一
things I've learned is that when you aim
我学到的一点是，当你瞄准时
at the big big big goal, it can feel
在实现那个重大目标时，会感到
incredibly psychologically uncomfortable
极度心理不适
because it's kind of like being stood at
因为感觉就像站在……
the foot of Mount Everest and looking
珠穆朗玛峰脚下，眺望
upwards. The way to accomplish your
向上。实现目标的方法
goals is by breaking them down into tiny
实现目标的方法是将目标分解成小块。
small steps. And we call this in our
小步前进。我们称之为我们的
team the 1%. And actually this
团队中那1%的人。实际上，
philosophy is highly responsible for
哲学对此负有很大责任
much of our success here. So, what we've
我们在这里取得的成功很大程度上归功于此。所以，我们已经……
done so that you at home can accomplish
这样做是为了方便您在家完成
any big goal that you have is we've made
你们的任何远大目标，我们都实现了。
these 1% diaries and we released these
我们发布了这些1%的日记。
last year and they all sold out. So, I
去年全部售罄。所以，我
asked my team over and over again to
我反复要求我的团队
bring the diaries back, but also to
把日记带回来，但也要
introduce some new colors and to make
引入一些新颜色并制作
some minor tweaks to the diary. So, now
对日记进行了一些小修改。所以现在
we have a better range for you. So, if
我们为您提供更丰富的选择。所以，如果
you have a big goal in mind and you need
你心中有一个远大的目标，你需要
a framework and a process and some
一个框架、一个流程和一些
motivation, then I highly recommend you
如果你有动力，那么我强烈推荐你
get one of these diaries before they all
趁它们还没全部售罄之前，赶紧入手一本吧
sell out once again. And you can get
再次售罄。而且你可以获得
yours now at the diary.com where you can
现在就访问 diary.com，即可拥有属于你的 diary.com，你可以在那里……
get 20% off our Black Friday bundle. And
黑色星期五特惠套装享八折优惠。和
if you want the link, the link is in the
如果你想要链接，链接就在这里。
description below.
详情如下。
Do I need a financial adviser?
我需要财务顾问吗？
Cuz a lot of people out listening now
因为现在很多人都在听。
will be thinking, "Yeah, I will figure
会想，“嗯，我会想办法的。”
out my money situation when I have
当我有
enough money to pay a financial
有足够的钱来支付财务费用
adviser." Yeah, I think uh my attitude
顾问。” 是的，我想呃，我的态度
is by the time you know enough to choose
等你懂得足够多，能够做出选择的时候……
a good financial advisor, which is no
一位优秀的财务顾问，这并非易事。
easy task, you probably know enough to
这很简单，你可能已经掌握了足够的知识。
do it on your own, at least on the
至少在某一方面，要自己去做。
investing part. Now, there are life
投资部分。现在，生命存在
kinds of decisions where maybe advisors
可能需要顾问做出的决策类型
would be more useful, but again, you
会更有用，但是，再说一遍，你
have to be careful and and it takes you
必须小心谨慎，而且这需要你
you need to really educate yourself as
你需要好好学习一下。
to how advisers get paid. For instance,
关于顾问如何获得报酬。例如，
my attitudes, by the way, are colored by
顺便说一句，我的态度受到……的影响
the fact that I I hear so frequently
我经常听到这样的事实
from [clears throat] my followers about
来自[清嗓子]我的粉丝们关于
bad experiences with financial advisors.
与理财顾问的糟糕经历。
So, I have a negative opinion. To be
所以，我持否定态度。成为
fair, I know there are good ones out
好吧，我知道市面上有很多好东西。
there, and all due respect to those good
在那里，并且对那些好心人表示应有的尊重。
ones, but let's suppose you have a
一个，但假设你有一个
financial advisor who gets paid based on
财务顾问的薪酬基于
the assets under management, right?
管理资产规模，对吧？
&gt;&gt; The amount of the amount that you've
你已经拥有的金额
given them.
已经给了他们。
&gt;&gt; Exactly. Right. So, maybe it's 1%. So,
确切地。正确的。所以，也许是1%。所以，
you give them a million dollars and they
你给他们一百万美元，他们
get 1% a year to manage that money for
每年收取1%的费用来管理这笔钱。
for you. Let's suppose you go to that
为你。假设你去了那里
advisor and you say, "You know, Stephen,
顾问，然后你说，“你知道，斯蒂芬，
I've I've been thinking about paying off
我一直在考虑还清贷款。
my mortgage. I've got a half a million
我的房贷。我有五十万
dollar mortgage on this house. It's 6%.
这栋房子是用美元抵押贷款的。是6%。
Let's say it's 5%. So, in that middle
假设是 5%。所以，在中间
range, it's 5%. I'm thinking about
范围是 5%。我正在思考……
paying it off. What do you think?" Okay.
还清贷款。你觉得怎么样？好的。
Well, now Stephen has a bit of a dilemma
现在斯蒂芬有点左右为难了。
because
因为
he can certainly give you the most
他当然可以给你最多的
accurate financial advice he is capable
他能够提供准确的财务建议。
of giving you and answering that
给你并回答这个问题
question.
问题。
But if that leads him to say yes, pay
但如果这让他最终同意，那就付钱。
off the mortgage,
还清房贷
he has just reduced his income by half
他刚刚将收入减少了一半。
because when you pay off that mortgage,
因为当你还清房贷之后，
half a million dollars is going to go
五十万美元将要花出去
out from his management and paying off
摆脱他的管理并偿还债务
the mortgage company. So you have just
抵押贷款公司。所以你刚刚
asked Steven to give you advice
请史蒂文给你一些建议
potentially that is bad for Steven. Now
这可能对史蒂文不利。现在
if Steven's a honorable, capable,
如果史蒂文是一位正直、有能力的人，
honest guy, then maybe Steven does that.
如果史蒂文是个诚实的人，那他或许会那样做。
But let's suppose Stephen has two kids
但假设斯蒂芬有两个孩子
in college.
在大学里。
Let's suppose Steven just bought a boat.
假设史蒂文刚买了一艘船。
Let's suppose Steven is going through a
假设史蒂文正在经历……
divorce.
离婚。
Let's think about that. Maybe Steven, as
我们来思考一下这个问题。或许史蒂文，就像
honest and capable and and decent as he
他诚实、能干、正直。
ordinarily is, has financial pressures
通常情况下，存在财务压力
that might play a role, right? There is
这或许会起到一定作用，对吧？有
a conflict of interest frequently. So,
利益冲突经常发生。所以，
you have to understand how your advisor
你必须了解你的顾问是如何工作的
is being paid.
正在领取报酬。
&gt;&gt; How does your portfolio look? Where have
你的作品集看起来怎么样？哪里有
you allocated your money in terms of
你按以下方式分配了你的资金：
percentages? How much money do you have
百分比？你手头有多少钱？
in real estate versus cash versus index
房地产、现金和指数的对比
funds?
资金？
&gt;&gt; Well, I don't even think about about the
嗯，我根本没想过这个问题。
real estate. We have this cabin in
房地产。我们在这间小木屋里
Wisconsin on the lake and then we have a
威斯康星州湖畔，然后我们还有
condo in Florida. Um, they're both very
佛罗里达州的一套公寓。嗯，他们俩都很
modest, so pretty small part of our net
规模不大，所以只占我们网络的一小部分。
worth. I like to buy things from a
值得。我喜欢从……买东西
position of power.
权力地位。
My stocks, I'm probably about 80% in in
我的股票，大概有80%都投进去了。
VTSAX, total stock market index fund,
VTSAX，全股票市场指数基金
and probably 15% in bonds, a total bond
其中可能15%是债券，总计债券
market index fund, and then the other 5%
市场指数基金，以及另外 5%
in money market fund. I keep some money
货币市场基金。我留了一些钱
in uh the checking account to pay the
在支票账户中支付
bills. And to break it down a little
账单。简单来说
further for you, my wife and I both have
此外，我和我妻子都……
IAS. We have a regular IRA and a Roth
国际行政服务 (IAS)。我们有一个普通的个人退休账户（IRA）和一个罗斯个人退休账户（Roth IRA）。
IRA. So there are four IAS. All four of
个人退休账户（IRA）。所以，IAS共有四种。这四个人
them hold VTSAX. We have taxable
他们持有 VTSAX。我们有应税资产
accounts and part of that is VTSAX. Part
账户，其中一部分是 VTSAX。部分
of it is the bonds.
其中最重要的是债券。
&gt;&gt; What is a bond?
什么是债券？
&gt;&gt; A bond is money that you have lent to a
债券是你借给债权人的钱。
company or to the government. So when
公司或政府。所以当
you buy a bond, you are essentially
你购买债券，本质上就是
lending money to a company or a
向公司或
government entity. So they pay you
政府实体。所以他们会付钱给你
interest. So you will they companies and
兴趣。所以你会和这些公司合作
the governments sell bonds of various
各国政府出售各种债券。
maturities. So they can be very short
到期日。所以它们可以很短
like a money market fund is basically
就像货币市场基金基本上
very short-term bonds, you know, like 30
你知道，就是那种期限很短的债券，比如30年期的。
days or less, right? Which makes it the
几天之内就能搞定，对吧？这使得它成为
equivalent of cash. But you could buy a
等值的现金。但你可以买一个
a certificate of deposit is a kind of a
定期存单是一种
bond. So you could buy one of those for
纽带。所以你可以买一个来
3 months or 6 months or a year, 5 years,
3个月、6个月、1年、5年，
10 years, buy US treasuries going out 30
10年期，买入到期30年的美国国债
years.
年。
&gt;&gt; Why would I do that instead of buying
我为什么要那样做而不是购买呢？
the index fund?
指数基金？
&gt;&gt; So the index fund is stocks. It's it's
所以指数基金就是股票。是它的
very stocks as we talked about big
正如我们之前讨论的那样，股票数量非常多。
growth engine, great long-term, very
增长引擎，长期前景广阔，非常
volatile. [snorts] So if you want
易挥发的。 [嗤笑] 所以如果你想
something to smooth the ride, bonds are
债券是缓解旅途颠簸的良药。
not very good for long-term growth, but
不利于长期增长，但是
they are not nearly as volatile.
它们的波动性远没有那么大。
&gt;&gt; Are they so they're safer? short-term,
是为了更安全吗？短期的，
yes, because they're less volatile.
是的，因为它们的波动性较小。
Long-term, they tend to lose value to
从长远来看，它们往往会贬值。
inflation.
通货膨胀。
Stocks, on the other hand, are riskier
另一方面，股票的风险更大。
short-term because of the volatility,
由于波动性，短期内难以预测。
but long-term they outpace inflation and
但从长远来看，它们会跑赢通货膨胀。
so they are safer long term. So, it
所以从长远来看，它们更安全。所以，它
depends on your time horizon is which is
这取决于你的投资期限。
which is safer. But traditionally people
哪种更安全？但传统上人们
think of bonds as being safer and really
把债券看作更安全、更可靠的东西。
the way you should hear that is less
你应该这样理解：
volatile and stocks being riskier.
波动性大，股票风险更高。
You should hear that is more volatile.
你应该听说，这种情况更不稳定。
&gt;&gt; So is it broadly true to say that if we
那么，如果我们这样说，是否大致正确呢？
exclude your real estate 70% of your
排除您的房地产，占您总收入的 70%。
assets are in stocks, 20% in bonds and
资产配置为股票，20%为债券，
5% in cash?
5%现金？
&gt;&gt; Probably more 80 155.
可能更多是 80 155。
&gt;&gt; 80% stocks, 15 bonds cash. Okay. It's
80%股票，15%债券，现金。好的。它是
interesting because um
有趣是因为……
&gt;&gt; which would be considered very very
这将被认为非常非常
aggressive and I wouldn't necessarily
咄咄逼人，我未必会这么做。
recommend that for most people my age.
建议大多数和我同龄的人都这样做。
&gt;&gt; I thought it would be curious cuz we now
我觉得这会很有趣，因为我们现在
have this new alien amongst us called
我们之中出现了一个叫做……的新外星人
AI. I thought it would be curious if I
人工智能。我想如果我这样做会很有趣
went on Chatt and I asked Chatt the
我上了 Chatt，然后问了 Chatt
question. I'm a normal person who earns
问题。我是一个收入正常的普通人
$50,000 a year. I want to be financially
年薪5万美元。我希望经济独立
free in the future. Give me a one-s
未来免费。给我一个一
sentence answer based on all of the
根据所有内容给出句子答案
wisdom in the world taken from every
世间智慧源自方方面面
expert in investing ever.
投资领域的专家。
&gt;&gt; Why? I know what the right answer is. I
为什么？我知道正确答案是什么。我
don't know what the answer.
不知道答案是什么。
&gt;&gt; What do you think it's going to say?
你觉得它会说什么？
&gt;&gt; Read the simple path of wealth. I don't
阅读致富的简单方法。我不
think that's what it's going to say, but
我想它会这么说，但是
that's the right answer.
答案正确。
&gt;&gt; And the the simple path of wealth talks
而致富的简单途径
about three principles, right?
大概有三个原则，对吧？
&gt;&gt; Right.
正确的。
&gt;&gt; What are those three? I'm going to check
那三个是什么？我去查一下
it against what it says.
它与它所说的内容相悖。
&gt;&gt; Avoid debt.
避免负债。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Live on less than you earn. Invest the
量入为出。投资
surplus. It said, "Focus on saving and
剩余。它说，“重点是储蓄和
consistently invest in lowcost
持续投资低成本
broad-based index funds like the S&amp;P 500
像标普500指数基金这样的广泛型指数基金
while living below your means and
同时过着量入为出的生活
allowing compounding to work over time."
让复利效应随着时间的推移而发挥作用。
I then asked another question. How do I
然后我又问了一个问题。我该怎么做？
earn more?
赚更多钱？
&gt;&gt; I should sue them for mining my book.
我应该起诉他们盗用我的书稿。
&gt;&gt; Yeah, they probably did. [laughter]
是的，他们很可能这么做了。 [笑声]
I said, "How do I earn more?" What do
我问：“我怎样才能赚更多钱？”什么
you think? You know if you if you
您认为？你知道如果你如果你
thought if your daughter came to you and
想想如果你的女儿来找你……
said
说
&gt;&gt; earn more in a job or
在工作中赚更多钱
&gt;&gt; I just asked a very broad question which
我刚才问了一个非常宽泛的问题，
is I now and now how do I earn more was
现在我该如何赚更多钱？
my question.
我的问题。
&gt;&gt; I would say develop develop your skills.
我会说，要努力提升你的技能。
&gt;&gt; Okay.
好的。
&gt;&gt; It said to earn more focus on developing
它表示要更加注重发展
high demand skills.
高需求技能。
&gt;&gt; Oh there you go.
哦，找到了。
&gt;&gt; Seek opportunities for career
寻找职业发展机会
advancement. Explore side hustles or
进步。探索副业或
invest in assets that generate passive
投资于能产生被动收入的资产。
income like real estate or dividends.
例如房地产或股息等收入。
But I really think that you know I
但我真的觉得你知道我
really think there's a really important
我真的认为这非常重要
part there about developing high demand
其中一部分是关于发展高需求的
skills.
技能。
&gt;&gt; What are those going to be in the
这些会是什么？
future?
未来？
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; With AI because programming for instance
例如，人工智能编程就是一个例子。
used to be a very high demand skill and
曾经是一项需求量非常高的技能，
people said learn how to program. Yeah.
人们说要学习编程。是的。
&gt;&gt; From what I understand in the age of AI.
就我所了解的人工智能时代而言。
Yeah. That's not so much.
是的。没那么夸张。
&gt;&gt; I even think about my own life. At 18
我甚至会思考自己的生活。 18岁
years old I started learning about
我从几岁起就开始学习……
social media. I dropped out of
社交媒体。我辍学了。
university doing my business management
我在大学攻读工商管理专业
degree after one lecture and I started
一节课后我就获得了学位，然后就开始了。
learning about social media because I
学习社交媒体是因为我
was building a business in social media
在社交媒体领域建立业务
and technology and although that first
以及技术，尽管第一
business failed I I was 19 years old in
生意失败了，当时我19岁。
201 what 14 or something really
201 什么 14 之类的
understood this thing called social
理解了社交这东西
media which led me to spend a year as a
媒体让我花了一年时间……
consultant flying around the world to
顾问飞遍世界各地
all these companies doing social media
所有这些从事社交媒体的公司
one of those companies turned around and
其中一家公司扭亏为盈，
said it's been so great could you turn
他说这太棒了，你能转过来吗？
this into a company I said no I've been
我说不，我一直都是这样。
through the founder PT of starting a 3
通过创始人PT启动3
months later I said yes turned into a
几个月后，我答应了，结果却变成了
company called social chain and that
公司名为社交链，而且
changed my entire life
改变了我的一生
&gt;&gt; that worked out well
结果很好
&gt;&gt; high demand skill I had even though I
即使我拥有高需求技能，我依然如此
failed I had this high demand skill that
我失败了，我拥有一项高需求技能。
was honestly at the time paying me
当时确实在付我钱。
£70,000 a month
每月7万英镑
&gt;&gt; you probably had it because you went
你可能得过它，因为你去过
through the process of failing
通过失败的过程
&gt;&gt; yes
是的
&gt;&gt; failure is you know it used to be in
失败就是你知道它过去的样子。
some cultures that if you failed once
有些文化中，如果你失败一次……
that was it you were a pariah nobody
就这样，你成了个被人唾弃的无名之辈。
would even look at you anymore failure
甚至都不会再看你一眼了，失败者
in our culture is just a stepping stone
在我们的文化中，这只是一块垫脚石。
I've heard venture capitalists say they
我曾听风险投资家说过他们
won't even look at an entrepreneur to
甚至连看都不看一眼创业者。
fund if they haven't failed at least
如果他们至少还没有失败，就应该提供资金
once.
一次。
&gt;&gt; The advice I'd now give to my kids based
我现在会根据以下情况给孩子们提建议
on that is I would ask if my kids came
我会问我的孩子们是否来过
to me and said, "Dad, what should I go
他对我说：“爸爸，我该去哪儿？”
learn?" I would say
学习？”我会说
go and work for a startup. I said
去创业公司工作吧。我说
startup because you're going to be very
创业，因为你将会非常
close to the CEO and founder because
因为与首席执行官和创始人关系密切
there's going to be less desks. So,
办公桌数量将会减少。所以，
you're going to be closer to the
你会更接近
proximity. That is failing at the
距离近。这是失败之处
cutting edge. So if it's AI, I'd say go
前沿。所以如果是人工智能，我会说去吧
work for an AI startup. I I probably not
为一家人工智能初创公司工作。我可能不会
going to work out. You're probably going
去健身。你可能要走了
to be the company will be bust in a
这家公司最终会破产。
couple of months time, but you're going
还有几个月时间，但你就要走了。
to be so close to the failure.
离失败如此之近。
&gt;&gt; You will learn so much.
你会学到很多东西。
&gt;&gt; Yes.
是的。
&gt;&gt; I wish somebody had given me that
我希望有人能把那东西给我。
advice.
建议。
&gt;&gt; And that's that's like in a way I guess
某种程度上来说，大概就是这样吧。
roundabout way. What I did is I started
绕远路。我所做的就是开始
a company that failed at the very
一家从一开始就失败的公司
forefront of a wave coming into shore,
涌向海岸的波浪最前端，
which meant that as I hit, you know, as
这意味着，当我击球时，你知道，就像
the wave crashed down and I was left
海浪猛烈地拍打下来，我被留在了原地。
there on my surfboard, I now had this
我的冲浪板上，现在有了这个
high demand set of skills that people
人们需要掌握的高需求技能组合
were like begging me for, which set
就像在乞求我，哪一套
myself up. And frankly,
我自己爬起来。坦白说，
&gt;&gt; the D of a CEO would not be successful
首席执行官的D型人格不会成功
had I not spent the previous 10 years
如果我没花上这十年时间就好了
understanding how social media, content
了解社交媒体和内容
creation, growth worked.
创造和成长奏效了。
Is there a favorite story in this book
这本书里有没有你最喜欢的故事？
of yours?
你的？
&gt;&gt; Well, there's so many great ones. So,
嗯，有很多很棒的例子。所以，
&gt;&gt; share some.
分享一些。
&gt;&gt; I already I already alluded to my
我已经暗示过我的
favorite one, which is my friend Tom.
我最喜欢的是我的朋友汤姆。
You know, because he has I mean, Tom was
你知道，因为他有，我的意思是，汤姆是
a guy who got to the age of 62. He'd
一个活到62岁的人。他
been through multiple divorces. He lost
经历过多次离婚。他输了
his house to foreclosure. He lost his
他的房子将被取消抵押赎回权。他失去了
job. He was broke. He went bankrupt. And
工作。他破产了。他破产了。和
yet, his life has turned out pretty
然而，他的生活却变得相当不错。
well. He's an extraordinarily happy guy.
出色地。他是个非常快乐的人。
That's my favorite story. But the one of
那是我最喜欢的故事。但其中一个
the reasons I like this book so much and
我如此喜欢这本书的原因以及
one of the reasons candidly I did it is
坦白说，我这么做的原因之一是
if you read through it, you will find
如果你仔细阅读，你会发现
there are some stories from people who
有些人讲述了一些故事
were tech bros, right, who made big
他们是科技圈的兄弟，对吧，他们赚了很多钱
incomes and they read the simple path to
他们了解了收入的简单途径
wealth and applied and it worked very
财富和应用，而且效果非常好。
well for them. But there are many, many
对他们来说真是太好了。但是有很多很多。
more stories of people who have
更多关于拥有……的人的故事
accomplished this from much more humble
这一切都是从更加谦逊的起点实现的。
beginnings. Give me an example of
开端。请举一个例子
&gt;&gt; I have a very good friend of mine, high
我有一个非常好的朋友，他很厉害。
school buddy. I don't think he's ever
学校里的好朋友。我不认为他曾经
made more than $40,000 a year. He is
年收入超过4万美元。他是
financially independent because he
他经济独立是因为他
followed the basic principles that I
我遵循了以下基本原则
talk about in that book. I have a
那本书里有提到。我有一个
different friend and he was in the
另一个朋友，他当时也在。
financial business. He was living in
金融业务。他当时住在
Chicago and over lunch he told me that
芝加哥，午餐时他告诉我……
his Christmas bonus had come in at
他的圣诞奖金已经到账了
$800,000.
80万美元。
That's back in the mid '90s when that
那是在90年代中期。
was real money, right?
是真钱吧？
And he was already making, I don't know,
他当时已经在做，我不知道，
a million dollars a year or whatever it
一年一百万美元，或者其他什么数额
was, big income. And he was broke.
曾经收入很高。他当时身无分文。
And you see, most people listening this
你看，大多数听这首诗的人
thing, I said, "What are you talking
我说：“你在说什么？”
about? This guy got a bonus for 8.
关于？这家伙因为8分拿到了奖金。
People paid me $800,000 for a year. I'd
人们付给我80万美元，为期一年。 ID
be done forever, right? And that'd be my
就此结束了吗？那将是我的
nut. I'm good. How can he be broke?"
坚果。我很好。他怎么会破产呢？
Well, when you listen to him talk about
嗯，当你听他谈论……
the house, the cars, the schools, and
房子、汽车、学校，以及
you start doing the math, you realize
你开始计算，然后你意识到
that no, his income is not enough. He's
不，他的收入不够。他是
barely barely making it. So, here's a
勉强过关。所以，这里有一个
guy with a big income who is, unless he
一个收入很高的人，除非他
changes his ways, is never going to be
他会改变自己的行事方式，但永远不会改变。
financially independent. Financially
经济独立。财务方面
independent. Here's my guy with a tiny
独立的。这是我的朋友，他个子很小
income comparatively who got there. I've
收入与达到目标的人相比如何。我已经
come to believe that a large income
逐渐相信高收入
actually can be an impediment to
实际上可能成为一种阻碍
accomplishing it. And my reasoning for
实现了它。我的理由是
this is that I think people who have a
我认为，拥有这种能力的人
large income are much more likely to be
高收入者更有可能……
drawn into the competing with the
被卷入与……的竞争
Joneses scenario because they associate
琼斯一家的情况是因为他们彼此关联
with other people have large incomes and
其他人收入都很高，
they're all driving a certain car,
他们都开着同一款车。
living in a certain neighborhood,
居住在某个社区，
sending their kids to certain schools
把孩子送到某些学校
and that probably becomes very hard to
这可能会变得非常困难。
disengage with and making it perhaps
脱离并使其可能
even less likely that they are going to
他们更不可能这样做
decide to spend a large portion of their
决定花费大部分时间
income on buying their freedom. Whereas
他们用所得收入换取了自由。然而
the people who make less money probably
收入较低的人可能
don't have those same social pressures
没有同样的社会压力
and are more readily able to do it.
而且他们更容易做到这一点。
So starting from humble beginnings is no
所以从卑微的起点开始并非不可能
obstacle and that's was the point of
障碍，而这正是问题的关键所在。
doing Pathfinders.
进行探路者活动。
&gt;&gt; Interesting.
有趣的。
&gt;&gt; It does track that. I think the
它确实会追踪到这一点。我认为
goalposts continue to move in different
目标不断变化
ways and
方式和
&gt;&gt; yeah,
是的，
&gt;&gt; I guess you go from competing to the
我想你会从竞争走向……
Joneses to competing with the size of
琼斯一家与规模庞大的公司竞争
someone else's yacht, which is all
别人的游艇，仅此而已
slippery slopes to bad places
滑向坏境的危险斜坡
&gt;&gt; or your own or your own demons
或你自己的心魔
as we talked about earlier, right?
就像我们之前讨论的那样，对吧？
&gt;&gt; Yeah. You mentioned a word in there as
是的。你提到了里面的一个词，
well. You mentioned I think you were
出色地。你提到过，我想你是
talking about your friend Tom. Tom had a
你在谈论你的朋友汤姆。汤姆有一个
divorce.
离婚。
&gt;&gt; Multiple divorces. Yeah.
多次离婚。是的。
&gt;&gt; I
我
&gt;&gt; which is bad for [clears throat] your
这对你的身体不好（清嗓子）
wealth.
财富。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. I didn't real I didn't I didn't
是的。我没有，我真的没有，我真的没有
realize this cuz I've never been through
我意识到这一点是因为我从未经历过。
one before. Um I spoke to James Ston on
前一个。嗯，我和詹姆斯·斯顿谈过了。
the show who's a divorce lawyer who kind
节目里那个离婚律师，真是个好人。
of opened my eyes to it. But actually I
它让我对此有了更深的认识。但实际上我
had a private conversation with a friend
和朋友进行了一次私下谈话
here in New York City, I'd say a couple
在纽约市，我想说有几个
of months ago who's going through a
几个月前，谁正在经历
divorce and he he sat me down and he
离婚后，他让我坐下，然后他
talked me through the specific
他详细地给我讲解了具体细节。
consequences of of divorce that he's
离婚的后果是他面临的
going through.
正在经历。
&gt;&gt; He said to me, he's a very successful
他告诉我，他非常成功。
person. I reckon he's probably worth 500
人。我估计他大概值500美元。
million, right? He said the divorce
百万，对吧？他说离婚
proceedings have now dragged on for five
诉讼程序至今已持续五天。
or 6 years. So I'm I'm having to go and
或6年。所以我不得不走了
see lawyers all the time. And he said to
经常见到律师。他说
me as well that he is paying for her
我也知道他是在为她付钱。
lawyer which I was I didn't really
我当时是一名律师，但我其实并不这么认为。
understand. But he was like no I have to
理解。但他却说不，我必须……
also cover her lawyer costs because you
你还要承担她的律师费，因为你
know I'm the the bread winner so she
她知道我是家里的经济支柱，所以她
doesn't have money so I'm covering her
她没钱，所以我替她付钱。
lawyer costs which is what I have to do.
律师费，这是我必须要做的。
And he said the law firm have gone from
他说，这家律师事务所已经从
being a very very small practice in
是一家规模非常非常小的诊所
those six years. Now they have a massive
那六年。现在他们拥有庞大的
building and he goes, "I know it's my
大楼，然后他说：“我知道这是我的。”
money. I bought it. I [laughter] bought
钱。我买了。我（笑）买了
it."
它。”
&gt;&gt; He literally is like, "I have paid for
他简直就像在说：“我已经付过钱了。”
her lawyer and now they're doing really
她的律师，现在他们真的在做
really well and they're milking this
他们做得非常好，而且正在充分利用这一点。
this case. They're drawing it out
这个案例。他们正在拖延时间。
because they have no incentive to this
因为他们没有这样做的动机。
to this ending." Yeah.
到此为止。” 是的。
&gt;&gt; So he's like, "I've spent tens of
所以他就说：“我已经花了数十万……”
millions on her lawyer who is basically
她花了数百万美元聘请律师，而这位律师基本上
dragging me. Um, and now they've got
拖着我。嗯，现在他们有了
this massive building." What else did he
这座巨大的建筑。”他还做了什么？
say to me? He said, "Because some of my
跟我说？他说：“因为我的一些
assets are subjective in value, like my
资产的价值是主观的，就像我的
company, her lawyer [laughter] is
公司，她的律师[笑声]是
inflating the price of my assets because
因为抬高了我的资产价格
she's going to get half of whatever they
她将得到他们所得的一半。
can convince a judge my assets are
能否说服法官我的资产是
worth." So he, you know, for example,
值得。”所以他，你知道，例如，
his business might be worth 100 million,
他的生意可能价值1亿美元，
but the lawyer is making the case to the
但律师正在向……陈述案情
judge that it's worth 500 million so
判断它的价值是5亿美元。
that she gets 250 million. He also said
她获得了2.5亿。他还说
to me,
大部头书，
&gt;&gt; which really isn't there,
实际上并不存在这种情况。
&gt;&gt; which really he doesn't have, right? And
他其实并没有，对吧？和
then he was saying to me, he goes, you
然后他对我说，他说，你
know, I bought this particular stock.
我知道，我买入了这支股票。
&gt;&gt; So he is, I'm sorry to interrupt you,
没错，他就是。不好意思打断一下。
but now he's forced to fight it.
但现在他被迫与之抗争。
&gt;&gt; He's fighting.
他在战斗。
&gt;&gt; It's not like he could just say, okay,
他不可能就这么简单地说，好吧，
she can have half.
她可以分到一半。
&gt;&gt; Yeah.
是的。
&gt;&gt; Because this is a judgment
因为这是一项判决。
that is going to create a a an
这将创造一个
obligation on his part for assets that
他对资产负有义务
don't actually exist.
实际上并不存在。
&gt;&gt; So it's more than half.
所以超过了一半。
&gt;&gt; She could end up taking 60 70. And the
她最终可能会拿下60到70分。
other thing he said to me, which was
他还跟我说了另一件事，那就是
quite sad, he was like, you know, I was
他当时挺难过的，你知道，我当时
one of the f He was one of the early
其中之一 他是早期的
investors in a big company that we all
我们都是这家大公司的投资者
know. and um he said to me, I bought
知道。然后，他对我说，我买了
that stock 15 20 years ago. It's
那支股票是15到20年前的。它是
actually quite emotional to him that he
实际上，他对此非常激动。
was so early in back in the company and
当时我刚回到公司不久，
now he's forced to sell that. So he has
现在他被迫卖掉了那件东西。所以他有
to liquidate investments he made 20
为了清算他20年前进行的投资
years ago because again she's entitled
几年前，因为她又一次觉得自己有资格这么做了。
to half
一半
&gt;&gt; and that'll be a huge tax hit.
这将造成巨大的税收损失。
&gt;&gt; A huge tax hit,
巨额税收打击
&gt;&gt; right? And I think some people don't
正确的？我觉得有些人并不这么认为。
realize that wealthy people can
意识到富人可以
get a loan against that stock without
无需抵押股票即可获得贷款
ever having to sell it.
永远不必卖掉它。
&gt;&gt; So he's probably, if he's wrong, he's
所以，如果他错了，那他很可能……
probably got a big loan against that
可能用那东西作抵押贷了一大笔款。
stock,
库存，
&gt;&gt; right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; Probably a 50% loan. So, just for anyone
可能是50%的贷款。所以，仅供参考
that doesn't understand this, because I
他不理解这一点，因为我
only understood this in the last couple
直到最近几个月才明白这一点
years where where I started doing
那些年开始做这件事的岁月
similar things, is if the stock is worth
类似的情况是，股票是否值
a h 100red million, he can get 50
如果他有1亿，他可以得到50
million tax-free from a bank just by
从银行获得数百万免税额
keeping that stock there and really
把那些库存留在那里，真的
never have to pay it back because it's
永远不用偿还，因为它是
such a great stock. Um, and it was also
这是一支很棒的股票。嗯，而且也是
just looking in his face and just seeing
看着他的脸，就能看到
the stress and the toll of having to go
不得不去旅行带来的压力和负担
to court all the time and fight this
一直上法庭，为此抗争到底。
thing for six or seven years that I
这件事持续了六七年，我一直都在做。
thought, wow, we we give people
心想，哇，我们给人们带来什么？
financial advice all the time about the
一直都有关于财务建议
best stocks to pick or invest in index
最佳股票选择或投资指数
funds. We don't talk enough about the
资金。我们谈论得还不够多
how divorce can just destroy your life.
离婚如何彻底摧毁你的生活。
&gt;&gt; You know, you have to be so careful in
你知道，你必须非常小心。
choosing your spouse. I've had push back
选择你的配偶。我遇到了阻力
on that and people say, "Well, then
人们对此表示：“好吧，那么……”
you're choosing your spouse is not a
你选择配偶这件事本身并不重要。
financial decision. It's, you know, it's
财务决策。你知道，就是这样。
emotional, it's romantic, it's well,
感人的，浪漫的，嗯，
yeah, it's all those things, but it you
是的，它包含了所有这些因素，但是如果你
better take finance into account for all
最好将所有财务因素都考虑在内。
the reasons that we're discussing." This
我们正在讨论的原因。”
also, by the way, loops us back to an
顺便一提，这又把我们带回到了……
earlier part of our conversation where
在我们之前对话的一部分中
does money buy happiness? Does, you
金钱能买到幸福吗？是吗？
know, being richer,
要知道，富有之后，
is that always necessarily better? Well,
那样就一定更好吗？出色地，
this guy is more of a target because of
这个人更容易成为攻击目标，因为……
his wealth than he would be if he were.
如果他还在世，他的财富会比现在更多。
So, is his money really making him
所以，他的钱真的让他赚到了钱吗？
happier at this point in his life? Yeah,
他现在的生活更快乐了吗？是的，
probably not so much, you know.
可能不会那么夸张，你知道的。
&gt;&gt; You know, and he's he's going to be fine
你知道，他会没事的。
either way, like sure, you know, um
总之，当然，你知道，嗯
which is a point worth saying of nuance,
这是一个值得一提的细微差别。
but also and the other point of nuance
但还有另一点细微差别
worth saying is that
值得一提的是……
&gt;&gt; he's going to be fine financially, but
他的经济状况不会有问题，但是
emotionally it's he's still going to go
情感上，他仍然会离开。
and she's probably going through it too
她可能也正在经历这一切。
on the other side.
在另一边。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. [laughter] And the other point of
是的。 [笑声] 另一点是
nuance here is that she did raise the
这里的细微差别在于，她确实提出了……
four or five the the three or four kids
四五个，那三四个孩子
&gt;&gt; while he was off building the business
在他忙于发展业务的时候
for, you know, 20 odd years. So, one
你知道，差不多有二十多年了。所以，一个
could argue that he wouldn't have that
可以辩称他不会那样做。
wealth without her being at home to look
她不在家，却拥有了财富，无需照看。
after the kids and she'd made huge
孩子们出生后，她赚了很多钱。
sacrifices to her own career,
她为了自己的事业做出了牺牲，
&gt;&gt; right?
正确的？
&gt;&gt; So, you know, there's balance. But I I
所以，你知道，凡事都要讲究平衡。但我
just think with um
想想嗯
James Ston said to me, even if you don't
詹姆斯·斯通对我说，即使你不
get a prenup,
签婚前协议，
there's still a prenup. You either use
还有一份婚前协议。你要么使用
the government's prenup,
政府的婚前协议，
&gt;&gt; which is
即
&gt;&gt; or you create your own,
或者你可以自己创作，
&gt;&gt; or you create your own. Either way,
或者你可以自己创作。无论哪种方式，
there's a prenup.
有婚前协议。
&gt;&gt; Absolutely.
绝对地。
&gt;&gt; Do you want to let some judge decide
你想让法官来决定吗？
&gt;&gt; or do you want to be intentional before
或者你想事先有意识地考虑一下？
you get married with your partner about
你和你的伴侣结婚大约
how things will be split?
如何分配？
&gt;&gt; And even when I think about my partner
即使当我想到我的伴侣时，我也会这样想。
at the moment, and we're probably going
目前是这样，我们可能要走了
to get married soon.
即将结婚。
&gt;&gt; Congratulations.
恭喜。
&gt;&gt; Thank you. I haven't proposed just yet,
谢谢。我还没求婚呢。
but I'm working on it. Don't tell her
但我正在努力。别告诉她
that.
那。
&gt;&gt; We We just let the secret out.
我们只是不小心把秘密说漏嘴了。
&gt;&gt; She doesn't She doesn't WATCH THIS
她不看这个
ANYWAY. [laughter]
反正。 [笑声]
&gt;&gt; Someone's going to do
有人会这么做
&gt;&gt; Wait a second. But I'm on this time, so
稍等片刻。但我现在在线，所以
this is the one episode she's going to
这是她唯一会出演的一集
watch.
手表。
&gt;&gt; True.
真的。
&gt;&gt; Well, I'm very fortunate as if this
嗯，我真是太幸运了，如果……
spring I will have been m married 44
春天的时候，我将结婚44年了。
years.
年。
&gt;&gt; Damn.
该死。
&gt;&gt; And [clears throat] I I tell people I I
然后（清嗓子）我告诉人们我
married my wife out of the gate. Why
我一出道就娶了我老婆。为什么
wait? Do you have a framework for
等待？您是否有相关的框架？
choosing the person or for sustaining
选择这个人或维持
for 44 years? Cuz I'm what, six, seven
44年？因为我才六七岁吧。
years in with my girlfriend, but you got
我和女朋友在一起好几年了，但是你却……
44 years in.
44 年了。
&gt;&gt; Funny story about that is people used to
关于这件事有个有趣的故事，那就是人们过去常常
ask me, did you and Jane sit down and
问问我，你和简有没有坐下来谈过？
discuss money before make sure you were
在讨论金钱之前，请确保你已了解相关信息。
on the same page financially before you
在你之前，财务方面要保持一致。
got married? [snorts] And I always used
结婚了吗？ [嗤笑] 我一直都用
to say, you know, it's a great idea. You
也就是说，你知道，这真是个好主意。你
should do that. But no, we never did
应该这样做。不，我们从来没有这样做过。
that. I just I just got lucky. you know,
那。我只是运气好而已。你知道，
we never talked about it, but as it
我们从未谈论过这件事，但正如它
happens, we got married and we were
事情就是这样，我们结婚了，然后我们就……
very, very compatible financially, which
在财务方面非常非常契合，
we are, but just got lucky. Well, I told
我们是，但只是运气好。嗯，我告诉过
that story in front of her one time and
她曾经听过那个故事，
she leaned back in her chair and she
她向后靠在椅子上，然后
said, "What are you talking about? On
他说：“你在说什么？”
our first date, you said to me, you need
第一次约会时，你对我说，你需要
to be saving 50% of your income." You
把收入的50%存起来。”
said, "What do you mean we never talked
他说：“什么意思？我们从来没说过话？”
about money?"
关于钱的事？
I guess that's such a natural part of my
我想这大概是我性格中非常自然的一部分吧。
persona. I didn't even remember doing
角色。我甚至都不记得自己做过什么了。
it.
它。
&gt;&gt; Interesting. [laughter]
有趣的。 [笑声]
[snorts]
[嗤笑]
&gt;&gt; My last question for you is about
我最后一个问题是关于
regret.
后悔。
You said you're 75.
你说你75岁了。
&gt;&gt; I am.
我是。
&gt;&gt; What are your biggest regrets?
你最大的遗憾是什么？
&gt;&gt; So, I I think regrets are are tricky and
所以，我觉得后悔是很棘手的事情。
and I will I'll answer your question
我会回答你的问题
directly and it's a couple of things
直接地，而且是两件事。
that or at least one thing that occurs
或者至少发生过这样一件事。
to me that might be surprising.
对我来说，这可能有点出乎意料。
The reason they're tricky is because
它们之所以棘手，是因为
there is an assumption like you re you
这里有一个假设，比如你是你
regret doing A and you think if only I'd
后悔做了A，你会想如果我当初……
done B, things would be better. But you
如果按照B方案来做，情况会好得多。但是你
don't know that that's true. But you
我不知道那是否属实。但是你
might say, "Boy, I regret starting that
可能会说：“唉，我真后悔开始那件事。”
company that failed because it was a
这家公司倒闭是因为它……
failure." Well, yeah, but it led to
失败。”嗯，是的，但这导致了
something much bigger. You learned so
更大的东西。你学到了这么多
much. Now maybe if you'd said instead of
很多。也许如果你当时说的是……
starting that company that failed, maybe
创办那家失败的公司，也许吧。
I took this highpaying job and and I
我接受了这份高薪工作，而且
worked my way up through the corporate
我一步步晋升到公司高层
organization. And you'd be saying there,
组织。然后你会说，
you know, you'd be sitting at some high
你知道，你会坐在很高的位置上。
executive level in this corporation and
这家公司的管理层
looking back and saying, "Wow, am I glad
回首往事，不禁感叹：“哇，我真高兴！”
I didn't do that startup that failed,
那家失败的创业公司不是我创办的。
right?" And yet you're so much further
对吧？”然而你却远远走远了。
ahead now than if you So who knows? Who
现在比你领先，所以谁知道呢？ WHO
knows what choice you made that appears
知道你做出了什么选择
to be the wrong choice as to whether it
是否是错误选择
really was. Maybe it was exactly right.
确实如此。也许结果完全正确。
Maybe things would have turned out
或许事情会朝着另一个方向发展。
better, maybe they wouldn't. So, I'm
或许他们不会。所以，我是
very hesitant to look back on. There are
非常不愿意回顾过去。有
many things I can look back on and say,
有很多事情我可以回顾并说：
"Gee, I do wonder what if I'd gone down
“哎呀，我真想知道如果我当时下去会怎么样。”
the right path instead of the left path.
选择正确的道路而不是左边的道路。
What would that have looked like?" But
那会是什么样子呢？”
there's no guarantees it would look
不能保证它看起来会怎样。
better and my life has been pretty damn
情况好多了，我的生活也相当不错。
good. So, in that sense, I have no
好的。所以，从这个意义上讲，我没有
regrets.
遗憾。
Two regrets I do have, very personal
我有两件非常私人的遗憾。
regrets. I don't I've never shared these
遗憾。我没有，我从来没有分享过这些
publicly.
公开地。
When I was a kid,
当我还是个孩子的时候，
my father was a very handy guy. He loved
我父亲是个非常能干的人。他爱
building things, working on the house,
建造东西，修缮房屋，
that kind of stuff.
诸如此类的事情。
I was not that kind of kid. And I don't
我不是那种孩子。我没有
know, I was eight or 10 years old at one
我知道，我当时大概八岁或十岁。
point. And for my birthday or Christmas,
观点。而我的生日或圣诞节礼物，
I don't remember, he brought me a bought
我不记得了，他给我带了一个买的
me a jigsaw, which is a for people who
给我一副拼图，这是给那些
don't know, it's a it's an electric saw.
不知道，这是一台电锯。
It's got a little blade. It goes up and
它有个小刀片。它上升，
allows you to cut wood and very fine
可以切割木材，而且非常精细。
kinds of patterns.
图案的种类。
Last thing in the world this kid wanted.
这是这孩子最不想要的东西。
And I let my dad know and he was crushed
我告诉了我爸爸，他非常伤心。
because for him
因为对他来说
it was the best gift he could possibly
这是他能送给别人的最好的礼物。
think of to give to an eight or
想想给八岁或
10year-old or whatever it was. And so
10岁左右吧。所以
one of the regrets and I give myself
其中一个遗憾是我对自己说的。
some grace cuz I was very young and
因为我当时年纪很小，所以请多多包涵。
reasonably you could expect that I
理所当然地，你可以预期我会
didn't have the maturity to deal with it
当时他没有足够的成熟度来处理这件事。
the way I would. But I I do regret
我会这么做。但我确实后悔
because I could see the pain in his face
因为我能看到他脸上的痛苦。
when I I kind of rejected that gift,
我当时有点拒绝了那份礼物。
right?
正确的？
And maybe that taught me a good lesson
也许这件事给我上了一堂很好的课。
in being more empathetic going forward.
今后要更有同理心。
So again, do I really regret it? Well, I
所以，我真的后悔吗？嗯，我
regret that I hurt my father, but I
我很后悔伤害了父亲，但我
learned something pretty valuable.
学到了很有价值的东西。
&gt;&gt; And you've let you've remembered that
你已经记住了这一点。
for 70 years.
70年。
&gt;&gt; I've remembered that for 70 years. Yeah.
这件事我记了70年了。是的。
Yeah. I've got similar stories of things
是的。我也有类似的经历。
ways I reacted as a kid.
我小时候的反应方式。
&gt;&gt; I think most people do.
我想大多数人都会这么想。
&gt;&gt; You know, yeah, it sucks.
是啊，真糟糕。
&gt;&gt; And then my second one, and this is even
然后是我的第二个，而且这个甚至更糟。
bigger. [clears throat] I was 24 when my
大。 [清嗓子] 我24岁的时候
dad died
父亲去世了
and he died of emphyma
他死于肺气肿
and [clears throat]
然后[清了清嗓子]
slow lingering death. He died in the
缓慢而痛苦的死亡。他死于
hospital.
医院。
And
和
the night before he died, the day before
在他去世的前一天晚上
he died, I was visiting him and um he
他去世了，我去探望他的时候，嗯……
was sitting on the edge of the bed
他坐在床边
and he said to me, "Uh,
他对我说：“呃，
I'm going to die now.
我即将死去。
You know, I'm I'm going to die tonight."
你知道吗，我今晚就要死了。
Turns out, of course, he was right. He
事实证明，他是对的。他
did. That was the night he died.
做过。那天晚上他就去世了。
And instead of recognizing that
而他们却没有意识到这一点。
this was a moment where
这是一个……的时刻
he wanted to talk to his son about this
他想和儿子谈谈这件事。
this probably the most momentous event
这可能是最重大的事件
that any of us will ever face.
我们每个人都将面临的挑战。
Right? Instead of recognizing that,
正确的？相反，他们却没有意识到这一点。
I went to the typical trope of, "Oh,
我使用了典型的套路：“哦，
dad, don't don't talk like that. You
爸爸，别这样说话。你
you're not going to die. you got a long
你不会死的。你走了很长一段路
way to go. You're going to be fine. I
干得好。你会没事的。我
went to all that [__]
都去参加那些破事了。
instead of just recognizing whether he
而不仅仅是判断他是否
was right or wrong
对还是错
[clears throat] that
[清嗓子]
he was facing a momentous thing and
他正面临着一件意义重大的事情，
[snorts and clears throat] he didn't
[嗤笑一声，清了清嗓子] 他没有
want to hear
想听
don't don't think about that think more
别想那么多，多想想。
positively. He he wanted to share with
肯定地。他想与……分享
his son
他的儿子
what he was facing.
他所面临的挑战。
And I regret that I wasn't there for him
我后悔当时没能陪在他身边。
in that moment.
那一刻。
But I regret that I didn't get to
但我很遗憾没能……
experience that with him in that moment.
在那一刻，和他一起体验这一切。
So that's my biggest.
这就是我最大的困扰。
&gt;&gt; I can still see it still in your face.
我仍然能从你的脸上看出来。
That was 50 years ago.
那是50年前的事了。
&gt;&gt; Is there a reason why you think in that
你这么想是有什么原因吗？
moment you didn't
你没有的那一刻
want to go in that direction with him?
你想和他一起朝那个方向走吗？
&gt;&gt; Was it a matter of what I wanted? Cuz
这是我意愿的问题吗？库兹
it's not like I considered
我并没有考虑过这个问题。
[clears throat]
[清嗓子]
I can either blow it off, which is what
我可以置之不理，就是这样。
I did, or embrace it and go there with
我这么做了，或者接受它，然后一起去那里。
him. I I didn't even think that way.
他。我根本没往那方面想。
It's not like
并非如此
it's not like I made the wrong choice. I
我并没有做出错误的选择。我
wasn't mature enough to recognize there
当时还不够成熟，没能意识到这一点。
was a choice. I wasn't mature enough to
这是一种选择。我当时还不够成熟
recognize
认出
the real dynamic of what was happening.
事情的真实动态。
&gt;&gt; And for that you deserve grace.
为此，你值得被宽恕。
&gt;&gt; Thank you. And I agree with that. But I
谢谢。我同意这一点。但我
still regret it because how much better
仍然后悔，因为这样好太多了。
for both of us would it have been
对我们俩来说，那会是……
if I had recognized it? JL, we have a
如果我认出来了呢？ JL，我们有一个
closing tradition on this podcast where
本播客的结尾传统是……
the last guest leaves a question for the
最后一位客人留下了一个问题。
next.
下一个。
&gt;&gt; What is something that you think is true
你认为什么是真的
that you haven't yet been able to
你还没能做到
validate? I think at at this point in my
证实？我认为在这一点上，我的
life, I'm I feel pretty comfortable
生活，我感觉很舒服
about what I think is true. Right? So,
关于我认为的真相。正确的？所以，
I'm not sure this answers the question,
我不确定这是否回答了这个问题。
but uh
但是呃
but a good example is I am pretty sure
但一个很好的例子是，我很确定
that there is no afterlife,
没有来世，
right? I I have a high degree of
正确的？我拥有高度的……
confidence to that. But of course, as
对此我充满信心。当然，作为
the song once said, we never know by
这首歌曾经唱道，我们永远不会知道
living and only our dying will tell. And
只有活着，只有死亡才能告诉我们答案。和
I am very curious about death. I am very
我对死亡非常好奇。我非常
curious as to
好奇的是
what is on the other side, if anything.
另一边是什么？如果有的话。
So, in a perverse way, I guess I'm I am
所以，从某种扭曲的角度来看，我想我就是我。
looking forward to my death, right? I I
期待死亡，对吧？我 我
don't want to get there too soon. I
不想太快到达那里。我
mean, I'm as long as I'm mentally and
我的意思是，只要我的精神状态良好，我就能一直这样下去。
physically capable, I'm happy to
如果身体条件允许，我很乐意
continue living. Thank you very much.
继续活下去。非常感谢。
But I do have a great curiosity about
但我确实对……非常好奇。
death, and I'm almost 100% sure that
死亡，我几乎百分之百确定
when I'm dead, that's just it. It's
我死后，一切就都结束了。它是
over.
超过。
But I'm curious, and it'll be
但我很好奇，而且会是
interesting if I die, and it's like,
如果我死了，那就太有趣了，感觉就像……
whoops. You know, it's like, oh, there
哎呀。你知道，感觉就像，哦，那里
is a guy with a white beard and
是一个留着白胡子的男人，
okay, I'll just show myself out. Thank
好的，那我这就走。感谢
you very much.
非常感谢。
&gt;&gt; [laughter]
[笑声]
&gt;&gt; There was one last question I wanted to
我还有一个问题想问。
ask you which is kind of just about the
问问你，这其实就是关于……
subject of happiness. Again at 75 years
幸福的主题。 75岁高龄
old you have a retrospective clarity
年纪大了，你就能回顾过往，看得更清楚。
that I don't yet have on what actually
但我目前还没有关于实际情况的答案。
mattered.
很重要。
What actually matters?
真正重要的是什么？
&gt;&gt; Nothing.
没有什么。
Nothing really matters ultimately.
归根结底，一切都无关紧要。
&gt;&gt; Yeah. I think
是的。我认为
that's kind of like asking what's the
这有点像问什么是……
meaning of life, right?
这就是人生的意义，对吧？
And I don't think there is a meaning to
我不认为这有什么意义
life when you look at the scale of the
当你审视生命的规模时……
universe, the scale of the cosmos.
宇宙，宇宙的尺度。
The concept that
这一概念
we as individuals bear some meaning
我们作为个体，都具有某种意义。
seems to me to be silly. Human beings
我觉得这很愚蠢。人类
have been around for I don't know two
已经存在了两年左右了，我也不知道。
300,000 years depending on when you
30万年，取决于你何时……
define homo sapiens. I mean that's
定义智人。我的意思是，那是
that's a infantestibly small smudge of
那只是婴儿时期极其微小的污渍。
time
时间
in that has happened already and that
这件事已经发生了，而且
will happen in the future even if humans
即使人类
last for another few million years. It
还能持续几百万年。它
will be an infinitely
将会是一个无限的
tiny bit of time against this huge
这点时间对抗这巨大的挑战
cosmic universe and our individuality
宇宙与我们的个体性
within that is infantessimally small and
其中非常小，如同婴儿一般
I think there's some great meaning
我认为这其中蕴含着深刻的意义。
behind that seems to be to be the height
其背后似乎是高度
of arrogance. So I think that if you go
傲慢。所以我觉得如果你去
through life and you treat people pretty
一生中，你待人友善。
well and you have a a pretty good good
嗯，你有一个相当不错的……
run of it, I think you've done well. I
我觉得你做得很好。我
don't but I don't think there's
不，但我认为没有。
something profound in that.
这其中蕴含着深刻的意义。
&gt;&gt; So So what is the point then? Is there a
那么，重点是什么呢？是否有
point? Is that the real question?
观点？这才是真正的问题吗？
&gt;&gt; There is no point. I mean the the point
毫无意义。我的意思是重点
is we happen to be here and it can be a
如果我们碰巧在这里，这可能是一个
good fun ride. It can be a very
非常有趣的旅程。这可能是非常
difficult ride depending on what you
旅程是否艰难取决于你
make of it and in some cases depending
制作它，在某些情况下取决于
on your circumstances. There have
根据你的情况而定。有
certainly been people in history that
历史上确实有一些人……
have born been born into circumstances
出生于某种境况
that
那
you know made it a a miserable existence
你知道，这让生活变得无比悲惨。
with no options out of it. I mean what's
别无选择。我的意思是，那是什么？
the meaning of that? You know, you and I
那是什么意思？你知道，你和我
and the vast majority of people
以及绝大多数人
listening to us, probably I venture to
听我们这么说，我大概可以这么说
say 100% of them have a lot more
假设他们中100%的人都拥有更多
autonomy over over how we can make our
自主权高于我们如何创造我们的
life. And
生活。和
will it have great meaning? No,
它会有重大意义吗？不，
ultimately not. But it's the only life
最终并非如此。但这是唯一的生活
you have and you may as well make the
你已经有了，不妨就这么做吧。
best of it.
其中最好的部分。
&gt;&gt; I actually listened to something last
我最后其实听了点东西。
night by a guy called Lucas Jones who is
晚上，一个名叫卢卡斯·琼斯的人……
an actor. Um, he has some great books.
一名演员。嗯，他有一些很棒的书。
He's also a poet as far as I'm aware.
据我所知，他也是一位诗人。
I'll link his books below. Um, but he he
我会在下面附上他的书的链接。嗯，但是他
made wrote this poem which I thought was
我写了这首诗，我认为是
quite related to that that I'm just
这与我刚才说的完全相关。
going to play for you cuz I think it's
我会为你演奏，因为我觉得是
kind of captures the essence as well of
某种程度上也抓住了本质。
what you're saying.
你说的。
&gt;&gt; He starts by saying, "I saw God on the
他首先说道：“我看见了上帝……”
train."
火车。”
&gt;&gt; Okay.
好的。
&gt;&gt; Saw God on the train.
在火车上看到了上帝。
&gt;&gt; A pretended I didn't. So, I sat far away
我假装不知道。于是，我坐在了很远的地方。
from the seat he was sitting in. And
从他所坐的座位上看去。
then he got up, I think probably to piss
然后他就起身了，我想大概是去小便吧。
and he noticed me there and said, "All
他注意到我，说道：“所有
right, what's this? What are you saying?
对，这是什么？你在说什么？
You hiding from me?" I said, "Ah, mate,
你在躲着我吗？”我说：“啊，伙计，
nah, just a comfy seat." And he looked
“不，只是个舒服的座位。”他看着
at me like I was a kid covered in
看着我，就像我是个浑身湿透的孩子一样
chocolate surrounded by rappers saying,
巧克力周围环绕着说唱歌手，他们说：
"Don't know what happened." And he go,
“不知道发生了什么事。”然后他就走了，
"It's coming then, mate. I've got a few
“那就快了，伙计。我还有一些……”
minutes. Tell me what's wrong, but don't
分钟。告诉我出了什么问题，但不要
[__] around with it." And it shocked me
“随便摆弄一下。”这让我很震惊。
then that it fit in one sentence. I
然后，它正好可以用一句话概括。我
said, "Just think heaven's a stupid
他说：“想想看，天堂就是个愚蠢的地方。”
incentive." Like what a [__] life for a
激励措施。” 就像，这算什么糟糕的人生啊
beautiful death. And those who are evil
美丽的死亡。还有那些邪恶的人
can suddenly repent like a killer or not
可能会像杀人犯一样突然忏悔，也可能不会
can live like a monster. Then right at
可以像怪物一样生活。然后就在
the end say, "I'm sorry, dear God, sir."
最后说：“对不起，亲爱的上帝，先生。”
And end up in heaven right there with my
最后，我和我的家人一起升入天堂。
nana. She's doing some knitting. He's
娜娜。她正在织毛衣。他是
waving a hammer. He's like, "Jesus god,
挥舞着锤子。他就像在说，“我的天哪，
what a horrible deal." And he goes,
“真是太糟糕了。”然后他继续说道，
"Yeah, it's [__] I know how you
“是啊，糟透了。我知道你……”
feel." I'm like, "Mate, you're the one
感觉。” 我心想，“兄弟，就是你了。”
spinning the wheel." And he goes,
他转动着轮盘。”然后他继续说道，
"Listen, I'll tell you a secret." All
“听着，我告诉你一个秘密。”全部
that stuff, mate. I didn't speak it.
就是那玩意儿，伙计。我没说过这种话。
Like the old joke says about liars and
就像那句关于说谎者的古老笑话所说……
men. If God wrote the book, why are you
男人。如果这本书是上帝写的，为什么是你写的？
holding the pen? Now, the rules I wrote,
手里拿着笔吗？现在，我制定的规则是：
I wrote on your heart. Truth I spoke,
我把字写在了你的心上。我说的是实话。
you've known from the start, be kind,
你从一开始就知道，要善良。
don't harm, isn't that hard. Heaven is
不要伤害别人，这很难吗？天堂是
just life if you're doing your part. You
只要你尽到自己的责任，生活就是如此。你
want white clouds and endless skies. Uh,
想要白云和无垠的天空。呃，
yeah. Look around. You don't have to
是的。环顾四周。你不必
die. I know it probably brings you some
死。我知道这可能会给你带来一些好处
pain to think of the dead as just dust
想到逝者化为尘埃，令人心痛。
in a grave. But humans can't comprehend
在坟墓里。但人类无法理解
it when I say life is the cloud and
当我说生活就像云一样时，它就变成了这样。
death is the rain. And I got to my stop
死亡是雨。我到站了。
and felt kind of mad. Not sure he
我当时有点生气。不确定他
answered the questions I had. Then I
他解答了我的疑问。然后我
looked up and saw the sun rising. Said,
抬头望去，只见太阳升起。说，
"You're looking for heaven, but you're
“你在寻找天堂，但你……”
the one hiding."
躲藏起来的那个人。
[laughter]
[笑声]
&gt;&gt; LJ, thank you. Thank you for writing
LJ，谢谢你。感谢您的来信。
these incredible books that I highly
这些我强烈推荐的精彩书籍
recommend anybody who is on their own
推荐给所有独居人士
journey to financial freedom and is
通往财务自由的旅程是
looking for a free life, a financial
追求自由的生活，追求财务自由
independence or just independence from
独立，或者仅仅是独立于
one's own tormenting psychology should h
一个人自身令人痛苦的心理应该……
should uh should buy this book. The
应该……应该买这本书。这
simple path to wealth has been an
通往财富的简单途径一直是
absolute smash hit for um understandable
绝对大获成功，嗯，可以理解。
reasons once you read it. Sold many
读完之后你就会明白了。卖出了很多
millions of copies from what I
据我所知，销量已达数百万份。
understand, more than a million copies
据了解，超过一百万份
at least. And I highly recommend
至少。我强烈推荐
everybody goes and starts with this book
每个人都从这本书开始读起。
and then picks up Pathfinders. I'm going
然后他又玩起了《探路者》。我要去
to link both of these books below. And
下面附上这两本书的链接。和
there is a third book, it's slightly
还有第三本书，稍微有点
smaller, called How I Lost Money in Real
篇幅较短，名为《我如何在现实生活中赔钱》。
Estate Before It Was Fashionable, A
在庄园风靡之前，
Cautionary Tale. Um, I'm going to link
警示故事。嗯，我要链接一下。
all of them below. And if anybody else
以下全部。如果还有其他人
wants to find more of your work, is
想找到你更多的作品，是
there anywhere else that they can get in
他们还能从哪里进去呢？
contact with you, read your work that I
联系你，阅读你的作品
should recommend? So probably the
应该推荐吗？所以大概是
easiest thing is the blog which is
最简单的办法就是写博客。
jlinsnh
jlinsnh
at uh or.com and uh you know you'll find
在 uh or.com 上，你知道你会找到
a lot of my writing. I don't write on
我写的大部分东西。我不写
the blog too much anymore but the
博客已经看得太多了，但是
material that's there is evergreen. It's
那里的材料是常青材料。它是
the source material for the books that
这些书籍的素材来源是：
you were kind enough to share. Uh the
感谢您的分享。呃
last book the how I lost money in real
最后一本书讲述了我如何在现实生活中赔钱。
estate is if somebody wants to have a
遗产是指如果有人想要拥有……
laugh at my expense that's the book they
嘲笑我，这就是那本书的内容
want to pick up.
想去取。
&gt;&gt; Thank you for doing so much of what you
感谢你做了这么多。
do. Um, I know what the comments are
做。嗯，我知道评论是什么。
going to say already. They're going to
我已经打算说了。他们将要
be people talking about how soothing
人们都在谈论如何舒缓情绪
your voice is, and I [laughter] I happen
你的声音是，而我[笑声]碰巧
to I happen to agree. Thank you so much.
我恰好同意。太感谢了。
&gt;&gt; My pleasure. Thank you for having me.
我的荣幸。谢谢邀请。
&gt;&gt; If there's anything we need, it is
如果说我们有什么需要的话，那就是
connection, especially in the world
联系，尤其是在世界上
we're living in today. And that is
我们生活在当今时代。就是这样。
exactly why we created these
这正是我们创造这些的原因
conversation cards. Because on this
对话卡片。因为在这个
show, when I sit here with my guests and
节目中，当我与我的客人坐在这里时，
have those deep, intimate conversations,
进行那些深入、私密的对话，
this remarkable thing happens time and
这种奇妙的事情会随着时间的推移而发生。
time again. We feel deeply connected to
又一次。我们与……有着深厚的联系
each other. At the end of every episode,
彼此。每集结尾，
the guest I'm interviewing leaves a
我正在采访的嘉宾离开了
question for the next guest, and we've
下一个问题要问下一位嘉宾，我们已经……
turned them into these conversation
把它们变成了这些对话
cards, and we've added these twist cards
卡片，我们还添加了这些扭转卡片
to make your conversations even more
让你的对话更加精彩
interesting. And there are so many more
有趣的。还有更多呢。
twists along the way with the
一路上的曲折
conversation cards. This is the brand
对话卡片。这是品牌
new edition and for the first time ever,
新版本，并且有史以来第一次，
I've added to the pack this gold card,
我已将这张金卡加入卡包。
which is an exclusive question from me.
这是我个人提出的问题。
But I'm only putting the gold cards in
但我只放金卡进去。
the first run of conversation cards. So
第一批对话卡片。所以
get yours now before the limited edition
限量版即将发售，赶紧入手吧！
gold cards are all gone. Head to the
金卡全部都用完了。前往
link in the description below. [music]
链接在下方说明中。 [音乐]
&gt;&gt; [music]
[音乐]
[singing]
[歌唱]